<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine poems and meditations in two parts / written by William Williams ...</title>
            <author>Williams, William, b. 1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12529359</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12529359</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 952:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine poems and meditations in two parts / written by William Williams ...</title>
                  <author>Williams, William, b. 1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 42, [2], 59, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F. Redmayne for the author, and are to be sold by John Williams ... and John Crump ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: p. [2]-[6]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious poetry, English --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:1"/>
            <p>DIVINE POEMS AND MEDITATIONS.</p>
            <p>IN TWO PARTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> William Williams <hi>of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of</hi> Cornwall, <hi>Gent. when he was Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in the</hi> Kings-Bench, <hi>in the Sixty ſecond, and Sixty third year of his Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ponder my words, O Lord, conſider my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Redmayne</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>John Williams</hi> at the <hi>Crown,</hi> and <hi>John Crump</hi> at the <hi>Three Bibles</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED <hi>March the Seventh.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable Sir <hi>Francis Winnington</hi> Knight, Sollicitor General to His Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this preſent Parliament. And to Sir <hi>John King</hi> Knight, Sollicitor to His Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOble Gentlemen, your words ſpoken for me in the High Court of Chancery, the Firſt day of Trinity Term, 1675. were, like Apples of Gold in Pictures of Silver, they are fit to be Recorded to poſterity, to encourage other Worthy Perſons that now live and may ſucceed you, to be kind and take part to aſſiſt Priſoners, for they can be grateful (if ingenuous,) you little thought what you then ſpoke for me, would be the ſubject and occaſion of all theſe following Lines. The Firſt, I took it to be my duty to preſent to God as my Thanksgiving; And then to you
<pb facs="tcp:62740:3"/>(which bountifully rewarded and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged my gratitude.) This unexſpected mercy did ſo raiſe my contemplations, (which were formerly exerciſed in vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er fancies) 'twas God and you that raiſed my Meditations on more Diviner Poems, if there be any thing in them that be good, let God have the Glory, and you as his Inſtruments, and the for ever moſt thankful acknowledgments of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, to the infinite comfort of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my lodging in the Mint in <hi>South-wark,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 10. 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and obliged Servant. <hi>William Williams.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:3"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful <hi>Arthur Sprye</hi> Eſq; one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, for the County of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and a Member of this preſent Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>REnowned <hi>Homer,</hi> (for whom Seven Cities contended for the Honor of being the place of his Birth,) when he firſt betook himſelf to Poetry, thought himſelf obliged to expreſs his thankfulneſs to his Benefactors, and firſt to <hi>Mentor</hi> who took care of him when he had ſore eyes, and to his Maſter which brought him up in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and he gratefully requited <hi>Tychicus</hi> the Leather-ſeller, that received him into his Houſe.</p>
            <p>If I endeavor to imitate the worthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this darling of the Muſes, and render you my moſt hearty thanks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord to all ages, your ſo Generous, Free, and Bountiful love to me, and care of me when a Priſoner deſerted by my Kindred and
<pb facs="tcp:62740:4"/>Relations, not ſparing your pains in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and coſt on my occaſions, with your bounty to me other waies, (never to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) which hath ſet me ſometimes into Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of Gods great mercy to me, in raiſing me ſuch a Friend, that hath ſent me ſo many comforting Letters, which as ſo many Cordials have revived my ſad and drooping Spirits. And that you who are ſo eminently imployed in the publick, and have ſo many great affairs of your own, ſhould lay all aſide, and Travel, and expend on my occaſions, which did never, nor ever was in a capacity ſo highly to engage you. And all this done, when I was caſt down ſo low, when no ſatisfaction from me was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, your favors were then ſo clear, and continued without any reſerve to your ſelf. Your indefatigable pains in being the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Gods hands of ſetting me at liberty, which is to me the beginning of a new life.</p>
            <p>Should not theſe ſo eminent favors call me to gratitude, I were worſe than the beaſt that periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir.</hi> It hath not a little rejoyced my ſoul
<pb facs="tcp:62740:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>that God (in my old Old age) hath enabled me, (amid all this more than Three years cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity) to have ſomething of my own to preſent you with (though not worthy of you.) They are my Two laſt years exerciſes by way of Meditations in the <hi>Kings-Bench.</hi> They were for the moſt part written in the Houſe, But Corrected, and Enlarged in the Rules. I beſeech you accept them as the moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acknowledgment of your ſo much Care, Pains, Travel, and Expence for me. It is the only requital that ever I can be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and that I can tell afterages that I can be thankful.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be moſt rude and ungrateful, if I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the favors which I have ſo chearfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Right Honorable Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful and many of my noble countrymen, and others, by whoſe bounty and favors I have bin ſupported in this my ſo long impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Most thankfully acknowledging their favors (eſpecially of ſome) which have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded far beyond my expectation and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my deſerts.</p>
            <p>Sir, I pray that you will take theſe papers
<pb facs="tcp:62740:5"/>with the author into your protection, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your favor, that God will continue his grace and favor to you, ſhall ever be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of my heart while I breath and remain.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ever obliged Servant</hi> William Williams.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:5"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is not unknown to many that have bin, and ſome that now are priſoners in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> in what a ſad, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate condition I was for many moneths after I came Priſoner to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable place finding my ſelf redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from ſo plentiful a condition, to the ſad calamities of a Priſon; neglected by my kindred, and relations, from whom I had moſt cauſe to expect comforts. And to add to my griefs, I was encountred with railing <hi>Rabſhecah's</hi> and curſing <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei's</hi> to the great diſcomfort of my ſoul.</p>
            <p>In Trinity term 1675 I was called by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> to anſwer a bill in chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, endeavoring to turn me over to the fleet for a contempt as the adverſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. It grieved me much to think of a remove, and renew a new place of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I not thinking my ſelf able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the court, as might be acceptable, did retain councel; But before I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, my councel went of, pretending he
<pb facs="tcp:62740:6"/>had buſineſs to attend the Parliament, then ſitting, So I was left to my ſelf. But it pleaſed God ſoon to ſupply that defect to my great advantage, by enclining the hearts and tongues of the eminent, and ever to be honored perſons, <hi>Sir Francis Winnington</hi> and <hi>Sir John King</hi> To improve the reaſons I then delivered, with ſo much pious and charitable zeal for me, againſt councel retained againſt me, that they got me an order for my return. And at another time enclined one Mr <hi>John Hearl</hi> a councel at law, and my noble Countryman in like manner, to defend my cauſe at the Rouls unknown to me, and without a fee, for which I make him this my thankful acknowledgment. Theſe ſo eminent mercys from God, and ſo great favors from perſons of ſo high place and parts, with whom I had never ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor ſeen their faces as I knew of, made me admire Gods great mercy to me a Priſoner, meerly upon principals of Honor and Charity.</p>
            <p>Theſe providences my Adverſary obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gods dealing with me ſtopt the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his proceeding, and the Matter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference
<pb facs="tcp:62740:6"/>is like to have a better compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and my Adverſary is become my friend. When I returned to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> I took it to be my duty to return thanks and praiſes to God for his ſo great a mercy never to be forgotten. The which I did in the manner as is hereunto annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which I hope God hath accepted of. For ſince which time I began to write theſe following meditations, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before did dare to adventure on ſuch ſubjects. But ſince I am never well nor at quiet with my ſoul, but when I am about ſuch exerciſes, and I was ſo far from helps, as it is well known that I had to many hindrances.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay to you that I preſent you with the fruits of idle hours, but of the beſt hours that ever I ſpent. For it hath ſet more gladneſs in my heart than when the Corn, and wine and oyl encreaſed.</p>
            <p>It may be that the reverend Clergy will be offended with me, for preſuming to take upon me to deſcant on Scriptures. I humbly beg their pardons. Yet I hope I have not abuſed any text that I have inſiſted on. But kept cloſe to the matter of it, without making any vain fictions and truly I had ſcarce any book but
<pb facs="tcp:62740:7"/>the bible. And I was without that too, until I complained of it, as one of my greateſt wants for my ſpiritual refreſhment to a very good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Madam Scawen</hi> who preſently ſent me a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Bible. And I was beholding to Mr <hi>Stretch</hi> the Miniſter of the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> which really is a very civil perſon to priſoners doing them any good offices that lies in his power; he lent me alſo Doctor <hi>Featleys</hi> Sermons. And from thence as in my dayly practice, and obſervations, as my fancy led me, I took ſome things to meditate on for my divertiſement. The which I hope they will charitably cenſure theſe weak exerciſes, and accept them not as coming from a colledg, but a Priſon. I have much hopes of their favors, for I have communicated ſome of theſe to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral good Divines, from whom I have had good encouragement, which I ſhall ever moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge.</p>
            <p>I believe, that there be ſome that will taxe me for too much boldneſs for coming forth in print, And condemn theſe as weak and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted. I am ſenſible enough of the weakneſs of them, and therefore they may ſave that Labor. But ſhould I be without reproof, I ſhould fare much better, than many far my betters, who cannot eſcape the tongues of ſuch carping <hi>Zoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus's,</hi> who have only wit to cenſure, and not to amend, and think nothing well done, becauſe they do it not, yet will quarrel at the private
<pb facs="tcp:62740:7"/>divertiſements of a poor Priſoner.</p>
            <p>Should I to add to the heat of their fiery tongues burn theſe papers, or let them rot by me, I am ſure it would do leſs good, than they will do now. For though they want the rethorical ſtreins of great learning, yet they are the plain and harmleſs exerciſes of an old man a Priſoner, that may have the good hap to meet with more charitable and courteous perſons, that will friendly accept them from a Priſoner under ſo long, and ſevere a Calamity.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Boanerges,</hi> or Sons of Thunder I ſhall not Court, but leave them to their carping diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. But you whoſe pious Charity will be pleaſed to take this little Babe into your hands, and diſpiſe it not, though born in a Priſon. It ſpeaks the language of the Scriptures. I have ſome eminent predeceſſors, and preſidents even from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and I hope I do ſhew the duty and honor, I have ever born to the doctrin and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> In which I was born and bread. And I have ever ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it to be my duty to defend it even in the worſt of times to my irreparable ruin, as is too viſible. Therefore I hope it will meet with more charitable, humble, and good diſpoſitions, that will friendly accept of and charitably paſs by a Priſoners failings. And if they may have the good fortune to find acceptance, It will give much ſatiſfaction for the pains taken by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your hearty well wiſhing friend <hi>William Williams.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 32.11.</hi>
                  </bibl> Whoſo putteth his truſt in the Lord, mercy embraceth him on every ſide.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:8"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION. <hi>A Priſoners thanksgiving, that was by</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>brought to the Chancery Bar (by one that he had truſted with his Eſtate) the firſt day of Trinity term, where having expreſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, it moved ſo much pitty, that it pleaſed God to raiſe to his aſſiſtance, Sir</hi> Francis Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington, <hi>and Sir</hi> John King <hi>moſt effectually to plead his cauſe, without ever being ſpoke to, or retained, meerly out of principles of pitty and charity, for which the Priſoner at his return to the Kings-Bench wrote as followeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>CAn I forget thy mercies Lord, this day,</l>
               <l>So freely ſhew'd me? can I make delay</l>
               <l>To give thee praiſe oh Lord, 'twas by thy power</l>
               <l>I ſpake ſo feelingly, that happy hour</l>
               <l>Wherein thou ſhewd'ſt thy goodneſs, Lord, 'twas thine</l>
               <l>All powerful providence, not art of mine,</l>
               <l>Thou didſt direct great councel to aſſiſt</l>
               <l>A priſoner poor, encountred in the liſt</l>
               <l>With other councel, whoſe deſign yet miſt me.</l>
               <l>Lord, thou didſt 'ope their mouths for to aſſiſt me,</l>
               <l>For which I ſhall for ever praiſe thy name,</l>
               <l>Too weak's my pen for to expreſs the ſame.</l>
               <l>Accept dear Lord, my thankful hearts expreſſion,</l>
               <l>That's fill'd with praiſes, let not the Tranſgreſſion</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:8"/>
               <l>Of my frail heart, be hindrance to declare</l>
               <l>Thy praſſes in a work ſo plous, rare</l>
               <l>That Lawyers which are men deſign'd for hire</l>
               <l>Should freely ſpeak, 'twas cauſe thou didſt inſpire</l>
               <l>Their hearts, and made them unto pitty bent,</l>
               <l>To plead the cauſe of the poor innocent;</l>
               <l>That was by wiles and promiſes ſeduc'd,</l>
               <l>Being aſſured much good ſhould be infus'd</l>
               <l>To me and mine. But, Lord, thou truly art</l>
               <l>The God of truth, and ſearcher of the heart.</l>
               <l>Thou know'ſt what cruel threats I have endur'd,</l>
               <l>That did expect relief, and be aſſur'd</l>
               <l>Of ſome kind uſage, but that I muſt ſee</l>
               <l>My whole dependance is alone on thee.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt ſtill by thy own Almighty power</l>
               <l>Preſerv'd me, to this very day and hour.</l>
               <l>Dear Lord, 'twas thou that doſt provide for me</l>
               <l>Means of ſupport, when preſt with miſery.</l>
               <l>Continue ſtill thy all preſerving power,</l>
               <l>Leave me not helpleſs in my lateſt hour;</l>
               <l>A waken ſtill in me a thankful heart,</l>
               <l>That from depending on thee, may not part,</l>
               <l>But let my hope be caſt on thee that can</l>
               <l>Preſerve me from the cruel rage of Man,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe projects are to ſtarve this body frail,</l>
               <l>Oh keep me, Lord, that they may not prevail.</l>
               <l>Thou that canſt bleſs the little ſtock of meal</l>
               <l>And by thy power art able to reveal</l>
               <l>VVonderful providences, to preſerve</l>
               <l>The weakeſt mortals, who in faith thee ſerve.</l>
               <l>Give me content, oh let me not repine</l>
               <l>At thy juſt dealings for thoſe ſins of mine.</l>
               <l>Pardon my youthful wandrings, aged faults,</l>
               <l>My many weakneſſes, and numerous halts,</l>
               <l>My crooked walks, oh let my ſad condition</l>
               <l>Excite a pious grief, for my tranſgreſſion</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:9"/>
               <l>Againſt thy ſacred name, let me implore</l>
               <l>Thy heavenly grace to help me, oh reſtore</l>
               <l>To me an humble heart, that may ſubmit</l>
               <l>To what thy knowing wiſedom ſhall think fit</l>
               <l>For me poor mortal, who am weak and frail</l>
               <l>VVhoſe only hopes in Chriſt is to prevail.</l>
               <l>Lord, waſh me in his blood, then ſhall I be</l>
               <l>Though black by nature yet made white by thee,</l>
               <l>And though I am in Priſon caſt full low,</l>
               <l>Raiſe me again good God, and now beſtow</l>
               <l>Thy abundant graces, let thy will be done</l>
               <l>I am reſolv'd thy will to wait upon,</l>
               <l>Until my change ſhall come, do not delay</l>
               <l>That happy hour, that I may ſee the day</l>
               <l>VVhen thou by death wilt perfectly reſtore me,</l>
               <l>Lord, let a priſoners ſighes now come before thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm <hi>86.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Shew ſome good token upon me for good, that they which hate me, may ſee it, and be aſhamed: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou Lord, haſt holpen me, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62740:9"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Phillippians Chap. 4. v. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>I know how to abound, and how to ſuffer need, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>DIvineſt Saint,</hi> there's few on Earth but thee</l>
                  <l>Have learnt contentment, a felicity</l>
                  <l>Beyond all Arts; th'Apoſtle only can</l>
                  <l>Approve himſelf the beſt contented Man.</l>
                  <l>A Leſſon which the World hath long forgot</l>
                  <l>To ſet in practice, (Men affect it not)</l>
                  <l>This is a thing unpleaſing to their taſt,</l>
                  <l>Therefore in ſad repining time they waſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were Heavens delightful Paths beſet with pleaſures</l>
                  <l>For Sence to revel in, our chiefeſt Treaſures</l>
                  <l>Would there be plac'd, our ſenſual hearts would be</l>
                  <l>Too full of Joy, in Earths felicity.</l>
                  <l>Were there no rubs, nor ſtops to make us faint,</l>
                  <l>Who would not be a Convert, and a Saint?</l>
                  <l>The Crown of Glory, it would truly be,</l>
                  <l>As the ſweet Garlands of Eternity:</l>
                  <l>But he that enters Heavenly bliſs muſt wear,</l>
                  <l>A Crown of Thornes e're he attain that Sphear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fond Worldlings are ſo vainly ſtufft with Pride,</l>
                  <l>That a Holy meekneſs can not abide,</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62740:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>Unleſs it carry pleaſing Pomp aloft;</l>
                  <l>Religious Meekneſs, it is ſeldom l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Preaching of Patience, it doth Clearly Show,</l>
                  <l>There are ſublime enjoyments which we owe</l>
                  <l>Due reverence to, and yet we will not learn</l>
                  <l>This holy Leſſon, fully to diſcern</l>
                  <l>Our vain repinings at the Almighties ways,</l>
                  <l>Who can caſt down, and in a moment raiſe</l>
                  <l>Our better fortunes; But th'Apoſtle here</l>
                  <l>Hath nobly learnt, for to Suſtain and bear</l>
                  <l>His pinching wants, ſans Murmurings or grudge</l>
                  <l>At his Corrections, thats a righteous Judge.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that hath bid us ſeek the heavenly glory,</l>
                  <l>Tells us that earthly things are tranſitory;</l>
                  <l>And after this vain Heathens, they do walk;</l>
                  <l>And ſhall we Chriſtians like the Heathens talk?</l>
                  <l>And have no higher proſpect, than this world</l>
                  <l>For which the Angels from the heavens were hurl'd?</l>
                  <l>Shall we lye groveling in this lower Sphear</l>
                  <l>Rowling our ſelves in Carnal pleaſures here,</l>
                  <l>Making morality our only bliſs</l>
                  <l>And have no other thoughts of Heaven than this?</l>
                  <l>Was it for this that the Eternal Lord</l>
                  <l>Bow'd the high Heavens, and came with free accord,</l>
                  <l>Leaving his Throne, to bring us unto glory?</l>
                  <l>Then let us ceaſe from things ſo Tranſitory;</l>
                  <l>And raiſe our ſouls unto ſublimer Joys,</l>
                  <l>For terrene pleaſures are but fooliſh Toys.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vain is that Man, which fooliſhly doth wrap</l>
                  <l>His chief felicity in natures Lap;</l>
                  <l>And all the dull enjoyments of his Sence</l>
                  <l>With care, and vehement Toyle, to fetch it thence:</l>
                  <l>Tell me then man, That doeſt in pleaſures ſwim,</l>
                  <l>And haſt the Cup with joy fil'd to the brim,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62740:10"/>
                  <l>Haſt thou forgot thy God, thy Guide, thy Maker?</l>
                  <l>Be not ſo ſtupid, leaſt thou be partaker</l>
                  <l>Of endleſs Torments, ſhould the Luminaries</l>
                  <l>Looſe their bright Luſters, that but ſeldom varies,</l>
                  <l>And put on purple Robes, that Direful ſight</l>
                  <l>Of bleeding planets, would thy ſoul affright;</l>
                  <l>Or if the air were turn'd into a ſtream</l>
                  <l>Of blood, by that moſt powerful hand Supream;</l>
                  <l>Or could thy deafned ear, but hear the blaſt</l>
                  <l>Of the laſt direful Trump, what ſpeedy haſt</l>
                  <l>wouldſt thou then make? &amp; be moſt fully bent</l>
                  <l>To check thy Fancy, poſting to repent?</l>
                  <l>Such things prodigious greatly would affright</l>
                  <l>The Bold'ſt prophaner, that took delight</l>
                  <l>In actions, Sacrilegeous wicked ways,</l>
                  <l>The memorie then of former ſinful days</l>
                  <l>Will fill the inner man, with diſmal fright,</l>
                  <l>And make the Sinner reſtleſs day, and night.</l>
                  <l>Oh man remember this! 'Tis truth alaſs</l>
                  <l>The enjoyments of the world are poor, and paſs</l>
                  <l>Away like empty aire, there's no fruition,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Dives</hi> like, we make a ſad petition.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So doth the vain voluptuous worldling laugh</l>
                  <l>At pure religion, and do vainly quaff,</l>
                  <l>Scorning the poor oppreſſed Suffering Man,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew him all the envious ſpight they can;</l>
                  <l>As though a pious life could not enjoy;</l>
                  <l>Some tides of pleaſure; but have ſtill annoy</l>
                  <l>His ſight's bemiſted, he can't yet deſcry</l>
                  <l>The expected hopes of bleſt eternity;</l>
                  <l>He thinks himſelf Secure, and free from ſtrife</l>
                  <l>And knowes no Joyes, but in this preſent life.</l>
                  <l>Did we but know, theſe rich rewards will fall</l>
                  <l>On the religious poor, to crown them all,</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62740:11"/>
                  <l>What happineſs attendeth on the Motion</l>
                  <l>Of ſuffering Saints, in their moſt pure devotion?</l>
                  <l>'Twould make us triumph in our low eſtate,</l>
                  <l>And be in love with hardſhip at this rate;</l>
                  <l>Imbracing poverty with a holy zeal,</l>
                  <l>To enjoy that bliſs, which we cannot reveal:</l>
                  <l>'Twould comfort in our very low eſtate,</l>
                  <l>When ſuffering by the cruel hand of fate</l>
                  <l>From Men enrag'd, but we are ſtill to learn</l>
                  <l>The Apoſtles rule, to wait, till the return</l>
                  <l>Which crowns, with bliſs, the patient waiting Soul,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill expects in faith without controul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet how hardly do we grief endure,</l>
                  <l>When ſmalleſt troubles do our ſouls inure</l>
                  <l>With ſo much paſſion, that we hardly can,</l>
                  <l>Bear the leaſt brunt of Scorne! ſo vain is man;</l>
                  <l>So ſenſleſs are we of Gods greateſt power,</l>
                  <l>Forgetful wretches, that even every hour</l>
                  <l>We cenſure, and accuſe thy providence,</l>
                  <l>Like faithleſs perſons, ſcarce enricht with ſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord ope our eyes, and make us plainly See</l>
                  <l>The worlds vain ſhews, Mans inſufficiency,</l>
                  <l>That empty air, the pleaſures here below,</l>
                  <l>Grant theſe Joyes that from thy preſence flow;</l>
                  <l>To theſe good Lord let our hearts ſtill ſtand bent,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall we evermore have full content.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62740:11"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Job 2.10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>In all this did not <hi>Job</hi> Sin with his Lips.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>WAs <hi>Job</hi> a ſtatue, was his noble heart</l>
                  <l>Impenetrable? could not Sorrows Smart</l>
                  <l>Move his ſo fixed Soul? nor yet Hells hate,</l>
                  <l>His ſo Strong bulwark conſcience penetrate?</l>
                  <l>Behold him then, mirror of patience,</l>
                  <l>Whom all the Legions could not fright him thence!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay he could breath divinity in groans,</l>
                  <l>Make ſighs his Muſick, and in ſacred tones,</l>
                  <l>Turn ſorrows into Sermons, and his pains</l>
                  <l>To pious Lectures, improving for gains</l>
                  <l>Even ſaddeſt ſufferings, and did never vent</l>
                  <l>The leaſt invective, from foul diſcontent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How wondrous is that ſoul, that is ſo fixt,</l>
                  <l>Valiant in conflict, and indeed not mixt</l>
                  <l>With baſe repinings, but can bear his Croſs,</l>
                  <l>And triumph in it, without ſence of loſs!</l>
                  <l>By ſuffering much humility hath taught</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Job</hi> patience, which with greateſt care he ſought</l>
                  <l>So nobly that it doth adorn his parts,</l>
                  <l>And makes them lovely, ev'n beyond all arts;</l>
                  <l>Like the Philoſophers ſtone, that with each touch</l>
                  <l>Turns all to gold, and doth the ſame enrich;</l>
                  <l>His very grave becomes a cabinet</l>
                  <l>Of precious duſt, the which is all beſet</l>
                  <l>With Saphires, like a Rock that ſtoutly braves</l>
                  <l>The raging Sea, and its tempeſtuous Waves:</l>
                  <l>Or like the morning Sun that ſhines moſt bright</l>
                  <l>After 't hath long bin clouded from our ſight,</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62740:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>And more transparent ſhines to the eye of ſence,</l>
                  <l>Attracting many muddy vapors hence.</l>
                  <l>For like the conquering palm, that ſtill doth flouriſh</l>
                  <l>Under its preſſures, which doe never nouriſh</l>
                  <l>His ſpreading limbs, into a full extent</l>
                  <l>Maugre the cloggs, and weights of puniſhment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Job</hi> theſe are but poor emblems of thy glory,</l>
                  <l>Like as the Lower Sphears are tranſitory,</l>
                  <l>Hurri'd with ſtorms, but ſtill thy high-born ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Like the true loadſtone, points the heavenly pole,</l>
                  <l>And turns no other way, although ſurrounded</l>
                  <l>With griefs abounding, thou art not confounded.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me of ſtones, whoſe power can expell,</l>
                  <l>Or herbs whoſe virtue, can indeed repell</l>
                  <l>The dangerous Thunder, theſe are of ſmall power,</l>
                  <l>Compar'd with that moſt glorious ſparkling Tower</l>
                  <l>His ſoul, that theſe flames only purifie</l>
                  <l>And brighter made, ſo that we may deſcry</l>
                  <l>Our conquering glory, o're the worlds great ſame</l>
                  <l>In which he is a Mirror ſtill the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſhall our light afflictions temporary</l>
                  <l>Diſcourage us from climing to thy glory,</l>
                  <l>And drive us from thy ſervice, by ſuch Toyes</l>
                  <l>As Satan caſts to hinder purer Joyes?</l>
                  <l>No, thou doſt skreen thy love in diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>And ſheweſt thy goodneſs in our puniſhment;</l>
                  <l>And whilſt we do moſt fooliſhly repine,</l>
                  <l>And grumble at this providence of thine</l>
                  <l>Being two much troubled, at the ſmalleſt croſs</l>
                  <l>Of wealth, and Honor, which doe us ſo toſs</l>
                  <l>With vain affections, ſhews we cannot take</l>
                  <l>Danger of ſufferings for thy bleſſed ſake;</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62740:12"/>
                  <l>But are without true ſence, of thy dear Love,</l>
                  <l>And the Celeſtial Glory that's above,</l>
                  <l>Treaſur'd for us, our duty's to ſubmit</l>
                  <l>To thy bleſt will, and all thou thinkeſt fit,</l>
                  <l>Triumphing in our ſufferings, not repine;</l>
                  <l>Lord bow our wills unto that will of thine</l>
                  <l>Eternal wiſdom, Let it now be done</l>
                  <l>To thine own Glory, and thine only Son.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Romans 6.12.</hi> and part of <hi>21.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let not Sin therefore raign in you mortal bodies, that you ſhould obey in the Luſts thereof: For the end of theſe things are Death.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Bleſt, and Learn'd Apoſtle here doth Preach</l>
                  <l>Attonement made by Chriſt, doth likewiſe teach</l>
                  <l>Th'effects and power of Baptiſm here on earth,</l>
                  <l>Saying, we'er all Baptiz'd into his Death,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall be ſurely raiſed from the Grave,</l>
                  <l>By th'only power of him that did us ſave</l>
                  <l>From Death Eternal, and may freely walk</l>
                  <l>In a renewed Life, and thereof talk</l>
                  <l>To th' comfort of our Souls, and Crucifie</l>
                  <l>Our foul affections wherein we deſcry</l>
                  <l>Sins large dominion in us, it's recoyl'd</l>
                  <l>Which only Chriſt in Love did reconcile,</l>
                  <l>Made us alive to God by's interceſſion:</l>
                  <l>Therefore, let ſin not raign to the tranſgreſſion</l>
                  <l>Of Gods moſt Holy will, nor yet obey</l>
                  <l>The raging Luſts thereof, which do bear ſway</l>
                  <l>Within our mortal bodies, while w'have breath,</l>
                  <l>Remembring that the end thereof is Death.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62740:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who'l fancy ſuch felicity on earth,</l>
                  <l>Which quite expireth with this preſent breath,</l>
                  <l>And the reward of Luſts will ſurely be</l>
                  <l>Filled with horror, and calamity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had we no hopes, and were our ſences gone,</l>
                  <l>Had we no thoughts of a Reſurrection,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe again decayed natures frame,</l>
                  <l>To a more noble ſhape, than is the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Then might we well thus drown our ſelves in pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>And think on Heaven at our remoteſt leaſure;</l>
                  <l>Like Epicures Study, and ſtill invent,</l>
                  <l>New faſhioned Luxury with an intent,</l>
                  <l>For to be thought ingenious, Rich in Wit,</l>
                  <l>And take felicity to revel in it.</l>
                  <l>Thinking that all confuſion would do well,</l>
                  <l>And make no reckning either of Heaven or Hell;</l>
                  <l>But mingle all into a wild confuſion,</l>
                  <l>By making ſuch Athiſtical concluſion:</l>
                  <l>Yea, deem't no ſcandal for to be thus hurld</l>
                  <l>To Blaſphemy, as for to think the world</l>
                  <l>Is without God; no, ſtop thy prophane breath,</l>
                  <l>Sins certain wages is eternal death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis not the fear of death that takes thee hence,</l>
                  <l>But the horror of a guilty conſcience</l>
                  <l>That doth affright thee: when the ſting of death</l>
                  <l>Seizeth our vital parts, and ſtops our breath,</l>
                  <l>The memory of our ſins doth ſmartly ſting</l>
                  <l>Awakened conſcience; when we'er hovering</l>
                  <l>Over our Graves, where we muſt ſoon be laid,</l>
                  <l>Then Hell and Judgment make us moſt afraid</l>
                  <l>Who ſuffred ſin to vaunt thus in our blood,</l>
                  <l>Following our Luſts, and ſhunning what is good.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62740:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell me O thou, who makeſt Earth thy Treaſure,</l>
                  <l>And wrapſt thy ſelf up in the ſofteſt pleaſure;</l>
                  <l>'Tis but a little Span before thine eyes,</l>
                  <l>With age grown weak and weary, yea deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>Such objects, when each tired limb doth crack</l>
                  <l>With anguiſh of thoſe pains, thy crimes did make,</l>
                  <l>Which were th'officious inſtruments to act</l>
                  <l>Sins fatal Scene, and following the tract</l>
                  <l>Of Luſts, and Luxury, rev'ling with heat,</l>
                  <l>That ſets thy darling body in a ſweat,</l>
                  <l>Afflicts thee with the terrors of theſe fires,</l>
                  <l>Which thou haſt kindled with thy foul deſires.</l>
                  <l>Strictly examine now thy ſelf, vain man,</l>
                  <l>Whether theſe flattering falſe enjoyments can</l>
                  <l>Reſtore thy ſoul, which they have ſtoln from Heaven</l>
                  <l>Recover it again, and ſo make even</l>
                  <l>That long and vaſt accompt, which heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt laid by, and ſet it on the ſcore</l>
                  <l>Of thy bleſt Saviour, ſtop, I ſay, bewail</l>
                  <l>The memory of thy crimes, and ſo prevail</l>
                  <l>To get that pardoning mercy, that doth heal</l>
                  <l>All broken hearts that unto Chriſt appeal;</l>
                  <l>Breathing ſuch aires, whoſe Muſick ſoon would charm,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Davids</hi> Harp, 'twill drive away all harm;</l>
                  <l>Still conſcience cries, make Muſick to delight</l>
                  <l>Th'Almighties ears, and bring thee to his ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where are thoſe fond diverſions, that did take</l>
                  <l>Up thy vain thoughts, and did as ſhadows make</l>
                  <l>A tranſcient ſplendor, which prov'd little gain</l>
                  <l>It could not bribe thy pardon, nor obtain</l>
                  <l>The leaſt reprieve to keep thee from the Grave,</l>
                  <l>Or be a means at all thy ſoul to ſave.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62740:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>See ye blind Lovers, of this Maſs of Clay,</l>
                  <l>How quickly your enjoymonts fade away,</l>
                  <l>Being built on ſuch Foundations, which do ſlide</l>
                  <l>And turn to Rubbiſh, it will not abide</l>
                  <l>Your vain felicities, they have no power</l>
                  <l>For to ſecure you in the lateſt hour.</l>
                  <l>Yea, that impartial Conqueror, pale Death</l>
                  <l>Will ſeize your Vitals, and ſtop your Breath:</l>
                  <l>Such as delight in pleaſures, live in flame,</l>
                  <l>And Death will bring them Torments, Hell, and Shame</l>
                  <l>All that now ſpurn at Virtue, and it Scoff,</l>
                  <l>Following vain pleaſures, and the Luſts thereof.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bewitching World, thou, thou betray'ſt our ſence,</l>
                  <l>And ſmoothly wheels us to impenitence,</l>
                  <l>Making tranſitory pleaſures our delight,</l>
                  <l>And through dark miſts, leads to Eternal night.</l>
                  <l>Yet we imbrace, and hug the waies of Sin,</l>
                  <l>And with a pleaſing madneſs live therein;</l>
                  <l>Stopping our ears to the profers of thy Love,</l>
                  <l>The which would raiſe us to the joyes above,</l>
                  <l>Wildly we follow the dictates of ſence;</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe vile affections flowing thence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pitty, O Lord, our Captiv'd natures frail,</l>
                  <l>And give us ſuch deſires as may prevail</l>
                  <l>Over our Luſts, that our whole Souls may be,</l>
                  <l>Breathings in perfect longings after thee,</l>
                  <l>With holy ſervency, whilſt we have breath,</l>
                  <l>Knowing that ſins reward is certain Death.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62740:14"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 15.28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And he ſaid unto her, O Woman great is thy Faith.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>BLeſt importunity, that did procure</l>
                  <l>An anſwer ſo Divine, that did aſſure</l>
                  <l>The poor impatient woman in diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Of'r Daughters cure, to eaſe her heavineſs.</l>
                  <l>Her anſwers were ſo pious, they did tell</l>
                  <l>That in her breaſt did all the graces dwell,</l>
                  <l>And richer Mines of Treaſure there were hid,</l>
                  <l>Then Princes Crowns, though highly valued.</l>
                  <l>All Paleſtine, and the rich Spices there,</l>
                  <l>Could not procure a Cordial, to compare</l>
                  <l>With her ſtrong Faith, which could have no denial,</l>
                  <l>But cur'd two Souls, ſans any further trial,</l>
                  <l>Save only this, the great Phyſitian ſaith</l>
                  <l>Unto this ſuppliant, <hi>Great is thy Faith.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Faith is a grace, prevails with God above</l>
                  <l>To work great wonders, Mountains to remove,</l>
                  <l>To ſmooth the rugged Ocean for a walk,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Peters</hi> feet, to hear his Saviour talk.</l>
                  <l>It ſtops the Mouths of Lyons, quenches fire,</l>
                  <l>'Twas the Centurians Faith got his deſire:</l>
                  <l>It cures the blind, in Scripture we may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Thy Faith hath ſaved thee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet the Faith, that hath ſuch wonders wrought,</l>
                  <l>Is quite neglected, and not duly ſought,</l>
                  <l>Some place the greatneſs of their Faith in merit,</l>
                  <l>And think thereby Salvation to in herit:</l>
                  <l>In many ſuch a fancy there doth dwell,</l>
                  <l>They think it Faith enough for to do well.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62740:15"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But naked ſpeculations will not get</l>
                  <l>The heavenly prize, 'tis vanity to ſet</l>
                  <l>Our faith in our abilities &amp; parts;</l>
                  <l>This is a doctrine which exceeds all arts.</l>
                  <l>Faith's rooted in the ſoul moſt firm and ſtable,</l>
                  <l>By which the Bleſſed <hi>Abraham</hi> was able,</l>
                  <l>For to believe Gods promiſe true, to bleſs</l>
                  <l>His ſeed, which God did count his righteouſneſs;</l>
                  <l>'Tis not profeſſion only, that makes noiſe,</l>
                  <l>But wee muſt practice to obtain true Joyes:</l>
                  <l>Yet mourning ſouls, when they do ſigh and groan,</l>
                  <l>Are in the road unto the heavenly Throne:</l>
                  <l>They'l find acceptance, pardon for defects,</l>
                  <l>Which doth our ſouls, and bodies thus perplex.</l>
                  <l>Let no one think he can take to much pain</l>
                  <l>To be aſſur'd that Heaven he ſhall attain.</l>
                  <l>Thus was the Womans faith, ſo firmly fixt</l>
                  <l>That it no ſhew of doubting with it mixt,</l>
                  <l>The eccho of the voice did ſtraight affright,</l>
                  <l>Foul Sathan from his hold, not all his might</l>
                  <l>Could keep poſſeſſion, when our Saviour Spake,</l>
                  <l>He quickly vaniſht, and did her for ſake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus doth our faiths divine all powerful Charmes,</l>
                  <l>Drive Satan to his Chain, and free all harmes,</l>
                  <l>Raiſeth immortal ſtatues to the Juſt,</l>
                  <l>And makes their names venerable in duſt;</l>
                  <l>Yea, ſeals their happineſs for ever ſure,</l>
                  <l>With Chriſt in glory ever to endure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſent'ſt thy Son, O Lord, for us to Die,</l>
                  <l>That we through him might gain eternity;</l>
                  <l>Him whom thou haſt advanc'd above all things,</l>
                  <l>Is pleas'd to take us under his bleſt wings;</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62740:15"/>
                  <l>That we may have the triumphs of his Croſs,</l>
                  <l>And afterward, Heavens glory without loſs.</l>
                  <l>Let not the miſeries of our patures frail,</l>
                  <l>Which firſt did with thy mercies rich prevail.</l>
                  <l>Oh let not theſe which only know thy power,</l>
                  <l>More zealouſly acknowledge thee each hour:</l>
                  <l>Than we to whom thou manifeſts thy love,</l>
                  <l>And claim an intereſt in thy Chriſt above.</l>
                  <l>Let us be ever thankful for his merit,</l>
                  <l>By whoſe rich bounty we ſhall ſure inherit</l>
                  <l>The heavenly manſions, and ſhall ever be</l>
                  <l>Above faith there, to wait all times on thee:</l>
                  <l>That faith with which thou giveſt every grace,</l>
                  <l>And without which, we nere ſhall ſee thy face.</l>
                  <l>Teach us thy mercies, ſo far to apply,</l>
                  <l>That we neglect not means, and ſo relie</l>
                  <l>On faith, that's dead, or on a vaine diſſembling,</l>
                  <l>Salvation's had by faith, faith's Join'd with trembling.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62740:16"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 12.2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But <hi>Lazarus</hi> was one of thoſe that ſat at the Table with him.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId <hi>Jews</hi> take Councel for to put to Death</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed Lord of Life, which gave them breath?</l>
                  <l>Was he aware of their moſt barbarous talk,</l>
                  <l>That openly with them he would not walk?</l>
                  <l>But came to <hi>Bethani</hi> where <hi>Lazarus</hi> lay,</l>
                  <l>And there he freely Supt, and made ſome ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Martha</hi> ferv'd, as well as ſhe was able,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Lazarus</hi> one of them that ſate at Table.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could <hi>Lazarus</hi> eat, and did his ſtomack crave,</l>
                  <l>That was ſo lately riſen from the Grave?</l>
                  <l>Is his late Tomb a Table, now his dreſs</l>
                  <l>That bound his head, his Napkin at that Meſs?</l>
                  <l>He that but now feaſted the worms for meat,</l>
                  <l>Doth feaſt himſelf, and with the Living eat.</l>
                  <l>The Mercies of our God's above all things,</l>
                  <l>He ſets at Table with the King of Kings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There hath been ſome, all liveleſs pall ſtretcht out</l>
                  <l>For Coffin, until others went about</l>
                  <l>To tin that ſpark of life that cloſe lay hid,</l>
                  <l>As glimering in the heart not wholly dead.</l>
                  <l>And by endeavors have call'd back that heat,</l>
                  <l>Which hath enabled them again to eat.</l>
                  <l>But here 'twas otherwiſe with <hi>Lazarus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As Holy Writings teſtifie to us;</l>
                  <l>He's rais'd from real death, yet <hi>Martha</hi> cry'd,</l>
                  <l>Lord, if thou hadſt been here, he had not dy'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62740:16"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold, him now as riſen from his bed,</l>
                  <l>All fleſh and life, no whit disfigured,</l>
                  <l>Perfect, and whole, really rendred able,</l>
                  <l>To feaſt himſelf with joy at the ſame table</l>
                  <l>Where his redeemer ſupt, a bleſſed feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Lazarus</hi> is admitted to be Gueſt!</l>
                  <l>He's throng'd with multitudes, aged, and younger,</l>
                  <l>Which came to be ſpectators of the wonder;</l>
                  <l>Yet would not believe the power that wrought it,</l>
                  <l>But wickedly oppoſ'd, and never ſought it.</l>
                  <l>Thy thought of beaven on earth, inricht with treaſures,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields, or ſuch like feigned pleaſures.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reſtored <hi>Lazarus</hi> though thou haſt new breath,</l>
                  <l>There is a time will bring a ſecond death:</l>
                  <l>Yet thou art happy in the ſacred ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Inricht with that entitles thee to glory.</l>
                  <l>A happineſs indeed beyond expreſſion,</l>
                  <l>Death will thee bring unto the full poſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>Of the bleſt Manſions, with the Saints in bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Where Angels Sing and every Comfort is.</l>
                  <l>Come, tell me <hi>Lazarus,</hi> didſt thou e're believe</l>
                  <l>T'enjoy the world again, and to receive</l>
                  <l>Thy riſe from grave, before the general day,</l>
                  <l>And grand aſſize, which we muſt obey,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſiſters doubted it, but yet did ſee</l>
                  <l>This miracle of mercy ſhewed to thee,</l>
                  <l>Who wilt ſo walk, and be a great adorer</l>
                  <l>Of breath divine, That was thy great reſtorer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What numbers of expiring ſouls are frighted;</l>
                  <l>At the horror of thoſe crimes, that once delighted</l>
                  <l>Their ſenſual appetites? (The dying man)</l>
                  <l>Scar'd with his pains would leng then out his Span,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62740:17"/>
                  <l>And gladly turn their late profaner ayres</l>
                  <l>To penetential ſighs, and earneſt prayers;</l>
                  <l>New tune their lives into moſt pious ſtrains,</l>
                  <l>And be ſufficient gainers for their pains.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that defers it to the lateſt hour</l>
                  <l>Shall find his weakneſs, will not have the power</l>
                  <l>And vigor of that zeal, that ſhould invoke</l>
                  <l>Mercy divine, for to remove the Yoke</l>
                  <l>Of ſin, that doth ſo heavy on us lie,</l>
                  <l>And ſo benumbs us that we can't deſcry</l>
                  <l>Our ſins aright, the which we muſt confeſs</l>
                  <l>With truth of heart, and humble holineſs;</l>
                  <l>Therefore, we ſhould make uſe of ſtrength and parts</l>
                  <l>To invocate that God, which ſearches hearts,</l>
                  <l>And though his Judgments high are and ſublime,</l>
                  <l>He ſaith to wandring ſinners, at what time</l>
                  <l>You ſhall repent indeed, and humbly mourn,</l>
                  <l>I'le meet you, (if with faith) you do return.</l>
                  <l>And he whoſe piety hath any taſte</l>
                  <l>Of heavenly Joyes, will never vainly waſte</l>
                  <l>His precious time, nor no more fondly range,</l>
                  <l>But long, and be ambitious of his change.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, it was thy Almighty power did ſave</l>
                  <l>Good <hi>Lazarm</hi> being carried to his grave,</l>
                  <l>Return'd him Living. 'T was thy love divine</l>
                  <l>That made thy Almightineſs, ſo far to ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And made thee to diſcover that great power,</l>
                  <l>Which can raiſe mortals, every day and hour.</l>
                  <l>Oh let thy grace concur in me, to raiſe,</l>
                  <l>And to reform my ſoul, that all my days</l>
                  <l>I may improve endeavors to fulfill</l>
                  <l>Thy pious precepts, and perform thy will</l>
                  <l>Which bind my conſcience, dear Chriſt, do this rather</l>
                  <l>By that dear love, which drew thee from thy father,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62740:17"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ſave loſt Man, let th'Scepter of thy word</l>
                  <l>Have influence on me, that may afford</l>
                  <l>All ſpiritual comfort, which may ne're depart</l>
                  <l>From me, but live for ever in my heart,</l>
                  <l>That I may live a Life of Joy and bliſs,</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt the bleſt Saints in perfect happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Where nothing elſe but Sin can ſhut me out,</l>
                  <l>Lord, grant thy mercy, then I ſhall not doubt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Geneſis 2.8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And the Lord God Planted a Garden Eaſtward in <hi>Eden.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>WAS God a Planter? Did he thus take pain</l>
                  <l>So early for us, with ſome hopes to gain</l>
                  <l>Our Souls Immortal? how hath poor vain Man</l>
                  <l>Fancy'd ſome other place? tell me, who can?</l>
                  <l>Where was the Garden plac'd? Leave thy vain queſt,</l>
                  <l>It was in <hi>Eden Eaſtward,</hi> be at reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See, how ambitious Mortals; here are toſt</l>
                  <l>With nice enquiries, ſince Old <hi>Adam</hi> loſt,</l>
                  <l>That there was ſuch a place, we need not doubt it,</l>
                  <l>Our Parents ſin'd, and therefore went without it:</l>
                  <l>So quickly doth our ſin blaſt our enjoyment,</l>
                  <l>Man walk'd, and view'd, and loſt it in a moment;</l>
                  <l>Was ſuddenly expell'd, the riſing Sun</l>
                  <l>But newly warm'd the Earth, Mans Joyes were done.</l>
                  <l>This Ball was withered, into a dry complection,</l>
                  <l>And Man depreſt to ſervile baſe ſubjection:</l>
                  <l>The Heavens ſcarce ſeated well in their right Orb,</l>
                  <l>By Pride the Angels fell, that did diſturb</l>
                  <l>The frame Divine, and the baſe Serpents breath</l>
                  <l>Caſt out contagion over all the Earth,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62740:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>In that ſweet Paradiſe epitomiz'd</l>
                  <l>For its rare fragrancy, was Man ſurpriz'd,</l>
                  <l>Shut out, excluded from thoſe purer ſmells</l>
                  <l>Of new created flowers, took his farewells:</l>
                  <l>Thus man being ſtript of his moſt glorious prize,</l>
                  <l>By that foul friend the father of all lies;</l>
                  <l>He takes the fig-tree, for his laſt retreat,</l>
                  <l>His leaves for cloathing, and his fruit for meat.</l>
                  <l>How perfectly, hath <hi>Adams</hi> iſſue ſpent</l>
                  <l>Their vain deſires, and their affections bent</l>
                  <l>On fond felicities, and gainleſs Toyes,</l>
                  <l>Selling Heavens Paradiſe, and all its Joys!</l>
                  <l>Covetous man doats on his god of gold,</l>
                  <l>As though there were no other to behold</l>
                  <l>Counts his chief happineſs is only there,</l>
                  <l>Though ſtampt in hell it ſelf, and if it were</l>
                  <l>The Image of the beaſt, it will not deter</l>
                  <l>Man from it, But he'l be competitor</l>
                  <l>With Prince of darkneſs, for ſome glorious Toy</l>
                  <l>Of Terrene pomp, ſlighting his chiefeſt Joy;</l>
                  <l>Makes wantonneſs his heaven, and carnal pleaſures</l>
                  <l>His chief divinity, wanting right meaſures</l>
                  <l>In this his choice, But he will quickly find</l>
                  <l>Theſe upſtart lights, but darkneſs to his mind</l>
                  <l>Sent by the King of darkneſs, in deriſion</l>
                  <l>To caſt affronts, and puzzle our religion;</l>
                  <l>Ecclipſe the Goſpel by their vain pretences</l>
                  <l>To bleer our eyes, and to benight our ſences.</l>
                  <l>When they pretend to cloath us with more skill,</l>
                  <l>They ſtrip us of our cloathing at their will.</l>
                  <l>They'd ſhut us out of heaven, I'd rather bee</l>
                  <l>For ever blind, than by their balme to ſee</l>
                  <l>Of Satans making, nor yet be partaker</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a leſſon to diſtruſt my Maker.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62740:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>So miſerably are we by frailties toſt,</l>
                  <l>Not only Paradiſe, but Heaven is loſt.</l>
                  <l>We loofe not only pleaſures here below,</l>
                  <l>But joys divine, which thou wilt ſure beſtow</l>
                  <l>On us poor Mortals, he that then was chief</l>
                  <l>Monarch of the whole world, doth now with grief</l>
                  <l>Groan under his great burden, and doth flie</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the ſhades in ſad obſcurity.</l>
                  <l>We might ev'n all have bin, for ever caſt</l>
                  <l>Out of Gods ſight, but he that's firſt, and laſt</l>
                  <l>Breathed a new life into our 'clipſed ſtate,</l>
                  <l>By his prevailing merits, and he ſate</l>
                  <l>A mediator for our bould transgreſſion.</l>
                  <l>Lord, grant in mercy wee may have poſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>Of Heaven, and heavenly Joys, diſdain the Droſs</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſures, and indeed may fear the loſs,</l>
                  <l>Of our poor ſouls; that when we do expire</l>
                  <l>We may be carried to the heav'nly Quire,</l>
                  <l>Into that paradiſe, that never fades,</l>
                  <l>To ſit for ever in celeſtial ſhades.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62740:19"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke 10.25.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And behold, a certain Lawyer ſtood up and tempted him, ſaying, Maſter, what ſhall I do to Inherit Eternal Life.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold, Chriſt's miſſion he doth freely ſend</l>
                  <l>His choſen ſeventy for this bleſſed end,</l>
                  <l>To preach the Goſpel, and he doth admoniſh</l>
                  <l>Them to have humble hearts, and not aſtoniſh</l>
                  <l>His zealous ones, that do deſire to learn</l>
                  <l>The myſteries of faith, and would diſcern</l>
                  <l>The way unto ſalvation, by ſuch guide,</l>
                  <l>Not following the over active pride</l>
                  <l>Of fond Enthuſiaſts, and their bold intent,</l>
                  <l>That skip ſo faſt, and run before they'r ſent.</l>
                  <l>No, God's the God of order, law and right,</l>
                  <l>As the lawyer here obſerves, at the firſt ſight</l>
                  <l>His faith was quick, ingenious, bold and rife,</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall I do to attain eternal life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>T'was the beſt query, that ever he made,</l>
                  <l>It gain'd him more, than all his pleading trade</l>
                  <l>Could ever get him, he was bid to look</l>
                  <l>Into the law, for fear that he miſtook.</l>
                  <l>T'was no diſgrace to follow ſuch a ſuit,</l>
                  <l>As did concern his ſoul, had he bin mute,</l>
                  <l>Then he had miſt the time for to enquire</l>
                  <l>The way to bliſs, which was his chief deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This was the higheſt cauſe, he'ere could plead,</l>
                  <l>T'was for him ſelf, Gods ſpirit did him lead</l>
                  <l>To make that happy queſtion in ſuch ſort,</l>
                  <l>For he had never read of a report</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62740:19"/>
                  <l>Given in this caſe, no, not, in all his reading</l>
                  <l>Of judged caſes, 'twas not his learned breeding.</l>
                  <l>Philoſophy indeed doth reach no higher,</l>
                  <l>Than moral virtue, it doth not inſpire</l>
                  <l>The ſpirit of grace, 'tis that which works by love,</l>
                  <l>That doth acquaint us with the joyes above.</l>
                  <l>T'was this inſpir'd our Lawyer to this task,</l>
                  <l>To run to Chriſt, and him ſo boldly ask.</l>
                  <l>'Twas now high time indeed for him to run</l>
                  <l>To move this queſtion, or hee'd been undone;</l>
                  <l>For he had bin retain'd too long to plead</l>
                  <l>In others cauſes, leaving his own in dread.</l>
                  <l>He almoſt had forgot his better part,</l>
                  <l>I mean his ſoul, which prickt him to the heart,</l>
                  <l>And it did all his vital ſenſes ſeize,</l>
                  <l>Which made him ſtrongly plead for writ of eaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How natural are enquiries after bliſs?</l>
                  <l>Even pagans ſtudy it darkly, and amiſs;</l>
                  <l>The joyes they fancy, Paradiſe will yield</l>
                  <l>Are meer Chimera's, their Elyſian field</l>
                  <l>Of carnal pleaſures fill'd, are thought to be,</l>
                  <l>Which they affect as their felicity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But its the genuin ſenſe of a good mind</l>
                  <l>Full fraught with virtue, carefully to find</l>
                  <l>Something above the world, therefore, how vain</l>
                  <l>Are worldlings, which ſo fooliſhly take pain,</l>
                  <l>Making their chief enquiries, but for droſs,</l>
                  <l>Vexatious vanities, ſubject to loſs</l>
                  <l>Without a holy care! this Lawyer, wiſe</l>
                  <l>Makes right enquiry, and demands advice</l>
                  <l>Of the beſt councel, T'whom he doth reſort,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n him that beſt can anſwer, and report.</l>
                  <l>Some, Some, there are that only do enquire</l>
                  <l>After good titles, make it their deſire.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62740:20"/>
                  <l>'Tis there divinity, lead them that way,</l>
                  <l>So they grow rich, they care not who decay:</l>
                  <l>If they cant Rant, and ſwagger, cheat and prate,</l>
                  <l>They'l ſell eternity at any rate.</l>
                  <l>So ſadly doe our vices drown religion;</l>
                  <l>That to enquire of heaven, is held deriſion.</l>
                  <l>There's no ſuch airy queſtions in their books,</l>
                  <l>It's trivial, of no worth, 't will ſpoil their looks,</l>
                  <l>And marr their pleading, yea their gain, that's chief,</l>
                  <l>Have no ſuch memorandum in their brief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stop then vain Man, conſider with thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou covet to graſp ſo much pelf;</l>
                  <l>It's not the flattering title of a name,</l>
                  <l>Guilded with maſſey Gold, can keep thy ſhame</l>
                  <l>From the Almighty's eyes, ſo full of light</l>
                  <l>That do obſerve thy pleadings wrong or right,</l>
                  <l>Plead like the Lawyer here for a poſſeſſion:</l>
                  <l>It's ſuitable to every Mans profeſſion</l>
                  <l>To plead for Heaven; The client muſt not leave</l>
                  <l>That ſuit unfollowed, leaſt he doth deceive</l>
                  <l>His Heaven born ſoul, for they muſt both appear</l>
                  <l>Before one bar, in trembling, and in fear;</l>
                  <l>There's no delay when cal'd, no writ can move,</l>
                  <l>Our day of hearing's fixt in Heaven above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord let us with delight approach to thee,</l>
                  <l>Which art chief counſel in extremity,</l>
                  <l>And not reflect on parts, demurs of wit,</l>
                  <l>But eye that Throne, whereon indeed doth ſit</l>
                  <l>The Judge of all the Earth, from whoſe clear ſight</l>
                  <l>No fleſh can hide it ſelf, Let our delight</l>
                  <l>Be to enquire thy waies, which chiefly tend</l>
                  <l>To that true glory ne'r ſhall have an end.</l>
                  <l>The Lawyers moſt importunate requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Let it with zeal ev'n always warm our breaſt,</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62740:20"/>
                  <l>And ſtir up in our hearts a holy ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>To get aſſurance of eternal life.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 11.36.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Jeſus Wept.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>STop! O my ſoul, and here behold and ſee,</l>
                  <l>Thy Saviour ſweet in his humanity!</l>
                  <l>His paſſions did prevail, he could not keep</l>
                  <l>His eyes of mercy dry, but ſoare did weep</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and in him for us all</l>
                  <l>That wrapt are, and involv'd in ſin and thrall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh who can hear this, and yet have the power</l>
                  <l>To hold his eyes from ſtreaming out a ſhower</l>
                  <l>Of tears? what frozen heart can chooſe but melt</l>
                  <l>Into a flood of teares, if they e'r felt</l>
                  <l>A touch of conſcience, for thoſe ſins of theirs,</l>
                  <l>And yet will not accompany his tears?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold we ſee the marble hearted <hi>Jew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cenſuring his grief, with malice to purſue</l>
                  <l>Their envious taunts, corruption of their mind,</l>
                  <l>And jearing ſaid, can't he that cur'd the blind</l>
                  <l>Keep <hi>Lazarus</hi> alive, do not deride,</l>
                  <l>It was that God and Chriſt be glorified,</l>
                  <l>And clearly did determine that vain ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>I am the Reſurrection and the life.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No wonder if they did refuſe to be</l>
                  <l>Mourners, which acted ſuch a villany,</l>
                  <l>And had ſuch ſmall compaſſion on his grief,</l>
                  <l>That were become his Murderers in chief,</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62740:21"/>
                  <l>And op'd that fountain ſtream of his dear blood,</l>
                  <l>Which guſhed out like water from a flood;</l>
                  <l>Which ſtill lies op, where we may have acceſs</l>
                  <l>To him by faith, and truth and holineſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet how many are there, that do bear</l>
                  <l>Thy title, and boldly pretend to wear</l>
                  <l>The livery of thy name, but do refuſe</l>
                  <l>The characters of thy Croſs, and ſtill are <hi>Jews.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How coldly ſure are they, ſtand thus affected</l>
                  <l>That are not touched with grief, nor yet dejected</l>
                  <l>For his harſh ſufferings, at his lateſt breath,</l>
                  <l>Which ſeems to be forgetful of his death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How richly are good <hi>Mary's</hi> tears requited,</l>
                  <l>Which waſh't her Saviours feet, which ſhe delighted;</l>
                  <l>Her eyes were moving bathes, ſtill running over</l>
                  <l>To ſee his brim full drops, that did diſcover</l>
                  <l>His love divine, which nothing could remove</l>
                  <l>To ſhew his power, his mercy, and his love.</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Martha</hi> did diſwade for want of faith;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lazarus</hi> come forth, our bleſſed Saviour faith,</l>
                  <l>Had <hi>Lazarus</hi> but known; what a rich prize</l>
                  <l>He was eſteem'd in the Almighty's Eyes,</l>
                  <l>He would have dy'd and not repented</l>
                  <l>To be thus buried, and ſo much lamented.</l>
                  <l>Have ſuch a mourner wait upon his pall</l>
                  <l>Which is the Almighty Saviour, of us all.</l>
                  <l>Divineſt Saviour, thou didſt weep for thoſe</l>
                  <l>That could not weep, nor yet fully diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>Their vile affections, it was ſin that kept</l>
                  <l>Them priſoners to their luſts, their ſences ſlept.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou poureſt out thy tears, thy life and blood,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall we not pour ours even in a flood,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62740:21"/>
                  <l>That fully ſhould ſpeak out, unfained ſorrow</l>
                  <l>For ſin, and not defer it till the morrow.</l>
                  <l>But we're ſo plung'd in ſin, and many feares,</l>
                  <l>That we cannot accompany thy tears:</l>
                  <l>It is to ſad a walk for fleſh and blood,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs thy ſpirit lead us to what is good.</l>
                  <l>Shew us thy purer ways, leaſt we intrude,</l>
                  <l>And give us hearts of pious gratitude,</l>
                  <l>That we may glorifie thy name with praiſe,</l>
                  <l>For our redemption, and that all our days</l>
                  <l>May be a thanks giving, not to ſay we ſlept,</l>
                  <l>Remembring always, that our Jeſus wept.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matth. 6.33.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God and his Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>OUr bleſt Redeemer doth continue here</l>
                  <l>His precepts, teaching Goſpel courſe to ſteere,</l>
                  <l>Contained in his Sermon on the Mount,</l>
                  <l>A heavenly ſubject worthy our account.</l>
                  <l>But we poor wealkings, an how frail are we,</l>
                  <l>That's laſt in thought, which ought the firſt to be.</l>
                  <l>Our duller parts are now ſo dead, and numb,</l>
                  <l>All clog'd with earthly cares, our tongues are dumb</l>
                  <l>To make enquiry after thy purer ways,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhould expreſs our duty and thy praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such loyterers are we Heav'n ward, that we make</l>
                  <l>Small ſpeed, and have more mind, and care to take</l>
                  <l>Our carnal conſiderations with us ſo,</l>
                  <l>That we cannot effectually let go</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62740:22"/>
                  <l>Our thoughts from ſins but cauſe our Maker ſtay</l>
                  <l>Our leiſure, oh the wretched ſad delay</l>
                  <l>Of ſinful fleſh, that ſtudies to provide</l>
                  <l>Superfluous things for to abett our pride!</l>
                  <l>Mean while our better parts lie to th' view</l>
                  <l>Of Heavens great Eye, with whom we have to do.</l>
                  <l>Such ſtrangers are we to our ſouls concern,</l>
                  <l>That wee indeed don't in the leaſt diſcern</l>
                  <l>Thy love and favor to us, whence we miſs</l>
                  <l>Theſe joyes above, ev'n Heavens eternall bliſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We gaze no higher, than the Lower ſphear,</l>
                  <l>Rowling in meer morality, whilſt there,</l>
                  <l>As though we had nothing beyond our breath</l>
                  <l>To look for, when wee'r ſnatcht away by death.</l>
                  <l>What thoughts, ambitious do we ever carry</l>
                  <l>For terrene Joyes? how little for Gods glory?</l>
                  <l>Vain Jolities, and worldly pleaſures ſwallow</l>
                  <l>The thoughts of Heaven, not ſuffering us to follow</l>
                  <l>Gods heavenly Preceps, we do ſadly lie</l>
                  <l>Dead in our thoughts of immortality.</l>
                  <l>Vain man, what is't that thou doſt ſacrifice</l>
                  <l>Thy idle thoughts unto, or wherein lies</l>
                  <l>Thy chief felicity? The pagans can</l>
                  <l>Fancy a bliſs amongſt the ſhades, vain Man,</l>
                  <l>And place their trophies in their amorous walks,</l>
                  <l>Where there ghoſts revels, and their fancie talks</l>
                  <l>Of pleaſures, but can we, O Lord, forget</l>
                  <l>Thy Kingdom, and not once look after it!</l>
                  <l>He that prophanely wanders, is a ſtranger</l>
                  <l>To heavenly Joyes, and ſure is ſtill in danger</l>
                  <l>To looſe that would enrich him beyond meaſure,</l>
                  <l>With ſplendid glories, and with heavenly treaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How wretched then, are they that ſo miſtake,</l>
                  <l>And for themſelves no allegation make,</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62740:22"/>
                  <l>But thrive in ſin, and ſtill the world do court,</l>
                  <l>And with its fading glories make a ſport,</l>
                  <l>Exchanging a rich diadem of bliſs</l>
                  <l>For feigned pleaſures that are ſure amiſs!</l>
                  <l>Were the whole world a ſcene of choiceſt pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Zeraglio</hi> of delights, were all the treaſures</l>
                  <l>Of the <hi>Arabian</hi> region made a field</l>
                  <l>For man to revel in; theſe joyes would yield</l>
                  <l>But low fruitions, truly without thee</l>
                  <l>Our God, which only makes frail Man to ſee,</l>
                  <l>How he is kept in pleaſures temporary,</l>
                  <l>From an eternal weight of heavenly glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet how many are there which would pawn,</l>
                  <l>Their conſciences, and eagerly do fawn</l>
                  <l>Upon theſe vain allurements here below,</l>
                  <l>Slighting heavens mercies, whilſt they do beſtow</l>
                  <l>Their time, in ſome vain ſtudy to invent,</l>
                  <l>New modes of wickedneſs, and with intent</l>
                  <l>T'increaſe their credit in the world's account,</l>
                  <l>And do not care how far they ſwell and mount</l>
                  <l>Their ſtore in ſin, for their content to bee</l>
                  <l>Laborious in a ſweet impiety.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Are there no nobler ways to eternize</l>
                  <l>Our memories, than thus to looſe the prize,</l>
                  <l>I mean of ſouls? it's ſavage cruelty</l>
                  <l>Them to deſtroy to all eternity,</l>
                  <l>For to eſpouſe our names to fowleſt ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And ever vainly glory in the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Making a mock of ſin, and looſe all ſence</l>
                  <l>Of looſing our religions reverence</l>
                  <l>Unto our Maker, which makes no Man worſe</l>
                  <l>By ſerving him aright, with true remorſe;</l>
                  <l>But makes Men ſweeter in a heavenly frame</l>
                  <l>Of rich contentment, and doth breed no ſhame,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62740:23"/>
                  <l>But gain enlargement of his bounteous love,</l>
                  <l>For which we owe our praiſe to God above,</l>
                  <l>That is the only giver of our bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And ought to have our humbleſt thankfulneſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, raiſe in us thoſe aims that truly tend</l>
                  <l>To heavenly joyes, and let our cares moſt bend,</l>
                  <l>Our thoughts that way, then we need not to fear</l>
                  <l>Miſfortunes croſs, nor harms ev'n when they'r neer.</l>
                  <l>This is a policy that will non plus</l>
                  <l>The poring worldling, hel'd be baffled thus,</l>
                  <l>And after generations they muſt yield,</l>
                  <l>That pious policy ſhall win the field.</l>
                  <l>How ſenceleſs of our chiefeſt good are we,</l>
                  <l>That doe prefer the world's felicity</l>
                  <l>Before thy glory, and can ſpend in ſin</l>
                  <l>Our precious hours, which ſhould indeed have bin</l>
                  <l>Devoted, in ſincere returns to thee.</l>
                  <l>Behold, in mercy Lord, how frail we be,</l>
                  <l>That we account a little moment ſpent</l>
                  <l>In ſerving thee, a tireſome puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>So ſottiſh are we in the ways of pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>That for to do thy will, we find no leiſure.</l>
                  <l>We morgage our dear ſouls for vaineſt toyes,</l>
                  <l>And fondly undervalue richeſt joys;</l>
                  <l>Fading contentments, which we fancy here,</l>
                  <l>We purchaſe at a rate extreamly dear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, raiſe our Heaven born ſouls that we may ſee</l>
                  <l>Our vain delights in ſin, and turn to thee</l>
                  <l>By true repentance; give us grace to leave</l>
                  <l>Theſe low enjoyments, that in truth bereave</l>
                  <l>Us of our purer Joyes, O give content</l>
                  <l>In ſtooping to thy holy regiment.</l>
                  <l>Let our dear ſouls for ever more deſpiſe,</l>
                  <l>The flatteries of the world with its diſguiſe,</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62740:23"/>
                  <l>And as our ſouls are made by, and for thee,</l>
                  <l>So keep them Lord, to all eternity.</l>
                  <l>Enable us to breath forth thy high praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And give us of thy bleſſing all our days</l>
                  <l>What ever we do receive, it is from thee,</l>
                  <l>The fountain of all true felicity;</l>
                  <l>Who only canſt our pretious ſouls advance</l>
                  <l>To heavenly dwellings, Saints inheritance;</l>
                  <l>To which we ſeek a promiſed acceſs,</l>
                  <l>Lord, grant thy Kingdom and thy righteouſneſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 13.23.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And there was Leaning on Jeſus boſom one of his Diſciples whom he loved. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre Chriſts tranſcendent love to <hi>John</hi> is ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Being admitted on his breaſt to lean;</l>
                  <l>And as a boſome friend, whom Jeſus lov'd,</l>
                  <l>He took the boldneſs and was not reprov'd.</l>
                  <l>How freely did he make his Saviours breaſt</l>
                  <l>His pillow, and the place of ſweeteſt reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh bleſſed Kindneſs! would not Monarchs great</l>
                  <l>Ambitious be of this, and leave their ſeat,</l>
                  <l>And royal Canopies for to repoſe</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a boſom? as all wiſdom knows</l>
                  <l>The moſt ambitious ſouls can climb no higher,</l>
                  <l>To better reſt poor mortals can't aſpire</l>
                  <l>Then in that boſom, Saints Secureſt neſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is the eternal manſions of the bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62740:24"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>What carping worldling can find out a treaſure,</l>
                  <l>To ſatiate himſelf with fuller pleaſure?</l>
                  <l>The amorous wanton would with ſpeed forſake</l>
                  <l>Admired beauty, if he might partake</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a bed of ſpices, heed inſiſt</l>
                  <l>On Courtſhip to ſo fair an Amoriſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was not this happineſs above the reſt</l>
                  <l>To have procedency in Jeſus breſt?</l>
                  <l>A dignity might give him much delight</l>
                  <l>To be accounted the chief favorit.</l>
                  <l>How pleaſingly doth <hi>John</hi> here lay his ear</l>
                  <l>So cloſe Chriſt heart, it did him greatly chear,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe ſuch raptures in his longing breaſt,</l>
                  <l>As well might rock him into ſweeteſt reſt;</l>
                  <l>And make his dreams occaſions for to raiſe</l>
                  <l>His heart to joy and gladneſs, thanks and praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stop here my ſoul, behold, admire, and ſee</l>
                  <l>The emblem of moſt true felicity,</l>
                  <l>A perfect ſhew of meekneſs, and of love,</l>
                  <l>Mercies great tipe deſcending from above!</l>
                  <l>See Chriſt upon his Croſs, his armes extended,</l>
                  <l>T'imbrace loſt Man, was his heart blood expended,</l>
                  <l>To waſh us from Our guilt of ſin, and ſhame;</l>
                  <l>Lord let me ever glorifie his name,</l>
                  <l>Repoſe my ſelf on's breaſt the ſeat of love,</l>
                  <l>And thereby have true comforts from above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did <hi>Mary</hi> whoſe compaſſions quickly turn'd</l>
                  <l>Into a flood of teares? Her grief ſo mourn'd.</l>
                  <l>Had ſhee bin graced with ſo great a favor,</l>
                  <l>As to lean on the boſom of our Saviour?</l>
                  <l>Her eyes as living ſprings that ſweetly meet,</l>
                  <l>Her haires to wipe her bleſſed Saviours feet,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62740:24"/>
                  <l>Such grace, and priviledge would ev'n let out</l>
                  <l>Her nobleſt blood, in paſſion it would ſpout</l>
                  <l>Out into grateful ſtreams; for ſuch a price</l>
                  <l>And bleſt acquaintance, 'twould require her eyes</l>
                  <l>That ſent forth ſtreames, yet it would make clean</l>
                  <l>Her putrid ſoul, had ſhe but leave to Lean;</l>
                  <l>'Twould tranſport her in raptures of true mirth,</l>
                  <l>For ſuch a bleſſing to enjoy on earth.</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>John</hi> enjoyed as a favor to him given,</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed Emblem of the joyes of Heaven.</l>
                  <l>Did <hi>Peter</hi> give a beck, and did <hi>John</hi> ask?</l>
                  <l>Who ſhould commit that bold and bloody task?</l>
                  <l>Did Chriſt make anſwer? did his God reply?</l>
                  <l>O bleſſed condeſcention! that the high</l>
                  <l>And the Almighty King ſhould ſo ſubmit</l>
                  <l>To mortals, as to daign with him to ſit</l>
                  <l>And commune with them, o let mankind learn</l>
                  <l>All humble meekneſs! and in truth diſcern</l>
                  <l>This holy love of Chriſt to man on earth,</l>
                  <l>And ſee how lovingly he invites new birth,</l>
                  <l>To be born a new by faith and repentance;</l>
                  <l>Such holy practice will his ſoul advance</l>
                  <l>Into the boſom of God, do not delay</l>
                  <l>Thy turning from the vain, and idle way</l>
                  <l>Of ſin, which cauſeth endleſs ſhame and death.</l>
                  <l>Conſider it ye mortals of the Earth,</l>
                  <l>Who now carouſe in ſin and ſport away,</l>
                  <l>Thy bleſſed time of love by your delay.</l>
                  <l>Be not bewitcht with ſin, return and bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Behold our Chriſt admits you to his feaſt.</l>
                  <l>Oh let the endearments of a comon ſence,</l>
                  <l>Of love and lively faith ariſe from thence;</l>
                  <l>And let ſweet raptures of a holy zeal</l>
                  <l>Raiſe in my ſoul, ſuch joyes as may reveal</l>
                  <l>My conſtant faith, and love to him alone,</l>
                  <l>That is for ever ſeated in the Throne</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62740:25"/>
                  <l>Of heavenly glory, Lord, do thou permit</l>
                  <l>Me in his arms of love, and cauſe me ſit</l>
                  <l>Amongſt the Saints above, which take delight</l>
                  <l>To ſing ſweet <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> day and night,</l>
                  <l>To that bleſt quire good Lord in time unite me,</l>
                  <l>And let thy praiſes ever more delight me.</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall my longing ſoul have quiet reſt</l>
                  <l>In the boſom of that glory ever bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke 19.9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>This day is Salvation come to thy houſe.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold, our Jeſus trav'ling for to gain</l>
                  <l>Loſt Man, and ſee with what a loving pain</l>
                  <l>He paſſeth <hi>Jericho,</hi> after he'd wrought</l>
                  <l>Such mighty works, and cur'd them all that ſought</l>
                  <l>To him in faith, of which <hi>Zacheus</hi> hearing,</l>
                  <l>Haſtning he climbs to ſee his Chriſt, not fearing,</l>
                  <l>The publicans could hinder his good nature,</l>
                  <l>His zeal being warm although but low in ſtature.</l>
                  <l>He takes the <hi>Sicamore,</hi> as here we find,</l>
                  <l>To raiſe his body equal with his mind.</l>
                  <l>VVell warm'd with faith, and a deſire to ſee</l>
                  <l>His Lord and Chriſt, from branches of a Tree:</l>
                  <l>VVhere being ſeen, and call'd, he made no ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But with all Joy of heart, he did obey.</l>
                  <l>His infant faith did ſoon break forth in action,</l>
                  <l>And chearfully he vowed ſatisfaction,</l>
                  <l>And reſtitution; no Man did ever more</l>
                  <l>Largely expreſs his Love unto the poor,</l>
                  <l>By all he did it truly demonſtrate,</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt aſſur'd to be with in his gate.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62740:25"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>T'was time for him to haſt, and not deſiſt</l>
                  <l>To entertain ſo merciful a gueſt;</l>
                  <l>That did ſo paſſionately expreſs his love,</l>
                  <l>Calling <hi>Zacheus,</hi> from the Tree above.</l>
                  <l>He leaves the branches, that did him advance,</l>
                  <l>Proſtrates himſelf with humble reverence:</l>
                  <l>Had his low limbs been of a higher extent,</l>
                  <l>He might have wanted that true zeal he meant.</l>
                  <l>But being low in ſtature, high in grace,</l>
                  <l>Hee's call'd to ſee his Chriſt, ev'n face to face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh humble kindneſs of the King of glory!</l>
                  <l>As its recorded in the ſacred ſtory.</l>
                  <l>See how coldly th'world doth entertain</l>
                  <l>The Lord of life, which finds too much diſdain.</l>
                  <l>'Tis he invites who well could pay the coſt,</l>
                  <l>That came to ſeek, and ſave ſuch as were loſt.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Jew</hi> doth vainly look for his Redeemer</l>
                  <l>To come in pomp, which ſhews he's an eſteemer</l>
                  <l>Of worldly majeſty, but hee's become</l>
                  <l>A wandring vagrant till the day of doom.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stop, ſtop, ye glorious mortals, which do ride</l>
                  <l>In golden Chariots, ſtuft with carnal pride.</l>
                  <l>See your Redeemer, a bleſt preſident</l>
                  <l>To true humility, with care repent;</l>
                  <l>Place not felicity on Thrones of Gold,</l>
                  <l>But on the Scepter of Gods word take hold;</l>
                  <l>And if you'l climb, climb like <hi>Zacheus</hi> here,</l>
                  <l>Not after pomp, but with an awful fear</l>
                  <l>Caſt down your ſelves, even from the lofty Tree</l>
                  <l>Of carnal Luſts; Hear Chriſt ſaith, come to me</l>
                  <l>All that decline a Carnal converſation,</l>
                  <l>To them he offers life, joy and ſalvation.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62740:26"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who would not welcome ſuch a noble gueſt,</l>
                  <l>And treat his Saviour at a Bounteous feaſt?</l>
                  <l>And ſacrifice even all with joy, and love,</l>
                  <l>Sith every perfect gift is from above,</l>
                  <l>And giv'n by him, that can repay us double;</l>
                  <l>Conferring perfect happineſs for trouble.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But there are ſome that think it to much charge,</l>
                  <l>If veſtry ornaments be ſomething large,</l>
                  <l>To expreſs th'honor, dignity, and worth</l>
                  <l>Of ſacred things, and decently let forth,</l>
                  <l>As late religious arts perform'd in order;</l>
                  <l>They ſay that on Romes Church we neerly boarder,</l>
                  <l>If they ſee Gap, or Surplice, Hood, or Scarſe,</l>
                  <l>Like ſilly momes, they flout, and jeer and laugh;</l>
                  <l>But ſuch muſt know, unieſs they will be fools,</l>
                  <l>Theſe are diſtinctions in the learned Schools.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How happy was <hi>Zachem</hi> with the favor</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt his preſence, whoſe perſumes did ſavor</l>
                  <l>Of humility, in that he'ed condeſcend,</l>
                  <l>To come to ſinners, as unto a friend,</l>
                  <l>And be a gueſt unto ſuch a kind of Man,</l>
                  <l>As was a meer profeſſed publican:</l>
                  <l>Nor is his mercy ſhut up here alone,</l>
                  <l>But it extends to all that ſigh, and groan;</l>
                  <l>Yea every houſhould, that indeed doth clime</l>
                  <l>And mounts by virtue ſurely ſhall ſee him:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hark, you that ſacrifice your lives and blood,</l>
                  <l>And with a hearful zeal, do fly from good,</l>
                  <l>That foot the muſick of a vainer life,</l>
                  <l>And with true virtues, ever are at ſtriſe,</l>
                  <l>Strangers to God, his holy ordinance</l>
                  <l>The precious ſacraments, that ſure advance</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62740:26"/>
                  <l>The flight toward Heaven, and make thee ſee,</l>
                  <l>Like good <hi>Zachem</hi> here as from a Tree</l>
                  <l>Of grace, if this be planted in thy heart,</l>
                  <l>Then Chriſt will be thy gueſt, and nere depart:</l>
                  <l>If this be water'd with repenting tears,</l>
                  <l>Then it will bring forth fruit, in which appears</l>
                  <l>A holy life, which will the comfort give,</l>
                  <l>And in true Joyes thou ſhalt for ever live,</l>
                  <l>After thy body is by death mowed down,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul ſhall have a pretious heav'nly crown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord, we are as nothing in thy ſight,</l>
                  <l>'Tis thou haft rais'd us by thy power and might;</l>
                  <l>And when the leaſt deſire we feel, or find</l>
                  <l>To come to thee, 'tis thou that ſtirs the mind,</l>
                  <l>And makes us climb, for we are low of ſtature,</l>
                  <l>Lame, and decrepit, poor, weak things by nature,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs we take advantage by the Tree</l>
                  <l>Of faith, and holy life, wee ſee not thee;</l>
                  <l>And climb O Lord, wee can't without thy grace</l>
                  <l>Raiſe us O Lord, by it to ſee thy face:</l>
                  <l>Infuſe in us each holy good deſire,</l>
                  <l>Blow up in us a zeal as hot as fire.</l>
                  <l>A zeal that may a doubtleſs warmth ſure bring,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall we praiſe thee, and for ever ſing</l>
                  <l>Loud <hi>Halelujahs</hi> to thy bleſſed name,</l>
                  <l>That art th'Almighty God, ever the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe mercies condeſcend to every one,</l>
                  <l>And gives aſſurance of ſalvation.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62740:27"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke 9.57.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Lord, I will follow thee whereſoever thou goeſt.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold, our Saviour here who doth reprove</l>
                  <l>Revenging raſhneſs, prompting peace and love,</l>
                  <l>When his Apoſtles fill'd with deſire</l>
                  <l>To be reveng'd would ſet a Town on fire,</l>
                  <l>And in that paſſion were ſo fully bent,</l>
                  <l>They urged to Chriſt a former preſident:</l>
                  <l>Saying, did not <hi>Elias</hi> do ſuch things,</l>
                  <l>As'tis recorded in the book of Kings;</l>
                  <l>But Chriſt reprov'd them, with a ſerious frown,</l>
                  <l>And pull'd their high avenging ſpirits down.</l>
                  <l>I came not to deſtroy mens lives, but ſave</l>
                  <l>All ſuch as in humility do crave:</l>
                  <l>This heard, the ſcribe profeſſeth without boaſt,</l>
                  <l>Lord, I will follow thee where e're thou goeſt,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh bleſſed boldneſs in that reſolution,</l>
                  <l>A happy confidence to make intruſion</l>
                  <l>Into ſuch company, there's none can blame</l>
                  <l>His paſſionate affection, it became</l>
                  <l>Holy deſires, which did indeed expreſs,</l>
                  <l>His fervent zeal to God, and holineſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wondrous miracles which thus were wrought,</l>
                  <l>Brought him to Chriſt, whom he with fervor ſought</l>
                  <l>That divine light, whoſe powerful influence</l>
                  <l>Attracts all Eyes with holy reverence,</l>
                  <l>And all in raptures, proud of company,</l>
                  <l>That led him Heaven-ward in ſuch Majeſty.</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62740:27"/>
                  <l>Thus came the ſcribe attendant for to be,</l>
                  <l>Saying aloud, Lord, I will follow thee:</l>
                  <l>Nor could his poverty ſtop his intention</l>
                  <l>Of following Chriſt, he could have no prevention</l>
                  <l>But ſuffer all the miſeries, can attend</l>
                  <l>So good a Maſter, that can him defend:</l>
                  <l>In whoſe deep wants there is more fulneſs hid,</l>
                  <l>Than Earth amounts unto, if valued.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſcribe's a Coppy, ought we not to write</l>
                  <l>After this <hi>Jew,</hi> and yet how blind's our ſight,</l>
                  <l>We cannot ſee, our ſenſes are bereav'd</l>
                  <l>Of the true light, our ſouls they are deceiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Elſe would we not ſuffer this publican</l>
                  <l>Out ſtrip us in our duty, ah vain Man!</l>
                  <l>Where are thy thoughts, that thou doſt thus deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>That guide that leads to that bleſt place; where lies</l>
                  <l>All the hid treaſures, which can be expreſt</l>
                  <l>Of Saints, and Angels in the heavenly reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Were we to follow through a bed of flowers,</l>
                  <l>Who would not run, who now his viſage lowres.</l>
                  <l>The ſenſualiſt would walk, but that he ſcorns</l>
                  <l>To prick his tender feet, amongſt ſuch Thorns,</l>
                  <l>With prickles ſharp, this roſe is all ſurrounded,</l>
                  <l>He cannot follow, that's with care confounded.</l>
                  <l>Cares of this world, nor can the Epicure</l>
                  <l>Follow, cauſe abſtinence he cannot endure,</l>
                  <l>He cannot faſt, this, this will ſpoile his mirth,</l>
                  <l>And hinder his enjoyment on this Earth,</l>
                  <l>Which prizeth pleaſures, and at greateſt coſt</l>
                  <l>Them to endulge, although at laſt he's toſh</l>
                  <l>Into the Dungeon, 'mongſt eternal pains,</l>
                  <l>The juſt reward of his licentious ſtrains.</l>
                  <l>So hard it is for to correct our blood</l>
                  <l>To leave the world, and follow that is good.</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62740:28"/>
                  <l>The blandiſhments of ſence invalids bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And robs us of the fruits of happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Fruits that attends endeavors, if we took</l>
                  <l>A Serious proſpect, and with care would look</l>
                  <l>Into the ways of virtue, we might ſpie</l>
                  <l>The ſad effects of vain morality,</l>
                  <l>Which are but tinkling Simbals to our ears,</l>
                  <l>Though fill'd with muſick, it may end in tears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet how many are there that pretend</l>
                  <l>To follow Chriſt, and will their ways amend;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſtill are ſtrangers to his footſteps pure,</l>
                  <l>Treading their own tracts, and can not endure</l>
                  <l>Sound councel, but do beat theſe pathes anew</l>
                  <l>Scarce ever trod, but lately with a crew</l>
                  <l>Of confident aſſertors, that can find</l>
                  <l>A nearer pathe, which more diſturbs the mind</l>
                  <l>In their blind zeals they do too boldly ſay,</l>
                  <l>That th'holy Martyr'd fathers miſt the way.</l>
                  <l>They think they have a neerer cut to Heaven,</l>
                  <l>And that a better guide to them is given,</l>
                  <l>Then Chriſt and his diſciples, their new light,</l>
                  <l>Indeed will lead them to eternal night.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So various is their zeal, and given to change,</l>
                  <l>Which make them wander, and moſt fondly range</l>
                  <l>To find freſh oyl, for to enflame new light,</l>
                  <l>Though meet impoſtures, yet they think them right;</l>
                  <l>Scorn ancient foot-ſteps, and approved form</l>
                  <l>Of holy Church, which doth ſo much adorn</l>
                  <l>The grandure of true worſhip, but they'l find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meanders,</hi> and <hi>Euthuſiaſts</hi> ſtill are blind,</l>
                  <l>For in the darkneſs they do ſadly grope,</l>
                  <l>And for to find the door, they'r ſans all hope:</l>
                  <l>Wanting good government to keep them in,</l>
                  <l>From their blind zeal, the occaſion of their ſin.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62740:28"/>
                  <l>But hear the poor Man doth not make delay:</l>
                  <l>To come to Chriſt, who is the perſect way;</l>
                  <l>His humble reſolutions, he did preſs</l>
                  <l>In begging confidence, he made addreſs.</l>
                  <l>How vile am I, O Lord, thou only know'ſt,</l>
                  <l>Oh! I will follow thee where e're thou goeſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So raiſe our ſouls from off the world, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>In ſeeking thee, we friendly may accord.</l>
                  <l>Thou art aſcended to thy heavenly Throne,</l>
                  <l>Where all true joyes are lodg'd in thee a lone.</l>
                  <l>O draw our ſouls in raptures of thy love,</l>
                  <l>And ſpiritual exhalations from above;</l>
                  <l>That may enrich our ſouls, and make us be,</l>
                  <l>True converts ſhunning ſin, and following thee,</l>
                  <l>Which art the only fountain from whence ſprings</l>
                  <l>All ſtreams of mercy, thou art King of Kings.</l>
                  <l>Grant us admittance, for to wait on thee,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall our ſouls enjoy eternity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poems">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62740:29"/>
               <p>Sir <hi>Anthony Bateman</hi> being then a Priſoner in the Houſe, lay the next Chamber to the Author, He having received the ſad, and ſudden news of the death of his beloved Daughter, which died the Tenth day of <hi>December</hi> laſt. It being the very day Twelve moneth, that her Mother the Lady <hi>Bateman</hi> died, and neer about the ſame hour the day before. The deceaſed was much buſied about thoughts of death, and writ her Will, and ſomething about ordering her funeral, yet went to bed, Seemingly much grieved, and very p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>. The Author to comfort him writ as followeth.</p>
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>SIR, Death hath ſurprized your Daughter, ſo that ſhe</l>
                     <l>Thereby's tranſlated to eternity.</l>
                     <l>Her virtues follow her, that golden Chain,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe links are pureſt gold, doth ſtill remain</l>
                     <l>Unblemiſt, her pure ſoul, with joy to find</l>
                     <l>A heavenly reſt, her charitable mind</l>
                     <l>Richly rewarded is with heavenly treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Her ſorrows turn'd to joyes, beyond all meaſure.</l>
                     <l>Her mirth is endleſs, and ſhe doth aſpire,</l>
                     <l>To ſing ſweet Anthems in the heavenly quire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ceaſe then your tears, and forbear thus to grieve,</l>
                     <l>She's gone before, where death hath no reprieve.</l>
                     <l>VVe all muſt follow her, no writ can move,</l>
                     <l>Our day of hearing's fixt in heaven above;</l>
                     <l>VVhere Angels can chant forth praiſes, and ſtill ſing</l>
                     <l>Moſt divine Anthems to our God and King.</l>
                     <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> which ſhe bears apart (I hope) on high,</l>
                     <l>VVhere Saints are crown'd with bliſs eternally.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="elegy">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62740:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Elogy on the name and death of the virtnous Lady</hi> Martha Bateman, <hi>who departed this life the Tenth of</hi> Decemb. 1674.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Moſt happy Saint, by the eternals will</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the Gods, where thou art ever ſtill</l>
                     <l>Rankt with the heavenly ſitters, moſt ſublime,</l>
                     <l>To teach us mortals, that abuſe our time</l>
                     <l>Here in this vail of Earth, where we may ſee,</l>
                     <l>As in thy mirror, how weak, and frail we be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But now a flower of a ſweet fragrant ſmell</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the roſes, anon the paſſing bell,</l>
                     <l>Tolls the ſad ditty of her laſt farewel,</l>
                     <l>Even under the ſore pangs of mortal death,</l>
                     <l>Moſt willingly ſurrenders up her breath;</l>
                     <l>Altering her earthly ſhape, ſhe did lie down,</l>
                     <l>Natures frail caſe for a celeſtial Crown.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>Nature expoſtulating with death.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Grim death! why doſt thou aim thy fiery dart,</l>
                     <l>In ſo direct a poſture at my heart?</l>
                     <l>Be not miſtaken, My fleſh is tender,</l>
                     <l>And will not yet admit of a ſurrender</l>
                     <l>Of my pure vitals, why ſo cruel bent,</l>
                     <l>'gainſt this afflicted family for thy rent?</l>
                     <l>For to exact it the ſame day, ô why ſo cruel?</l>
                     <l>Might hot my deareſt Mothers precious Jewel</l>
                     <l>Be price enough, to ſtay thy angry fate</l>
                     <l>But muſt purſue her iſſue with thy hate?</l>
                     <l>And that ſame very Tenth day of <hi>December,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Muſt our ſad family with ſobbs remember.</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:62740:30"/>
                     <l>Ah is it ſo, be not in haſt to kill</l>
                     <l>My panting heart, O let me write my Will.</l>
                     <l>Let me have nought to do but ſigh, and die</l>
                     <l>Then farewel mortal, come immortality.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Into which joyes no prying eye can peep,</l>
                     <l>It is beyond our knowledge, and too deep</l>
                     <l>To ſearch into, ô lets a while admire</l>
                     <l>Her great perfections, that did thus inſpire</l>
                     <l>Her more diviner ſoul, that did prepare</l>
                     <l>Her funeral, and friends with love, and care.</l>
                     <l>Her earthly part ſhe did, as ſleep lay down,</l>
                     <l>Her temporal for a Celeſtial Crown;</l>
                     <l>So that henceforth it truly may be ſaid,</l>
                     <l>She is tranſplanted, rather than decayed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:30"/>
            <p>Meditations, written by <hi>William Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> Gentleman, Priſoner in the Kings Bench, <hi>Anno</hi> 1676.</p>
            <p>And in the ſixty third year of his age.</p>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:31"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62740:31"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Numbers 27.16, 17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Let the Lord, the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, ſet a Man over the congregation. Which may go out before them, and which may go in before them, and which may lead them out, and which may bring them in; that the congregation of the Lord be not as ſheep which have no ſhepherd.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId God command good <hi>Moſes</hi> to aſcend</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Abarim</hi> mount, unto that very end</l>
                  <l>To ſee the promiſed Land? did he not expreſs,</l>
                  <l>How that he ſinned in the wilderneſs,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Meribab?</hi> was he denied poſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Canan's</hi> land, for this his his foul trangreſſion?</l>
                  <l>The which he ſhall no ſooner ſee, but die,</l>
                  <l>Yet ceas'd he not unto the Lord to cry.</l>
                  <l>Let God, the Lord of ſpirits continue on,</l>
                  <l>A ſhepherd to the congregation.</l>
                  <l>Did not the Lord ſoon grant to his requeſt</l>
                  <l>Behold, take <hi>Joſhua</hi> my ſpirit's in his breſt,</l>
                  <l>But lay thine hands upon him, give him charge</l>
                  <l>In preſence of the people (not at large.)</l>
                  <l>Set him before <hi>Eleazar</hi> the chief prieſt,</l>
                  <l>He hath the <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> thou ſeeſt:</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62740:32"/>
                  <l>Let all go in, and out at his ſole word,</l>
                  <l>Yea all the congregation of the Lord.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> obeys, ſets <hi>Joſhua</hi> in their ſight,</l>
                  <l>Lays on his hands with reverence and might.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold, this miſſion did the Lord want power</l>
                  <l>To ſend out <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> at that very hour.</l>
                  <l>Needed he the help of <hi>Moſes</hi> to compleat,</l>
                  <l>A holy prieſthood to ſucceed his feat?</l>
                  <l>Needed he the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> to confirm</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed orders and decrees of Heaven?</l>
                  <l>No, 'twas his wiſedom to make all to know;</l>
                  <l>That God's the God of order, to which we owe</l>
                  <l>All poſſible obedience, with ſubmiſſion,</l>
                  <l>To his bleſt precepts, taking a commiſſion,</l>
                  <l>And run not on, in a furious preſumption,</l>
                  <l>Scorning all order and the holy unction.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did not this tipe in <hi>Meſes</hi> repreſent</l>
                  <l>Chriſt's miſſion to his holy Government</l>
                  <l>Of his ſucceeding Church, T'adorn the Station;</l>
                  <l>VVhen Chriſt bids go, and preach to every Nation,</l>
                  <l>His Apoſtles boldly went, and not till then,</l>
                  <l>They were not made the bleſt fiſhers of Men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſtop, thou bold Intruder, Learn and heark,</l>
                  <l>VVas not <hi>Uzzah</hi> ſtruck for touching the Ark</l>
                  <l>VVithout a Call, Let his Example learn</l>
                  <l>The meekneſs, that thou may'ſt truly diſcern</l>
                  <l>The way of order, continued in all ages,</l>
                  <l>And is from thence deſcended to the ſages,</l>
                  <l>And Governors of the Church, it doth preſerve</l>
                  <l>A holy Miniſtry, faithfully to ſerve</l>
                  <l>As Miniſtring ſpirits, truly to repreſent</l>
                  <l>Our dayly wants, and help us to repent</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62740:32"/>
                  <l>And bewail the times, never be at reſt</l>
                  <l>Still praying to ſend laborers in the harveſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No prayers ſo needful in this preſumptuous age,</l>
                  <l>When perſons run like players on a ſtage;</l>
                  <l>Venting their fancies, their vain ſhapes and guiſe,</l>
                  <l>Their fond deluſions, which amuſe the wiſe;</l>
                  <l>Who would not labor, and devoutly pray</l>
                  <l>To be freed from theſe blind leaders aſtray,</l>
                  <l>Which proudly prattle of their gifts and vaunt</l>
                  <l>Their inward calls, I compaſſionate their want</l>
                  <l>Of ſober meekneſs by which they may be,</l>
                  <l>Inſtructed in the rules of Modeſty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who can be hold this Garden become a field</l>
                  <l>For beaſts to revel in, and their hearts not yield</l>
                  <l>Compaſſionate tears, to ſee foxes pray</l>
                  <l>On ſilly lambs, and bear their ſouls away</l>
                  <l>To wild, and ſtrange deluſions by their prate,</l>
                  <l>And bold aſſertions do inſinuate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How vainly do they thus pretend new light,</l>
                  <l>When they do ſtrip their mother of her right,</l>
                  <l>And cry up the raſh fancies of their brain,</l>
                  <l>Beyond the decent holy goſpel ſtrain.</l>
                  <l>Can there be want of Laborers in this rout?</l>
                  <l>No, no, there are too many go about,</l>
                  <l>To lead away ſouls by their vain deluſion,</l>
                  <l>Thinking it zeal to bring in ſuch confuſion;</l>
                  <l>Where ſheep become ſhepherds, their brains are ſickle,</l>
                  <l>Preſumptuouſly handling the Goſpels ſickle,</l>
                  <l>Yea, he that can but talk in a Goſpel phraſe,</l>
                  <l>Doth think himſelf inſpir'd, but doth not pauſe</l>
                  <l>On the hid myſteries contain'd therein,</l>
                  <l>But vomits forth his ignorance and ſin,</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62740:33"/>
                  <l>And climbs a pulpit in ſome publick heard</l>
                  <l>And there to vent his folly is not affear'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that doth love his Saviour will delight</l>
                  <l>To honor his ſpouſe, the Church, and in her right</l>
                  <l>Lay out his intereſt, firmly to maintain</l>
                  <l>Her reverence, and eſteem, is all his aim,</l>
                  <l>And triumph in the felicity of her health,</l>
                  <l>And beg the perpetuity of her wealth;</l>
                  <l>In whoſe arms alone he can be mounted high,</l>
                  <l>Into the Throne of bleſt eternity.</l>
                  <l>He deſerveth not to be ſharer in bliſs,</l>
                  <l>That eternal harveſt of true happineſs,</l>
                  <l>That will not labor and devoutly pray</l>
                  <l>To ſend forth Laborers in that needful day,</l>
                  <l>And ſhepherds, that moſt faithfully will feed</l>
                  <l>Their flocks, and keep them in the time of need,</l>
                  <l>And ſave them from thoſe wolves that would devour</l>
                  <l>Their harmleſs lambs, if gotten in their power.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord, who can behold this bleeding ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>And not ſhed tears, and ev'n with fervor rouze</l>
                  <l>His very ſoul, in contemplation</l>
                  <l>Of this afflicted Church and Nation.</l>
                  <l>Shee that not long ſince, was but little leſs,</l>
                  <l>Than a Princeſs amongſt the provinces</l>
                  <l>Is become a widow, weeps ſore all night,</l>
                  <l>And is bereav'd of comfort, and her right.</l>
                  <l>Her lovers have forſaken her in ſuch ſort,</l>
                  <l>That many flout, few yield her true comfort.</l>
                  <l>She once, was worthy the kiſſes of his love,</l>
                  <l>That priz'd her highly as a Queen above.</l>
                  <l>And at her glory did no whit repine,</l>
                  <l>But magnified her love better than wine.</l>
                  <l>But now ſhe's black, but comely to the view</l>
                  <l>Of Heaven, though her locks are werted with the diew;</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62740:33"/>
                  <l>Yet is continued that ſweeter breath;</l>
                  <l>Tell me O thou, who my ſoul ſo loveth,</l>
                  <l>Where thou feedeſt, and ſets thy flocks to reſt,</l>
                  <l>Beſides the ſhepherds Tents, they are ſafe and bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such a ſweet dialogue the Church once had,</l>
                  <l>Though now grown pale with grief, heavy and ſad;</l>
                  <l>Yet is ſhe ſtill belov'd, though in mourning dreſs,</l>
                  <l>The time will come to caſt of heavyneſs.</l>
                  <l>Oh! let the accuſtomed mercies of thy love,</l>
                  <l>Protect thy Church from rapine, and remove</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Boars, and Foxes, that ſtrive to devour</l>
                  <l>Thy vine, Oh keep it by thy Almighty power</l>
                  <l>From envious ſtorms, for thou haſt plac't it high,</l>
                  <l>Where all may ſee it, and with hearts apply.</l>
                  <l>Oh! lets approach to it, not turn'd away</l>
                  <l>By ſuch blind guides, that vainly go aſtray.</l>
                  <l>Let ne're thy ſacred Oracles want power,</l>
                  <l>Nor prieſt to lead us, in our lateſt hour.</l>
                  <l>Nor let the gladſome tidings of our peace</l>
                  <l>Be turn'd to ſilence, Oh! let it never ceaſe</l>
                  <l>Thy holy Miniſtry, but, O Lord, ſupply</l>
                  <l>Their defects, pardon the wild vanity,</l>
                  <l>And ignorant phantaſtick zeal of thoſe;</l>
                  <l>That thus abuſe thy Church and are thy foes.</l>
                  <l>Give them true light, thy mercies quite diſpel,</l>
                  <l>That darkneſs which will lead them down to Hell.</l>
                  <l>Let us rejoyce in the Mercies of his love,</l>
                  <l>In ſending us his Son, which from above</l>
                  <l>Haſt left a holy Miniſtry to be our guide.</l>
                  <l>Oh keep us ſafe that we may never ſlide</l>
                  <l>Into ſuch pathes, that may lead us aſtray,</l>
                  <l>But follow our ſhepherds in a holy way;</l>
                  <l>And from a peeviſh zeal, good Lord, reſtore us,</l>
                  <l>And grant us ſhepherds, that may go before us.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62740:34"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 5.8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Bleſſed are the pure in heart for they ſhall ſee God <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>GOd of his abundant love, did ſend his Son</l>
                  <l>Into the world, to preach ſalvation</l>
                  <l>Upon the mount, whereon he freely taught</l>
                  <l>His bleſſed precepts, unto all that ſought</l>
                  <l>To him in faith, and obedience to his will,</l>
                  <l>Minding his holy precepts to fulfil.</l>
                  <l>He pronounced nine bleſſings with their recompence,</l>
                  <l>If we obſerve them with true reverence,</l>
                  <l>And keep his holy Lawes, not from it ſtart,</l>
                  <l>Surely bleſſed are they, are pure in heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who would not then ſtrive earneſt to be pure,</l>
                  <l>See David's fervent zeal for to aſſure</l>
                  <l>His panting ſoul, which long'd full ſore to find,</l>
                  <l>A place of reſt for his ſo grieved mind.</l>
                  <l>To attain the which, he paſſionately cri'd,</l>
                  <l>Lord, from thy precepts let me never ſlide.</l>
                  <l>That he would cleanſe his heart, he might inherit</l>
                  <l>The gifts, and graces of his holy ſpirit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hath piety ſuch a reward, no diſgrace?</l>
                  <l>Shall the pure in heart behold him face to face?</l>
                  <l>And with bleſt ſpirits ever happy raign</l>
                  <l>In endleſs glory, and true peace obtain.</l>
                  <l>Who will not labor to imitate the juſt,</l>
                  <l>VVho have ſuch heavenly viſions in their duſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62740:34"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Shall the treacherous vanities we enjoy</l>
                  <l>Steal off our hearts, and rob us of true joy,</l>
                  <l>And bereave us of the glory of that light,</l>
                  <l>VVhich is of endleſs ſplendor, power, and might;</l>
                  <l>So ſtrengthen me, That I may rather chooſe</l>
                  <l>The divine light, and all falſe lights refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſight the which in glory doth ſurpaſs,</l>
                  <l>All triumphs in the world that ever was.</l>
                  <l>VVhat ſplenders are there, compared to this,</l>
                  <l>It is an empty air, Nothing leſs;</l>
                  <l>A ſight which no eye ever ſaw, but may</l>
                  <l>If the worlds objects lead them not aſtray,</l>
                  <l>After the harmony of deluding Charms,</l>
                  <l>VVhich lulls frail fleſh a ſleep in natures arms.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Idea</hi> of this ſight cannot be drawn</l>
                  <l>In lively colors, leaſt we do prophane;</l>
                  <l>The ſpeculations of the brain can never</l>
                  <l>Portract him truly, that doth live for ever.</l>
                  <l>Then ceaſe thy fancie, and forbear thy art,</l>
                  <l>His liveleſs Character is in thy heart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The divine Traveller, though but newly there,</l>
                  <l>Could give no full deſcription of that ſphear.</l>
                  <l>Scripture Characters doth but even allude,</l>
                  <l>And ſet it forth but in ſimilitude.</l>
                  <l>And ſhew, how infinitely tranſcendent</l>
                  <l>Is that glory, which is omnipotent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVere diamonds all join'd, to make one ſplendor,</l>
                  <l>They were but Attoms to the Sun, not render</l>
                  <l>The ſmalleſt glimps, to that luminary</l>
                  <l>Of life and heat, the which by motions vary,</l>
                  <l>And feed a throng of ſparkling ſtars, that are</l>
                  <l>Inlivened with his light, which from a far</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62740:35"/>
                  <l>VVe do behold, each one in's proper place,</l>
                  <l>How dim's it to the glory of thy face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVho then would thus ſo vainly ſacrifies</l>
                  <l>Himſelf to ſin; and ſo bewreave his eyes</l>
                  <l>Of that bleſt viſion, and the chiefeſt good,</l>
                  <l>To gratifie his wild extravagant blood,</l>
                  <l>And revel in delights of ſin and ſhame,</l>
                  <l>And ſtiffle his nobler paſſions, and that flame</l>
                  <l>Of holy zeal, that ſhould chiefly delight us:</l>
                  <l>To the triumphs of thy bliſs, Good Lord unite us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that would dwell amongſt thoſe ſacred fires,</l>
                  <l>And holy ſpirits, by whoſe true light inſpires</l>
                  <l>The mind with holy motions, he muſt turn</l>
                  <l>His heart unto an altar, and their burn</l>
                  <l>The holy ſacrifice of penitence,</l>
                  <l>And lively faith, with all due reverence,</l>
                  <l>And humbleneſs of heart, which will do well,</l>
                  <l>For the graces of Gods ſpirit there do dwell.</l>
                  <l>The heart that mourns within us, there muſt be</l>
                  <l>The only ſeat of life, and love to thee.</l>
                  <l>The graces of the ſpirit there muſt reſt,</l>
                  <l>And be ſo firmly fixed in the breſt.</l>
                  <l>Naturaliſts, do well obſerve, that to the heart</l>
                  <l>Is firſt giv'n life, then death it doth them part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord, our hearts are frail, there cannot be</l>
                  <l>Strength to ſupport, unleſs it come from thee:</l>
                  <l>Give thy ſupporting graces, we are weak;</l>
                  <l>Touch thou our hearts and tongues, that we may ſpeak</l>
                  <l>To the glory of thy name, and ſo diſpiſe</l>
                  <l>The vanities of the world, with its diſguiſe.</l>
                  <l>O raiſe our contemplations to thy glory,</l>
                  <l>Caſt down our vain affections tranſitory;</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62740:35"/>
                  <l>That proudly do oppoſe it ſelf in error,</l>
                  <l>Correct our thoughts, oh let it be a terror</l>
                  <l>Unto our hearts, and make us plainly ſee</l>
                  <l>The horror of our crimes, Lord againſt thee.</l>
                  <l>Sanctifie to thy ſelf our whole devotion,</l>
                  <l>That we live holy lives in godly motion.</l>
                  <l>Oh let our chiefeſt contemplations raiſe,</l>
                  <l>A holy zeal in us to give thee praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Let it be our delight to do thy will,</l>
                  <l>And all thy holy precepts to fulfill</l>
                  <l>That when we ſhall lay down our lives in duſt,</l>
                  <l>VVe may be glorified with the Juſt.</l>
                  <l>And ſweetly ſeated in that bleſſed place.</l>
                  <l>VVhere we may all behold thee face to face.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Daniel 12.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the Brightneſs of the firmament and they that turn many to Righteouſneſs as the Stars for ever and ever.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId Michael th'archangel not ſtir thence,</l>
                  <l>But ſtood moſt valiant, like a mighty prince,</l>
                  <l>To aſſiſt Gods people in their times of trouble,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid their ſufferings would be requited double.</l>
                  <l>If that their hearts would be to wiſdom bent,</l>
                  <l>Should ſhine for ever in the firmament,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as by their pious pains do turn</l>
                  <l>Others from ſin, ſo that they ſigh, and mourn</l>
                  <l>Shall ſhine as ſtarrs, and be for ever bleſt</l>
                  <l>VVith glory, in everlaſting reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62740:36"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who then would not be ſtudious for to gain</l>
                  <l>True knowledge, that he might thereby attain</l>
                  <l>Such promiſed glory, and become moſt pure,</l>
                  <l>Holy, Celeſtial, to be ever ſure</l>
                  <l>To ſhine forth, as the Sun, oh bleſſed ſight!</l>
                  <l>In whoſe moſt glorious raies is the chief light:</l>
                  <l>Where mans diviner part not only lives,</l>
                  <l>As living ſplendor, it for ever gives</l>
                  <l>Tranſcending beams of luſtre, which ſhall ſhine</l>
                  <l>In the imperial heavens, moſt divine,</l>
                  <l>And there be ever fixt, and never ſever,</l>
                  <l>But ſhine as ſtars for ever, and for ever.</l>
                  <l>Look here, ye blind admirers of Earths bubble,</l>
                  <l>A robe of purple, or ſome glorious trouble,</l>
                  <l>A diadem of honor in this Earth,</l>
                  <l>Which brings forth care, ſmall comfort after death.</l>
                  <l>So vain is Man, that fondly doth deſire</l>
                  <l>Such trifling honors, that do ſoon expire;</l>
                  <l>Which carrieth not that light will give acceſs,</l>
                  <l>And by its virtue turn to righteouſneſs,</l>
                  <l>Which would make them Stars, but ſome deſire t'enjoy</l>
                  <l>Their fading pleaſures, ſuch a ſplendid toy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hear this all ye, that can on ſhadows dote,</l>
                  <l>And you that can to Tranſitory pomp devote</l>
                  <l>Your ſouls, and care not for immortal bliſs,</l>
                  <l>And think there is no other Heaven but this.</l>
                  <l>Sublunary pleaſures, couldſt thou call down</l>
                  <l>A robe of morning Stars to deck thee round.</l>
                  <l>Such Royal luminaries it would be</l>
                  <l>But gloomy ſplendor, a bright obſcurity</l>
                  <l>Compared to that luſtre, 'Twill ſhine but faint,</l>
                  <l>Not like that glory, that enwraps a Saint.</l>
                  <l>That azure ſpangled Heaven, which we do ſee,</l>
                  <l>Where the magazin of Stars ſo fixed be,</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62740:36"/>
                  <l>Which ſtocks the world with light, its but a vail</l>
                  <l>Or curtain drawn, to keep our ſences frail,</l>
                  <l>From over prying into th'almighties Throne,</l>
                  <l>Where only is felicity alone.</l>
                  <l>Which no eye ever ſaw, nor yet ſhall ſee,</l>
                  <l>The hidden glories of eternity.</l>
                  <l>Tombs are but wardrops, or Chambers of death,</l>
                  <l>Hung'd with their winding ſheets beneath the Earth,</l>
                  <l>Where we ſhall all after this life be laid,</l>
                  <l>Till to our fathers we be gathered.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that ſame heavenly glimps, which did appear</l>
                  <l>Upon the mount, did the diſciples chear,</l>
                  <l>Which made them wiſh, that they might there ſtrait raiſe</l>
                  <l>Three Tabernacles to eternal praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And there abide. Oh if that beauty then</l>
                  <l>Reveal'd from Heaven unto theſe bleſſed Men</l>
                  <l>Was ſo Tranſcendent, how will th'enjoyment be!</l>
                  <l>Oh raviſh us with deſires, that we may ſee</l>
                  <l>Where Chriſt is gone before, 'twas the Martyrs Joy</l>
                  <l>Amid their tortures, valued as a toy,</l>
                  <l>Though their limbs were broken, and mangled,</l>
                  <l>Yet they were ſure their hairs were numbred.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>Peters</hi> ſhadow had that healing power</l>
                  <l>To cure the ſick, which applied to him each hour,</l>
                  <l>How powerful is that ſhining glory then,</l>
                  <l>Which doth ſuch wonders for the Sons of Men.</l>
                  <l>Let no one doubt, nor be at any ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>If once his name be in the book of life.</l>
                  <l>Though his earthly Tabernacle be laid down,</l>
                  <l>Yet he ſhall have an everlaſting Crown</l>
                  <l>Of endleſs glory, beyond expreſſion far,</l>
                  <l>And ſhine in Heaven like a glorious Star.</l>
                  <l>Who is it would not ſlight, and diſregard</l>
                  <l>The vanities of this life for ſuch reward,</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62740:37"/>
                  <l>And welcome poverty with all its chains,</l>
                  <l>And triumph in the aſſurance of ſuch gains.</l>
                  <l>As that nobly divine tranſcendent love,</l>
                  <l>That is prepared in the Heavens above,</l>
                  <l>Where there's aſſurance for to live for ever,</l>
                  <l>And ſweetly reſt in the boſom of the father.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou didſt create us Lord, for to ſerve thee,</l>
                  <l>But by our frailties we'r become to be</l>
                  <l>For ever loſt. But thou of thy great love,</l>
                  <l>Didſt reſtore us to true joyes above</l>
                  <l>Oh fill us with meditations of thy praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Which may elevate our ſpirits all our days;</l>
                  <l>That we may walk in ſome meaſure divine,</l>
                  <l>That by a holy practice we may ſhine,</l>
                  <l>As Stars in the lower orb, and expreſs that light,</l>
                  <l>We have by faith received by thy might,</l>
                  <l>And power divine, Oh let our hearts be ever</l>
                  <l>Filled with praiſes, and be ſilent never;</l>
                  <l>And ſtill expreſs our thanks and not have done,</l>
                  <l>Until we ſhine in brightneſs, like the Sun,</l>
                  <l>And from a holy walking never ſever</l>
                  <l>But ſhine as Stars for ever and for ever.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 2.10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And when they ſaw the Star they Rejoyced with exceeding great Joy.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>I'm ſtill ſurpriz'd with wonder, at the love</l>
                  <l>Of our offended God, that from above</l>
                  <l>Should ſhew his Star to wiſe men of the Faſt,</l>
                  <l>Which welcom'd ſuch an object, did not reſt,</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62740:37"/>
                  <l>But gave it reverence, with an holy fear,</l>
                  <l>They well knowing the motions of the ſphear.</l>
                  <l>That bleſſed object, that unwanted Star,</l>
                  <l>Which they did with much joy behold, from far</l>
                  <l>And there was kindled in them a deſire</l>
                  <l>To poſt unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to enquire,</l>
                  <l>Where's he that is born King, we've ſeen his Star,</l>
                  <l>To worſhip him with joy, are come from far?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> ſeem'd troubled at ſuch ſudden news,</l>
                  <l>And all the congregation of the <hi>Jews;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On went theſe Men, the Star being ſtill their guide</l>
                  <l>It reſted where the bleſſed Babe was laid;</l>
                  <l>There they rejoyce, no frights did them annoy,</l>
                  <l>Seeing the Star, they had exceeding joy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rouſe then my ſoul, in a holy contemplation</l>
                  <l>Of this bright Star whoſe radiant beams and motion</l>
                  <l>Did quickly ſpread it ſelf <hi>Judea</hi> over,</l>
                  <l>Its powerful influence did ſoon diſcover</l>
                  <l>Divine effects, that it did fully tend</l>
                  <l>To be a tipe of mercy, to the end</l>
                  <l>To ſave loſt Man, oh beauteous Star of light,</l>
                  <l>The effects whereof will keep us from that night</l>
                  <l>Of utter darkneſs, in which we all lay hid,</l>
                  <l>And by it's mercy ſhall be glorifi'd!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had the ancients known this Star't would raiſe their ſence</l>
                  <l>And enrich their genius with due reverence.</l>
                  <l>This ſparkling ſplendor did ſurely outſhine</l>
                  <l>The knowledge of that age, it was divine.</l>
                  <l>T'was ſuch a luſtre, That it did adorn</l>
                  <l>The orb, beyond the glory of the morn.</l>
                  <l>That powerful luminary that directeth time,</l>
                  <l>That bleſſed morning Star, ſhin'd more divine,</l>
                  <l>And prov'd a happy guide, them ſafe to bring,</l>
                  <l>With holy offerings unto Chriſt their King.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62740:38"/>
                  <l>And in a joynt harmony with one voice,</l>
                  <l>They having ſeen the Star did much rejoyce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See how theſe pagans footed it, what pain</l>
                  <l>They took in travel for that happy gain</l>
                  <l>And bleſt fruition of that g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orious fight</l>
                  <l>Though poor, is full of Majeſty, and might.</l>
                  <l>They nimbly walk from the remoteſt parts</l>
                  <l>In pure devotion, and with chearful hearts;</l>
                  <l>When ſome that boldly do profeſs thy name,</l>
                  <l>Will ſcarce come forth their chamber: O! the ſhame</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch beſotted ſouls, as will not riſe,</l>
                  <l>And proſtrate themſelves, before the eyes</l>
                  <l>Of their offended God, though ne're ſo cheap,</l>
                  <l>But ſnug and ſnore in ſin, and fondly heap</l>
                  <l>Crime upon crime, not from their vices part,</l>
                  <l>Though th'offering ſmall, an humble penitent heart.</l>
                  <l>But theſe wiſe Travellers did freely bring,</l>
                  <l>Gold, Frankenſcence, and Myrrhe, to Chriſt the King,</l>
                  <l>And made an Inn a Temple, there to pay</l>
                  <l>Their tribute, O the miſerable delay</l>
                  <l>Of pure devotion! 'Tis their greater ſhame,</l>
                  <l>That ſtript him of the glory of his name,</l>
                  <l>It ſhould exalt all hearts for to rejoyce</l>
                  <l>With adoration, and a thankful voice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They'd but one ſingle Star to be their guide,</l>
                  <l>But we have many, that with active pride</l>
                  <l>Do darken religion, and have it in deriſion.</l>
                  <l>Such quaking Comets making an apparition</l>
                  <l>And fiery aſpect, that will fright away,</l>
                  <l>Rather than lead, will cauſe us go aſtray</l>
                  <l>Into their ſottiſh errors, to prevent</l>
                  <l>Lets keep cloſe to the holy government;</l>
                  <l>Which Chriſt, and his Apoſtles left behind,</l>
                  <l>To rectifie the errors of mankind;</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62740:38"/>
                  <l>Which if we practice, and ſtudy aright,</l>
                  <l>We need not fear Sathan with all his might.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pretended illuminations in religion</l>
                  <l>Eclipſeth real light, with foul deriſion,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a naſty Miſt doth often gather,</l>
                  <l>That in ſtead of clearing Eyes do blind them rather,</l>
                  <l>'Twas a true light by which the wiſemen ſteer'd,</l>
                  <l>Which brought them in ſuch triumph, that it cheer'd</l>
                  <l>Their hearts with joy, that they did ſee the day,</l>
                  <l>Which ſome do ſtudy, to forget, and lay</l>
                  <l>A load of obliquy on ſuch pretence,</l>
                  <l>Not allowing it a day of reverence.</l>
                  <l>But let them wallow in their haughty pride,</l>
                  <l>It prov'd a bleſſed day, and happy guide</l>
                  <l>To unwearied Travellers, but for ſuch as they</l>
                  <l>That ſottiſhly, and wildly run a ſtray,</l>
                  <l>And have no Star to guide them, but let them wander,</l>
                  <l>And fall in their own pitts, that thus do ſlander.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou that haſt ſtockt the world with ſo much light,</l>
                  <l>And enricht it with ſo many Stars ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve us Mortals, 'Twas fit thou ſhouldſt take</l>
                  <l>One to thy ſelf, thy herald for to make,</l>
                  <l>And cauſe the brightneſs of that Star ſurpaſs,</l>
                  <l>All other Stars that now, and ever was.</l>
                  <l>To declare thy birth all creatures do obey,</l>
                  <l>Save us wild Mortals, that do vainly ſtray,</l>
                  <l>And ſtop our Eares to the harmony of thy law.</l>
                  <l>But theſe wiſe Men inſpir'd, no ſooner ſaw</l>
                  <l>The Star of light, which did foretell thy birth,</l>
                  <l>But immediately did run with Joy and Mirth,</l>
                  <l>And grew angry with time, leaſt it delay</l>
                  <l>To begin their Journey in that happy day;</l>
                  <l>Which to direct, a Star became their guide,</l>
                  <l>And attracts their Eyes, which in a holy pride,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62740:39"/>
                  <l>They ſtill lift up with reverence to behold</l>
                  <l>With humble zeal, this Myſtery to unfold.</l>
                  <l>Oh Lord, ſo elevate our eys to thee,</l>
                  <l>Which art the Star of bleſt eternity,</l>
                  <l>And take us from the vain delights of ſin,</l>
                  <l>And kindle an holy fire of faith within</l>
                  <l>Of love and zeal, oh let his mercy great</l>
                  <l>Raviſh our ſouls with Joy, let us repeat</l>
                  <l>Loud <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> to thy name, and ſing</l>
                  <l>Moſt thankful Anthems for our Chriſt and King.</l>
                  <l>As the good wiſe Men with a chearful voice,</l>
                  <l>Having ſeen the Star exceedingly rejoyce.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 12.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Fear God and keep his Commandments for this is the whole duty of Man.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat needs the preacher more, is not this verſe</l>
                  <l>It ſelf, a ſermon, why ſhould he rehearſe</l>
                  <l>So many precepts, but he doth eſpie</l>
                  <l>Mans weak eſtate, ſubject to vanity;</l>
                  <l>Therefore he taught the people to take heed</l>
                  <l>And ſhun diſorders, every evil deed,</l>
                  <l>He wiſely ſought out all due means to find</l>
                  <l>Words acceptable, that would pleaſe the mind,</l>
                  <l>That with Compliance with them, he might gain</l>
                  <l>Upon them to believe, all things are vain,</l>
                  <l>Save to fear God, and ſerve him all we can,</l>
                  <l>This is the all that is required of Man.</l>
                  <l>And yet how few are they that will obſerve</l>
                  <l>This precept as a duty, though it ſerve</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62740:39"/>
                  <l>To their advantage, in that great great day,</l>
                  <l>When all Mankind formed of Earth and clay</l>
                  <l>Shall cited be before the glorious Throne</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt the lamb, who then ſhall Judge alone.</l>
                  <l>Oh be adviſ'd in time to take delight,</l>
                  <l>To adore thy maker, ſtudy it aright,</l>
                  <l>And be in love with wiſedome, and her ways,</l>
                  <l>Living to God, unto his dayly praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Glorifie him alone, above all things,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall he ſhroud thee under his bleſt wings.</l>
                  <l>Thy labor ſhall be gain, no time miſpent,</l>
                  <l>Then fear thy God and keep his Commandment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ah! how few there be of Davids ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>That prize Gods laws, and would indeed inherit</l>
                  <l>Eternal bliſs, which he did meditate</l>
                  <l>Both day, and night, and often ſadly ſat</l>
                  <l>Wailing his ſins, but we delight to break</l>
                  <l>His holy law, opening our mouths to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Rudely of God, his worſhip and his lore,</l>
                  <l>Letting our tongues run laviſh on that ſcore,</l>
                  <l>We pray not him to cloſe our vainer lips,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill give way to vent thoſe frothy ſlips,</l>
                  <l>That dayly ariſe from our Corrupted heart,</l>
                  <l>All which expoſes us to the biting ſmart</l>
                  <l>Of his ſevereſt Juſtice, thus poor Man</l>
                  <l>Ruins himſelf, not doing what he can.</l>
                  <l>Some think it is an honor to fly high</l>
                  <l>In vile attempts, and looſe debauchery,</l>
                  <l>And to be bold in ſins affecting oaths,</l>
                  <l>Like to vile Atheiſts, that are virtues foes.</l>
                  <l>Which count it valor for to ſtab religion,</l>
                  <l>Having its practice in ſuch vile deriſion,</l>
                  <l>And make a paradox of the preachers wit,</l>
                  <l>A meer Apocrypha, and jeer at it,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62740:40"/>
                  <l>And Scandalize the law, and them that ſpeak it,</l>
                  <l>And think it but a piece of wit to break it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is no wonder Atheiſm doth abound,</l>
                  <l>And that religion ſadly falls to ground.</l>
                  <l>Search all the ancient records page by page,</l>
                  <l>Vice ne'r engendred ſo, in any age.</l>
                  <l>The VVorld ne'r multiply'd ſo much in ſects,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe Men don't fully conſult this text.</l>
                  <l>Prophaneneſs it deſcendsby propagation,</l>
                  <l>In next poſterity this vitious Nation</l>
                  <l>Is like to be of a heatheniſh complexion,</l>
                  <l>If God prevent not by our due ſubjection</l>
                  <l>To his bleſt law, Atheiſm will gather ground,</l>
                  <l>And Men grow proud, becauſe the'r Atheiſts found.</l>
                  <l>Bold ſons of Belial glory will in it,</l>
                  <l>And boaſt in ſlighting as a piece of wit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Do ye blind followers of the world intend</l>
                  <l>To laugh at Heaven, and therein your time ſpend,</l>
                  <l>And make divinity a cloak to cover</l>
                  <l>Your fouler parts, that none may them diſcover</l>
                  <l>Your outſiide piety, and cunning trades,</l>
                  <l>Your ſpecious ſhews, and guilded pious frauds.</l>
                  <l>No, no, you cannot thus delude the Eye</l>
                  <l>Of the all ſeeing God, he will eſpy</l>
                  <l>Your want of zeal, though painted fair they be,</l>
                  <l>There's nothing hid from him that all things ſee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord, how ſadly do we thus forget</l>
                  <l>To do thee homage, and to pay the debt</l>
                  <l>VVe owe unto thy love, that didſt make</l>
                  <l>Thine only Son an offering for our ſake.</l>
                  <l>But like ungrateful wretches we do ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Moſt rudely ſcoff at thy revealed will,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62740:40"/>
                  <l>And caſt thy precepts from us, which ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Our guide unto the bleſt eternity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good God! it was thy bounty to beſtow</l>
                  <l>Gifts of reaſon on us, for which we owe</l>
                  <l>All thanks unto thee, for ſo great a boon,</l>
                  <l>VVhich we do miſemploy much much too ſoon;</l>
                  <l>Turning our reaſon 'gainſt thy Laws moſt right,</l>
                  <l>And act diſorderly with all our might.</l>
                  <l>Teach us to ſee our failings, and endeavor</l>
                  <l>To hearken to that voice, that lives for ever,</l>
                  <l>That the Oratory of thy ſacred word,</l>
                  <l>May win us to thy Love with one accord,</l>
                  <l>Renounce prophaneneſs, planting in its place</l>
                  <l>Deſired virtue, and each heavenly grace.</l>
                  <l>Let not blind heathens, which do not know thee,</l>
                  <l>Out ſtrip us in their moral honeſty.</l>
                  <l>Then we, which have ſure hopes by faith and love,</l>
                  <l>To be received into the joyes above;</l>
                  <l>As thou doſt by thy holy word reveal</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf in Chriſt, to whom alone appeal</l>
                  <l>Is to be made, make us to underſtand,</l>
                  <l>The advantages we have from thy good hand</l>
                  <l>Of mercy, grant our minds be fully bent</l>
                  <l>To fear our God, and keep his Commandment,</l>
                  <l>VVith all the holy fervency we can;</l>
                  <l>This duty is required from every Man.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62740:41"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 8.2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And behold! there came a Leaper and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him, ſaying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>SIn 's an infectious <hi>Leprofie</hi> that is ſpread</l>
                  <l>It ſelf all over from the foot, to head.</l>
                  <l>Is this the <hi>Leapers</hi> prayer only, no</l>
                  <l>It is all ſinners too, that have let go</l>
                  <l>The rains of virtue that it ſhould reſtrain</l>
                  <l>All vitious ways unto an holy aim.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that had ſeen the <hi>Leapers</hi> body over,</l>
                  <l>VVould think his prayer proper to diſcover</l>
                  <l>His loathſome parts, and yet would he but view</l>
                  <l>His ſoul, he'l find it of a blacker hiew.</l>
                  <l>A ſadder object to affright his ſence</l>
                  <l>VVith horror, if he ſtrickly look from whence</l>
                  <l>It did proceed, O the miſeries of his blood,</l>
                  <l>VVhich loſt its verdor, and became a flood</l>
                  <l>Of putrid nurtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re, yet it mov'd guilt,</l>
                  <l>To cry with faith, Oh Lord, if that thou wilt!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And he whoſe never failing goodneſs lacks</l>
                  <l>To ſhew compaſſion, and it never ſlacks</l>
                  <l>His power and mercy, where it is concern'd</l>
                  <l>To cure thoſe limbs, that were fully diſcern'd</l>
                  <l>To be already ſo, o'rewhelm'd with grief,</l>
                  <l>That was new bath'd by it, receiv'd relief</l>
                  <l>By the bounty of a touch, he was made clean,</l>
                  <l>VVhich was before both loathſome, and obſcene,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62740:41"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus, thus the <hi>Leapers</hi> bodied a new,</l>
                  <l>But we don't ſee what good there doth accrue</l>
                  <l>Unto his better parts, and that perhaps</l>
                  <l>Lies bed-rid in a very ſad relaps.</l>
                  <l>His ſucceſſor was happier, whoſe diſeaſe</l>
                  <l>And ſin, were both remov'd which did appeaſe</l>
                  <l>His piercing pains, at the <hi>Phiſicians</hi> talk,</l>
                  <l>Which ſaid ariſe take up thy bed and walk.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How many are there like the <hi>Leaper</hi> foul,</l>
                  <l>Look no higher than their bodies do controul!</l>
                  <l>All other conſiderations, but to cover</l>
                  <l>Their fowler parts, and willingly do ſmother</l>
                  <l>And ſlight their nobler parts, which ſhould adorn,</l>
                  <l>It lies infected, and expoſed to ſcorn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We are ſo eager to procure Chimeſtry,</l>
                  <l>And all that art can make to prompt Luxury;</l>
                  <l>To make our natures feed upon its flame,</l>
                  <l>While our better parts lie naked to the ſhame</l>
                  <l>Of mankind, that ſhould with right zeal deſire</l>
                  <l>To feed, not quench the true Celeſtial fire,</l>
                  <l>By which our ſouls ſhall ever truly be</l>
                  <l>Enlivened, and preſerved, O Lord for thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How do the Torments of a limb an hour</l>
                  <l>Move us to feel, and want thy healing power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVe practice more devotion in that fit,</l>
                  <l>Than many a moneth before we did feel it.</l>
                  <l>The loath'd deformities of our worſer parts</l>
                  <l>Gives us more grief, and more aflicts our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Than thoſe pale and infernal ſhapes, that thus</l>
                  <l>Diſſigureth Heaven's Character in us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come ſhew that beauty is without a blot,</l>
                  <l>That hath no bluſh of guilt, no <hi>Leprous</hi> ſpot,</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62740:42"/>
                  <l>That ſaintlike infant Man, that knows no guile,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſit, and here admire him for a while.</l>
                  <l>VVe're all conceiv'd in ſin, and cannot be</l>
                  <l>VVithout our ſpots, until we're waſht by thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVere our vains purer than the violets ſmell,</l>
                  <l>And could perfume the air yond paralel.</l>
                  <l>VVere <hi>Adams</hi> ſin a ſtranger to our blood.</l>
                  <l>And could our innocency have withſtood</l>
                  <l>Thy juſtice, our rebellious going aſtray</l>
                  <l>VVould Check our Luſts, and prompt us thus to pray.</l>
                  <l>The blackneſs of our thoughts would proclaim</l>
                  <l>(Though ſilently) ſin is our chiefeſt aim.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, was there not a generation</l>
                  <l>That thought themſelves clean without contagion,</l>
                  <l>VVere right in their own Eyes, and did deride</l>
                  <l>The world as <hi>Leapers</hi> in their ſcorning pride.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Phariſee</hi> was the more polluted Man</l>
                  <l>Than the ſoft hearted humble Publican,</l>
                  <l>VVhich did ſo proudly his beſt plums diſplay,</l>
                  <l>VVhich carried more contagion in that ſway</l>
                  <l>Of pride and oſtentation, but he's the winner,</l>
                  <l>Oh God be merciful to me a ſinner.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But he that truſts to merit and its paint,</l>
                  <l>And thinks himſelf a convert and a Saint</l>
                  <l>May looſe theſe Joyes, if that he doth deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>The mercy ſeat, where the true comfort lies,</l>
                  <l>And rely on his ſo great ſtock of parts,</l>
                  <l>His humane Learning, and his skill in arts;</l>
                  <l>VVithout thy poliſhing they cannot be</l>
                  <l>Made uſeful in our returns, O Lord, to thee,</l>
                  <l>No ſaint, nor Angel can procure us bliſs,</l>
                  <l>But the only begotten ſon whoſe merit it is,</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62740:42"/>
                  <l>The leaper is a beauty far beyond</l>
                  <l>My ſoul's more foul, and my vile courſes tend.</l>
                  <l>Yea <hi>Lazarus</hi> which had ſo many ſoars,</l>
                  <l>Are leſs in number far, than my vile ſcores,</l>
                  <l>Which I have run in ſin, and am as lame,</l>
                  <l>As the poor criple cur'd of ſin and ſhame.</l>
                  <l>Oh waſh me, Lord, in thy <hi>Betheſda</hi> pure,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be cleanſed, and be ever ſure,</l>
                  <l>Of thy healing mercies, let me not be</l>
                  <l>One of the nine ungrateful, Lord, to thee.</l>
                  <l>It will make my ſoares loathſome in thy ſight</l>
                  <l>And me eject unto eternal might,</l>
                  <l>But I do know thy goodneſs, and thy power</l>
                  <l>Doth ſtill preſerve us mortals every hour;</l>
                  <l>That ever can keep us in a holy mean,</l>
                  <l>Lord, if thou wilt thou canſt make me clean</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Kings 19.9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And he came unto a Cave and Lodged there.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId the good prophets zeal ſo far provoke</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Jezabel</hi> to threat the heavy ſtroak</l>
                  <l>Of death? did he then fle th'threatned rage</l>
                  <l>Of a furious woman to be more at large?</l>
                  <l>He came to <hi>Beerſhaba</hi> in ſo great fear,</l>
                  <l>And in much haſt he left his ſervant there,</l>
                  <l>While he journied on, in his ſo great diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>Until he came unto the wilderneſs.</l>
                  <l>Where under a <hi>Juniper</hi> tree he humbly ſate</l>
                  <l>With heavy ſobs, ſadly bewail'd his fate.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62740:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come Lord, it is enough, do not delay</l>
                  <l>Thy ſevere Juſtice, take my life away,</l>
                  <l>But a good Angel he doth interpoſe,</l>
                  <l>And wakes the ſleeping prophet from's repoſe,</l>
                  <l>And bids him eat, and ceaſe, this moan to make.</l>
                  <l>Behold, a cruze of water, and a cake</l>
                  <l>By divine providence prepar'd to be,</l>
                  <l>A ſupport to natures neceſſity.</l>
                  <l>He eat, he ſlept, and willingly obeys,</l>
                  <l>And in that ſtrength he travel'd forty days</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Horcb,</hi> the Mount of God, though ſtill in fear</l>
                  <l>He came into a cave, and lodged there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold, enraged Malice it doth force</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eliah</hi> to a Cave, there's no remorſe</l>
                  <l>In a Womans fury, there is no ſuſpence,</l>
                  <l>No liberty for life, or conſcience;</l>
                  <l>He muſt fly to a narrow compaſs to ſave both,</l>
                  <l>They are in danger if he admit of ſloth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold him now a <hi>Hermit</hi> to his pain,</l>
                  <l>For propheſying againſt wicked <hi>Ahabs</hi> reign</l>
                  <l>'Twas but a kind of tipe, that did foretel</l>
                  <l>To after ages ſuch a paralel.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe votaries of the Church the which did turn</l>
                  <l>Caves into cloiſters, and therein did mourn,</l>
                  <l>And fill theſe ſilent grots with divine love,</l>
                  <l>And chant forth ecchoes with the ſaints above,</l>
                  <l>And make them Chappels there to laud and praiſe,</l>
                  <l>In ſacred <hi>Halelujahs</hi> all their days.</l>
                  <l>The purity of their zeal I much admire,</l>
                  <l>Make ſolitude it's mirth in ſuch retire,</l>
                  <l>Can make Melancholly devotion fit</l>
                  <l>Object of glory, and the Joyes of it,</l>
                  <l>And ſequeſter themſelves from vain delight,</l>
                  <l>To contemplate with Angels day and night,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62740:43"/>
                  <l>So thoſe divine retirers have done well,</l>
                  <l>If they ring not too loud their merit bell.</l>
                  <l>If in imitation of the King of glory,</l>
                  <l>They faſt and pray, I ſuch a votary</l>
                  <l>Do highly prize, but if his vain tradition</l>
                  <l>Take place, he muſt be brought unto contrition.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that thoſe pious exiles in devotion</l>
                  <l>Not ſtudying humane praiſe, but virtues motion</l>
                  <l>Do contemplate with Heaven, and of its glory,</l>
                  <l>Abandoning the world thats tranſitory.</l>
                  <l>Such ſelf denial no Man ought to blame,</l>
                  <l>But worldlings court it, to their greater ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Not caring what vile courſes they purſue</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie their luſts, it is too true;</l>
                  <l>All rapine, and diſorder they commit,</l>
                  <l>And fondly brag, and boaſt, and glory in it.</l>
                  <l>But theſe our pious exiles, they do give</l>
                  <l>Up both their names, and lives that they may live</l>
                  <l>Religiouſly devout, 'tis ſtrange to have</l>
                  <l>A Prophet now retir'd unto a Cave.</l>
                  <l>No, no, they've higher thoughts, and their devotion</l>
                  <l>Tends much the way to get the beſt promotion.</l>
                  <l>But he's the Man that humbly can deny</l>
                  <l>His tempting luſts, when fortune caſt him high,</l>
                  <l>And can out face the world, and conquer it,</l>
                  <l>And with our Prophet in a Cave down ſit,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſweet contentment lodge in it all night,</l>
                  <l>VVhen high revenging rage ſets him to flight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Priſons and Caves are ſolitary places,</l>
                  <l>VVhere friends think it much if that they ſhew their faces</l>
                  <l>And give a word of comfort in that condition,</l>
                  <l>But leave poor priſoners to their ſaid contrition.</l>
                  <l>They'l ſay 'tis out of the way, they cannot ſtay,</l>
                  <l>They have no buſineſs that doth tend that way.</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62740:44"/>
                  <l>Such cunning ſlights they often do relate,</l>
                  <l>Let them have care they meet not with ſuch fate,</l>
                  <l>And then their cruelty may be required,</l>
                  <l>And their harſh dealings, in which they delighted.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He's the divine <hi>Hermit,</hi> that can gainſay</l>
                  <l>His carnal motions, and nobly obey</l>
                  <l>His virtue, which will quickly mount him high,</l>
                  <l>If he purſue the arts of Charity,</l>
                  <l>And not ſo ſlight the poor ſuffering Man,</l>
                  <l>But add unto his comfort all he can,</l>
                  <l>And make him muſick with his Chriſtian love,</l>
                  <l>Which will intitle him to the joyes above.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are ſuch graces in which God delight;</l>
                  <l>It Will have good acceptance in his ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If I am in a Cave, Lord, let me be</l>
                  <l>Refreſhed, and comforted alone in thee</l>
                  <l>Thy mercies doth refreſh me every morn,</l>
                  <l>Though by my friends I have been held in ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt given ſupport to me from hands unknown,</l>
                  <l>And many mercies unto me have ſhown.</l>
                  <l>Give me a thankful heart in my diſtreſs,</l>
                  <l>That I may follow thee, in the wilderneſs.</l>
                  <l>Oh let me worſhip with a reverence due</l>
                  <l>To thy great love, whoſe voice did thrice ſubdue</l>
                  <l>Thy murtherers, oh teach me to ſubmit</l>
                  <l>My ſelf to what thy wiſedom ſhall think fit.</l>
                  <l>Teach me all humility to make</l>
                  <l>A priſon comfortable, and therein take</l>
                  <l>My whole delight in thee and of thy ways,</l>
                  <l>And ſing forth <hi>Halelujahs</hi> to thy praiſe</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Siloas,</hi> let me ſweetly ſing</l>
                  <l>The praiſe and glory of my God and King.</l>
                  <l>O let not griefs confound me in this loſs,</l>
                  <l>But bear with patience this ſo heavy Croſs,</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62740:44"/>
                  <l>Which would ſink frail fleſh and blood, did not thy hand</l>
                  <l>Support my weak, and feeble ſoul to ſtand</l>
                  <l>Firſt to my confidence alone in thee,</l>
                  <l>Which hath appeared a Loving God to me,</l>
                  <l>Which truly is my hope, and help to ſave,</l>
                  <l>Which did relieve the Prophet in a cave</l>
                  <l>Wherein he lodged, and did take quiet reſt,</l>
                  <l>And was in thy preſerving power bleſt.</l>
                  <l>That I may do ſo, Lord, grant me thy ſpirit</l>
                  <l>To give due praiſes, then I ſhall inherit</l>
                  <l>Eternal manſions, thou my ſoul wilt ſave,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe me from a Priſon, or a Cave</l>
                  <l>Into eternal bliſs, the higheſt ſphear,</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt Saints and Angels to be lodged there.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Geneſis 28.12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And he dreamed a Dream and behold a Ladder ſet upon the Earth, and the top of it reached unto Heaven, and behold the Angels deſcending and aſcending on it.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId Iſaac call? ſurely he did no leſs,</l>
                  <l>And with a holy zeal his Son to bleſs,</l>
                  <l>And give him charge how to demean his life,</l>
                  <l>Forbidding <hi>Canan's</hi> Daughters for a Wife.</l>
                  <l>He bids him riſe and go unto none other</l>
                  <l>But unto <hi>Laban</hi> his own Mothers Brother,</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Padan-aram</hi> withour any ſtay,</l>
                  <l>And God Almighty bleſs thee in the way,</l>
                  <l>And multiply thy ſeed, that thou mayſt be</l>
                  <l>A mighty Nation; next poſterity.</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:62740:45"/>
                  <l>May inherit the bleſſed promiſe in good deed,</l>
                  <l>Which was made unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> obeys and travels all the day</l>
                  <l>Until the Sun declin'd, he made no ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Then laid he down his weary bones to reſt,</l>
                  <l>Stones were his pillow, where his ſleep was bleſt.</l>
                  <l>He dreamt, and behold a ladder there was ſet,</l>
                  <l>Where Angels did deſcend, aſcend on it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner had good <hi>Jacob's</hi> ſoul tak'n reſt,</l>
                  <l>His contented humility was bleſt</l>
                  <l>With an heavenly viſion, which ſalutes his ſence,</l>
                  <l>That bleſt obedience that brought him thence</l>
                  <l>Was raviſht with an object, that did prove</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed guide unto the Heavens above;</l>
                  <l>Where theſe bleſt ſpirits ſo enricht his ſence,</l>
                  <l>With a ſweet and harmonious influence,</l>
                  <l>Theſe divine Travellers not contending</l>
                  <l>But orderly aſcending, and deſcending.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh happy ſolitude, that thus doth meet</l>
                  <l>A heavenly company ſo rich and ſweet,</l>
                  <l>A bleſſed interview, that did requite</l>
                  <l>The hardneſs of his lodging with delight,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch an object did his ſoul take reſt,</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch dreams, was his ſtir'd fancy bleſt.</l>
                  <l>That the Lord of all the Earth ſhould not diſpence,</l>
                  <l>To make good his fore promis'd providence,</l>
                  <l>By Angels which did gradually aſcend</l>
                  <l>Up to that Heaven, which never ſhall have end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When I behold the poſture of this ſleeper,</l>
                  <l>Whom Angels had the charge of, as his keeper,</l>
                  <l>And his hard lodging, which gave him delight,</l>
                  <l>He had eternal glory, in his ſight.</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62740:45"/>
                  <l>I cannot chooſe but wonder, (in deriſion)</l>
                  <l>At them that laſily expect a viſion</l>
                  <l>Upon their beds of down, when moſt at leiſure,</l>
                  <l>Expecting apparitions in their pleaſure.</l>
                  <l>Their ſpirits would grow ſick of ſome diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>If viſions ſhould diſturb, or move their eaſe,</l>
                  <l>They quickly would catch cold, and loath to ſay,</l>
                  <l>At midnight I'le ariſe my vows to pay.</l>
                  <l>'Twas holy <hi>Davids</hi> zeal, he did not ſlumber</l>
                  <l>(Being fully awak'd,) his ſins did cumber</l>
                  <l>His new refined ſoul, Took much delight</l>
                  <l>In humility to proſtitute, in the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of his offended God, did oft confeſs,</l>
                  <l>How much he ſinned 'gainſt his holineſs,</l>
                  <l>With many a ſorrowful plaint, and piercing fears</l>
                  <l>He often waſht his couch in penitent Tears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God drops not miraclesin the wantons lap,</l>
                  <l>Nor communicate grace, by chance, or hap;</l>
                  <l>But confers his rich glories, chiefly to thoſe,</l>
                  <l>That ſtudy virtue, and are vices foes,</l>
                  <l>And are caſt down in trembling ſorrows deep,</l>
                  <l>Are comforted with viſions in their ſleep.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>John</hi> muſt be an exile, and brought low to pine</l>
                  <l>Before he be enabled a divine,</l>
                  <l>And confer with Angels in a holy trance,</l>
                  <l>Before his humane learning can advance,</l>
                  <l>And make him a fit Harbinger for Heaven;</l>
                  <l>Such gifts are not attain'd, but divinely given</l>
                  <l>By the wiſe diſpoſer of all events,</l>
                  <l>Which turneth ſufferings to their hearts contents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Holy Mans obedience made him leave</l>
                  <l>All carnal thoughtsbehind him, leaſt it bewreave</l>
                  <l>Him of the bleſt fruition of that bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Prepared for him in true happineſs.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:62740:46"/>
                  <l>His prayers and meditations only keep</l>
                  <l>Him company, it cauſed an happy ſleep,</l>
                  <l>So pleaſant, that he for ever diſclaim'd</l>
                  <l>All converſe with the world, and it diſdain'd</l>
                  <l>All ſecular intereſts, he did entertain</l>
                  <l>More noble thoughts, which prov'd his richer gain,</l>
                  <l>And made him an happy inſtrument of glory,</l>
                  <l>As 'tis recorded in the ſacred ſtory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacob</hi> had only a rich Canopie,</l>
                  <l>The azure ſpangled Curtains of the skie;</l>
                  <l>His lights the lamps of Heaven, O ſafe and bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Where Angels did protect, and guard his reſt,</l>
                  <l>Ever in motion with their care defending,</l>
                  <l>In a holy zeal aſcending, and deſcending!</l>
                  <l>Oh how ſecurely doth he ever reſt,</l>
                  <l>That leans on providence, and is not preſt</l>
                  <l>With worldly cares, but joyfully doth make</l>
                  <l>Providence his guard, and therein chiefly take</l>
                  <l>His ſole felicity; he cannot miſcarry,</l>
                  <l>If divine thoughts become his ſanctuary;</l>
                  <l>Nor need he fear diſturbance in his ſleep,</l>
                  <l>Where God and Angels do him ſafely keep.</l>
                  <l>Yea his very dreams will chear his ſoul with joy,</l>
                  <l>No dangers, nor aſſaults can him annoy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good <hi>Jacob</hi> having no ſooner clos'd his eyes,</l>
                  <l>But by an inſpir'd fancy he eſpies</l>
                  <l>Theſe holy Porters with endeared love,</l>
                  <l>Inviting him unto the Heavens above;</l>
                  <l>Preſenting him a ladder, whereby he ſees</l>
                  <l>There is no leaping there, but by degrees,</l>
                  <l>VVe muſt carefully climb Heaven, that Throne is high</l>
                  <l>By gradual ſteps of faith, and charity.</l>
                  <l>Every virtue is a ſtep, if by it we climb,</l>
                  <l>That ladder will advance us to ſee him.</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62740:46"/>
                  <l>If we tread our vices under, and by it ſhow</l>
                  <l>They'r fixt unto the Earth, that is below</l>
                  <l>Where the foot doth reſt, but we muſt leave behind</l>
                  <l>Our vain delights, the frailties of Mankind,</l>
                  <l>And ſtudiouſly be induſtrious for ſuch gain,</l>
                  <l>As will requite the trouble and the pain</l>
                  <l>Our progreſs muſt be conſtant, and not ſlack</l>
                  <l>A holy pace, if that we once look back</l>
                  <l>Into the plain, the world will ſteal our ſence</l>
                  <l>From climbing with a religious reverence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Lord! how doth this ſubject meet my caſe,</l>
                  <l>That am caſt down into a ſtony place.</l>
                  <l>I mean a place unpleaſant, 'cauſe not free,</l>
                  <l>But it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h mounted me, to come to thee.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſhew'd to me a ladder, thy bleſt ways</l>
                  <l>Enliven me, O Lord, to give thee praiſe.</l>
                  <l>Had I bin rich, and had of plenty ſtore,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould have ſcorn'd this ladder as heretofore;</l>
                  <l>I thought on pleaſures, and the worlds vain guiſe,</l>
                  <l>Did too too much affect and bleere theſe eyes</l>
                  <l>That now look up to thee, O let my ſight</l>
                  <l>Be clear to ſee the bleſt eternal light,</l>
                  <l>Thy abundant graces! oh thou which truly art</l>
                  <l>The great Phyſitian, which can cure my heart;</l>
                  <l>Give me a holy longing, and inflame</l>
                  <l>In me a ſervent zeal to praiſe thy name.</l>
                  <l>If bitter potions be for my ſouls health,</l>
                  <l>Apply them, Lord, although it purge my wealth.</l>
                  <l>There is more true riches in thy love in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Than ever I could loſe all times before.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt given, thou haſt taken, thy bleſſed will be done,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy mercies in thy only Son,</l>
                  <l>To be my ranſom, I ſhall be richer then,</l>
                  <l>Then e're I was amongſt the ſons of Men.</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62740:47"/>
                  <l>This caſting down will raiſe me to that Throne</l>
                  <l>Of mercy in whom is my faith alone,</l>
                  <l>And I therein rejoyce, though thus caſt down,</l>
                  <l>That thou look'ſt not on me with angry frown,</l>
                  <l>But haſt often ſent thine Angels to ſupport</l>
                  <l>My feeble ſtate, when they to me reſort,</l>
                  <l>And cheriſh this frail body, 'Tis from thee</l>
                  <l>That ſo much love and bounty comforts me,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy grace ſo far to uſe thy love</l>
                  <l>With temperate meekneſs, and from me remove</l>
                  <l>All carnal confidence and humbly bend</l>
                  <l>My ſtudies to pleaſe him, that me defend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy promiſes, O Lord, do never fail,</l>
                  <l>And yet how careleſs are we, that are frail;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſheweſt us the living way unto thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Yet we are blinded with the love of pelf</l>
                  <l>Of this deluding world, we're loth to walk</l>
                  <l>Thy pathes, yet proudly do we brag and talk</l>
                  <l>Of coming to thee, but we are loth to climb</l>
                  <l>That ladder, that will mount us to ſee him</l>
                  <l>That ſits upon the Throne, O how weak and lame</l>
                  <l>Are our devotions, 'tis our greater ſhame</l>
                  <l>To ſee how nimbly, we do thus purſue</l>
                  <l>The periſhing delights within our view,</l>
                  <l>But make ſo little progreſs in that race,</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt ſet all ways before our face.</l>
                  <l>Oh quicken, and make us earneſt with holy love</l>
                  <l>To invocate our Chriſt, that ſits above</l>
                  <l>To give us of thy ſpirit, that we may move</l>
                  <l>With holy zeal to the Altar of thy love,</l>
                  <l>Where the bleſt Angels do ever attend,</l>
                  <l>As miniſtring ſpirits that aſcend and deſcend.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:62740:47"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Proverbs 18.14.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But a wounded ſpirit who can bear!</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEark O my ſoul, conſider this wiſe prince,</l>
                  <l>Mark well his Councel, and not ſtir from thence.</l>
                  <l>Incline thine ear to wiſedom, don't delay</l>
                  <l>To mind his pious precepts, let it ſway</l>
                  <l>VVithin thy heart, O let inſtruction learn</l>
                  <l>Thee to delight, and ſtudy to diſcern</l>
                  <l>Theſe many moral virtues, which are taught,</l>
                  <l>And may by grace be obtain'd, if they be ſought</l>
                  <l>VVith a holy zeal, O let true virtue be</l>
                  <l>Thy chief deſire, then oyntment it will be</l>
                  <l>Unto thy neck, as Bracelets to thine arm,</l>
                  <l>If thou theſe precepts keep, 'twill keep from harm.</l>
                  <l>Therefore ſo value them as a rich price,</l>
                  <l>And obſerve how fully it correcteth vice,</l>
                  <l>And helpeth much mans ſpirits to chear,</l>
                  <l>But alas, a wounded ſpirit who can bear!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhere ſhall I find a temper can endure</l>
                  <l>Such ſtings of conſcience, of the ſad preſſure</l>
                  <l>Beyond belief, which rageth and is mad,</l>
                  <l>At every gripe and pain the ſoul is ſad.</l>
                  <l>The very Earth trembles, and can't ſuſtain</l>
                  <l>It ſelf, it groans and travels with its pain</l>
                  <l>To be delivered, the Ambitious Angels fell</l>
                  <l>And through their foul deſpair, do roar in hell.</l>
                  <l>How dolorous is deſpair? that wound is deep,</l>
                  <l>VVhere mercy is ſhut out, and Devils do keep</l>
                  <l>The feſterd wound a bleeding, without ſence</l>
                  <l>Oh the Horror of a wounded conſcience!</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62740:48"/>
                  <l>It ſo afflicts, and ſtartles all the parts</l>
                  <l>VVith the terrors of the pains rais'd by ſuch arts,</l>
                  <l>Yea all the tortures which the Martyrs felt,</l>
                  <l>VVere flea-bites to thoſe pains raiſed by this guilt;</l>
                  <l>Tortures of cruelſt ſhape, would well become</l>
                  <l>Be eaſy ſufferings, a pleaſing Martyrdom</l>
                  <l>Compared unto thoſe never dying pains,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe living deaths, thoſe tortures and thoſe Chains,</l>
                  <l>That ſo ſtrongly hold the ſences Captive in,</l>
                  <l>Satans foul bands, the reward of their ſin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVhat can there be compar'd! not all our ſence</l>
                  <l>Can paralel a wounded conſcience.</l>
                  <l>The ſhreiks of oyls, which add blackneſs to the night</l>
                  <l>Offends the ears, yea dying groans that fright</l>
                  <l>And fill our ſouls with ſadneſs, at ſuch cries</l>
                  <l>As conſcience makes, it even rends the skies</l>
                  <l>With the ſcreetches of thoſe pains their conſcience utter,</l>
                  <l>It beats within and horrid pains they ſuffer.</l>
                  <l>Deſpair ſo rageth with a furious voice,</l>
                  <l>That it diſtempers all with its hideous noiſe:</l>
                  <l>It deſcants, it writes Satyrs againſt it ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Sad dying elogies, alas poor! Elfe;</l>
                  <l>VVhat fatal Ideas doſt thou thus ſhape</l>
                  <l>VVithin thy fancy? what a tone doſt make</l>
                  <l>Surrounded with all the tortures, black grief</l>
                  <l>Can add? oh! 'tis ſo far beyond belief</l>
                  <l>To expreſs that ſuffering in a perfect ſence;</l>
                  <l>Oh the terrors of a wounded conſcience!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did <hi>David</hi> walk on mourning all the day</l>
                  <l>And night, his prickt conſcience to allay?</l>
                  <l>Did not his eyes run over with his tears,</l>
                  <l>Theſe weeping ſprings raiſ'd by his many fears?</l>
                  <l>He breaths nought, but ſuch ſad trembling accents,</l>
                  <l>As ariſeth from his ſouls ſad diſcontents,</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62740:48"/>
                  <l>Deſpairing Ecchoes, thinking it too late</l>
                  <l>He ſighes, he moans, and thus he expoſtulates.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dear God is thy Mercy ſhut up for ever?</l>
                  <l>Shall my poor ſoul enjoy it never?</l>
                  <l>That attribute of thy Mercy and thy love,</l>
                  <l>VVhich thou haſt treaſur'd in the Heavens above.</l>
                  <l>Oh ſhut not up from me that humbly crave,</l>
                  <l>But grant thy pardoning mercy, Lord, to ſave</l>
                  <l>My afflicted ſoul, I hope thou wilt not be</l>
                  <l>A God of love to all, and none to me.</l>
                  <l>Let any other torment fright me hence,</l>
                  <l>Than the terrors of a guilty conſcience.</l>
                  <l>Let me for ever dwell in dungeons deep,</l>
                  <l>Or ſuch a cell as light durſt not to peep,</l>
                  <l>In ſome forſaken vault, or diſmal place,</l>
                  <l>So as I may enjoy thy glorious face.</l>
                  <l>Let all the poverty that can attend</l>
                  <l>A wretched man, yet if thy Love thou ſend</l>
                  <l>And cover my naked ſoul, that is thus ſtorm'd</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Leprous</hi> with ſin, and much deform'd</l>
                  <l>VVith the terrors of thy Judgments, which may take</l>
                  <l>Vengeance on me if thou doſt once forſake</l>
                  <l>My ſpotred ſoul, oh hide theſe ſpots of mine,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall I be a beauty that will ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And invite thine Eye again, for to look on</l>
                  <l>A wretch that was furlorn, loſt and gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conſider this ye Riotors in luſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich dally with damnation till ye burſt,</l>
                  <l>VVhat agonies they endure, whilſt void of ſence</l>
                  <l>By the griping of a wounded conſcience,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſo doth rack them into many a fear</l>
                  <l>Of grief, but a wounded ſpirit who can bear!</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62740:49"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh who can mind his Murthering ſins with pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>And recount his bitter ſweets at his ſad leiſure,</l>
                  <l>He'l meet an ill account, ſin leaves behind</l>
                  <l>Having miſpent his nobler parts, his mind.</l>
                  <l>VVer't thou to die, would not thy parting groan</l>
                  <l>Mind thee of thy ſad life, ſo paſt and gone.</l>
                  <l>Flattery will prove ſmall comfort in that hour,</l>
                  <l>VVhen vain excuſes will have little power</l>
                  <l>To ſtill the conſcience, or thy thoughts to chear</l>
                  <l>VVith joy, a wounded ſpirit who can bear!</l>
                  <l>Shew me that <hi>Sampſon</hi> conſcience with his ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>But that this ugly vulture will at length</l>
                  <l>Both maſter, and ſubdue, what frozen ſoul</l>
                  <l>Thoſe aſhes would not melt, and ſo controul</l>
                  <l>The ſturdy ſinner, laden with loads of guilt,</l>
                  <l>VVhich hangs ſo heavy, that his conſcience felt</l>
                  <l>That naſty load of crimes, that down hath hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>His active parts into the lower world?</l>
                  <l>Not all his art, or courtſhip, cannot ſave</l>
                  <l>His Treacherous ſoul from the terrors of the grave;</l>
                  <l>They are but trifles to it, could it but ſhroud</l>
                  <l>The guilty ſoul from darkneſs, oh how proud</l>
                  <l>VVould the ſoul be, if that he might be free,</l>
                  <l>From the terrors of a future miſery!</l>
                  <l>But theſe are empty ſhadows, cannot keep</l>
                  <l>The tortur'd ſoul, it cannot ſweetly ſleep.</l>
                  <l>Sum all the croſſes that the ſoul ſurrounded</l>
                  <l>The Catalogue of afflictions, thus confounded</l>
                  <l>There's none like this, which his vices thus inherit</l>
                  <l>The grief, and anguiſh of a troubled ſpirit.</l>
                  <l>That intolerable grief, which admits no chear</l>
                  <l>Or joy, but a wounded ſpirit who can bear!</l>
                  <l>VVhat burthen then doth a wounded ſpirit endure,</l>
                  <l>Unſupportable of his pains? griefs are ſure</l>
                  <l>Still charged with the frights, which ariſeth hence</l>
                  <l>By the terrors of a wounded conſcience.</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62740:49"/>
                  <l>Oh let nor the apprehenſions of thy wrath</l>
                  <l>So far afright us, thy ſweet mercy hath</l>
                  <l>Much balm in ſtore to cure a wounded ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>Which being applied by faith we may inherit</l>
                  <l>Eternal bliſs; in our boſom thou haſt ſet</l>
                  <l>A perfect Regiſter, let us not forget</l>
                  <l>To ſumm them up in tears without delay,</l>
                  <l>Recounting all the ills, that did bear ſway</l>
                  <l>In our moſt raging luſts, then ſhall we be</l>
                  <l>Cur'd of our feſtred wounds, O Lord, by thee,</l>
                  <l>Which art the great Phyſitian, which can heal</l>
                  <l>All wounded ſpirits, when they with faith appeal.</l>
                  <l>Lord, ope our eyes, then ſhall we clearly ſee</l>
                  <l>Our many fold tranſgreſſions againſt thee,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall we by thy mercy ſure inherit</l>
                  <l>That bleſſed balm will cure a wounded ſpirit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 24.38.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And knew not untill the flood came and took them all away.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw great's the love of Chriſt, that did condeſcend</l>
                  <l>To acquaint his belov'd diſciples with the end</l>
                  <l>Of the old world, as the days of <hi>Noah</hi> were</l>
                  <l>Before the flood, whoſe lofty waves did bear</l>
                  <l>The preſerving Ark, he ſaith they all ſhall ſee,</l>
                  <l>That ſo the coming of the Son of Man ſhall be.</l>
                  <l>For in thoſe days, before the raging flood,</l>
                  <l>They eat, they drank, did little that was good,</l>
                  <l>Marry, and give in marriage, till that day</l>
                  <l>The flood came on, and took them all away.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:62740:50"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>How fondly, and ſecurely did they feaſt</l>
                  <l>Themſelves for ruin! they did make a jeſt</l>
                  <l>Of ſin, they only ſtriv'd to feed their luſts</l>
                  <l>And cram'd themſelves in riot till they burſt.</l>
                  <l>For luſt, and luxury took up their heart,</l>
                  <l>And ſo poſſeſt it, that they could not part,</l>
                  <l>Till deaths divorce, they were ſo firmly married</l>
                  <l>Unto their luſts, until the Ocean carried</l>
                  <l>Them all away, oh how ſad's that feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Where overflowing Judgment takes the gueſts!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Juſt <hi>Noah's</hi> preaching could not yet perſwade</l>
                  <l>This drunken Crew, that ſtill did ſwine-like wade</l>
                  <l>Into all filth, his fluent admonition</l>
                  <l>Could not prevail to bring them to contrition.</l>
                  <l>But the rougher waves made a language to detect</l>
                  <l>Their ranting noiſe, in their own dialect.</l>
                  <l>The prodigious raging of the angry deep</l>
                  <l>Silenc't their prophane noiſe, in deaths laſt ſleep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had not God bound himſelf by promiſe ſure,</l>
                  <l>That the Earth no more a deluge ſhould endure,</l>
                  <l>And hath his party colored bow ſo fixt,</l>
                  <l>As that there is no doubting with it mixt.</l>
                  <l>But how often hath our debauch'd vain ways</l>
                  <l>Corrouz'd, and rioted, in thoſe our days,</l>
                  <l>That we can teach the <hi>Epicure</hi> to revel,</l>
                  <l>And ſo provoke incenſed wrath to level</l>
                  <l>Juſt judgments on our heads, if we aſpire</l>
                  <l>Our next refining will be all of fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The former vices of our predeceſſor,</l>
                  <l>Come very ſhort of the preſent tranſgreſſor</l>
                  <l>Of theſe our times, we're giants now in growth</l>
                  <l>In ſin, by our unwairy lazy ſloth,</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:62740:50"/>
                  <l>That doth beſet us, and ſubdue our ſence,</l>
                  <l>That we grow monſters without penitence.</l>
                  <l>We ſtudy vices dayly, as though the Earth</l>
                  <l>Like an infernal <hi>Affrick</hi> hatcht new birth</l>
                  <l>Of ugly monſters, ſuch huge prodigies</l>
                  <l>Of minted ſins, which dayly doth ariſe;</l>
                  <l>It ſtartles reaſon, and as though we were</l>
                  <l>Only to feaſt in ſin, and frolick here.</l>
                  <l>Was the world drown'd, did not the waters ſtay,</l>
                  <l>But carried theſe living dead Men away?</l>
                  <l>And were they taken in their great exceſs,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall we think to eſcape this wickedneſs?</l>
                  <l>And be careleſs, of our lives? ſhall we not cry,</l>
                  <l>That have lived ſo long in ſuch impenitency,</l>
                  <l>And here behold them drown'd, that thus did ſcatter,</l>
                  <l>And freely drank iniquity like water,</l>
                  <l>And were ſhipwrackt in their houſes thus ſurpriz'd</l>
                  <l>By death and Judgment, which they ſo diſpit'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So righteous art thou, Lord, in thy judgment</l>
                  <l>And pure in juſtice, if we not repent,</l>
                  <l>Thy hand of juſtice will us overtake,</l>
                  <l>For our impenitency, if we don't forſake</l>
                  <l>Our foul tranſgreſſions, it will ſo incenſe</l>
                  <l>Thy juſtice in thy wrath, to ſweep us hence.</l>
                  <l>And yet how good is thy tranſcending love,</l>
                  <l>That never ſendeſt puniſhments from above,</l>
                  <l>But when our faults encreaſe ſo boldly high,</l>
                  <l>As to provoke thy ſacred Majeſty:</l>
                  <l>By our impenitencies we do provoke</l>
                  <l>Thy divine juſtice to the heavy ſtroak</l>
                  <l>Of judgment, which doth thus highly incenſe</l>
                  <l>Thy wrath in juſtice for to ſweep us hence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, 'twas thy mercy, out of thy great love,</l>
                  <l>To aſſure us by thy promiſe from above,</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62740:51"/>
                  <l>To free us from ſo great a puniſhment,</l>
                  <l>Its memory ſhould make our hearts relent,</l>
                  <l>And to admire thy mercy, meekly turn</l>
                  <l>Our hearts to holy penitence, and mourn,</l>
                  <l>And meditate, how thy judgments did o'retake</l>
                  <l>Them, that all virtuous precepts did foreſake.</l>
                  <l>Let their example mind us to repent</l>
                  <l>Leaſt we fall under ſuch juſt puniſhment.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke 7.5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For he loved our Nation and hath built us a Synagogue.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>WAs the ſervant ſick, and did his Maſters love</l>
                  <l>So far exceed, his charity to move,</l>
                  <l>As to ſend for help to him, that was able</l>
                  <l>To cure his ſoul, (though born in a ſtable?)</l>
                  <l>He knew it was his Jeſus which had power</l>
                  <l>To heal, he was his only Saviour,</l>
                  <l>To him he ſent, and did paſſionately ſay,</l>
                  <l>I am not worthy, Lord, that thou ſhouldſt ſtay</l>
                  <l>Under my roof, but ſpeak and he ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Healed, and give his praiſes unto thee.</l>
                  <l>To which the great Phyſitian freely ſaith,</l>
                  <l>I have not found in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo much ſaith.</l>
                  <l>The elders importunity exceeds</l>
                  <l>Moſt gratefully magnifying his deeds,</l>
                  <l>And his love unto his nation did expreſs</l>
                  <l>He built a Temple unto holineſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Behold the character of a pious Man,</l>
                  <l>Which by virtue doth oblige all that he can,</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62740:51"/>
                  <l>And lay out his outmoſt intereſt to encreaſe</l>
                  <l>His countries good, proſperity and peace!</l>
                  <l>And as a father he doth ſtill endeavor,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve his comon wealth in all what ever</l>
                  <l>Lies in his power, that he is juſtly ſtil'd</l>
                  <l>A vertuous patriot, ever meek and mild.</l>
                  <l>This good <hi>Centurion</hi> was not only high</l>
                  <l>In place alone, but lov'd true piety,</l>
                  <l>Where he was chief, and all Judea over</l>
                  <l>Could not paralel his worth, it did diſcover</l>
                  <l>A mine of treaſure, in his ſoul lay hid</l>
                  <l>Of precious faith moſt richly valued.</l>
                  <l>Did they not hate Idolatry to prize,</l>
                  <l>They would his perſon too much Idolize,</l>
                  <l>And pay reſpect unto with adoration,</l>
                  <l>Who was ſo great a lover of their nation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herod</hi> indeed their Temple did repair,</l>
                  <l>But it was not for love, but panick fear;</l>
                  <l>'Twas but in policy for him to get</l>
                  <l>The Crown, that ambitiouſly aſpir'd to it.</l>
                  <l>Devotion had in him the ſmalleſt aim,</l>
                  <l>Not a religious zeal for to maintain;</l>
                  <l>'Twas not his aim, he did not mind the thing,</l>
                  <l>His whole religion was to become King,</l>
                  <l>And as a Tyrant live, for to ſuppreſs</l>
                  <l>Chriſt's purer ways, which tend to holineſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such is the ſanctity that worldlings ſhew</l>
                  <l>By pretence to virtue, whilſt they beſtow</l>
                  <l>All their endeavor to guild o're their crimes,</l>
                  <l>Make ſeeming virtue footſtools to their aims.</l>
                  <l>Pretence of zeal, a paſſage to ambition,</l>
                  <l>Thinking they creep along without ſuſpicion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But the <hi>Centurion's</hi> zeal was nobly bent</l>
                  <l>To honor his nation, with a full intent</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:62740:52"/>
                  <l>To befriend religion with his countenance,</l>
                  <l>And pious acts of virtue to advance</l>
                  <l>With ſincere intention, not pretending,</l>
                  <l>But faithfully their ſouls, and church defending.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unlike thoſe rulers, which do ſet aſide</l>
                  <l>Religion, to ſet up their haughty pride,</l>
                  <l>And think themſelves the wiſeſt of the crew,</l>
                  <l>If they have no religion in their view:</l>
                  <l>And as our new <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> do delight</l>
                  <l>To pull down holy Temples in deſpight</l>
                  <l>To holy things, and raiſe even to the ground</l>
                  <l>The carved works of ſtructures, and abound</l>
                  <l>In novelties, and think it good to fight</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Kings, entruſted with protecting right,</l>
                  <l>Which ſparkles like to Diamonds in their Crown,</l>
                  <l>And fills them full of ſplendor and renown;</l>
                  <l>They are the Churches patriots to preſerve</l>
                  <l>All divine right, and faithfully to ſerve,</l>
                  <l>As conſervators of that dignity,</l>
                  <l>Which they do hold from God in humility.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No, theſe material Temples cannot be</l>
                  <l>Sure monuments to all poſterity;</l>
                  <l>Could we build Pyramids to reach the sky,</l>
                  <l>Or Alablaſter piles carv'd curiouſly,</l>
                  <l>Or plates of braſs, to eternize our name,</l>
                  <l>They were but empty ſhadows to the frame,</l>
                  <l>That building without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ands which none can ſever</l>
                  <l>From the immortal ſoul, which lives for ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Synagogue, which the <hi>Centurion</hi> raife</l>
                  <l>Became a greater monument to his praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And laſted longer, it engaged the Jews</l>
                  <l>To gratitude, and wonder, they did muſe</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:62740:52"/>
                  <l>At ſuch unwonted favor, they ſwift did run,</l>
                  <l>And became advocates to heal his ſon,</l>
                  <l>And preſt him with ſuch arguments to move</l>
                  <l>His pitty towards him, ſhew'd ſo much love</l>
                  <l>In ſuch abundant meaſure, he did raiſe</l>
                  <l>A ſynagogue to his immortal praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such honor is return'd to all that aim</l>
                  <l>To advance thy glory, and to praiſe thy name.</l>
                  <l>Such as have zeal for glory ſhall be bleſt</l>
                  <l>With ſpiritual joy, and ever be at reſt.</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt offering they do make to thee,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall not only here accepted be,</l>
                  <l>But ſo rewarded in eternal bliſs,</l>
                  <l>Where all true joy, and every comfort is,</l>
                  <l>And ſtir up emulation, who ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Moſt forward to expreſs true plety.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord, let not thoſe are ignorant of thy power</l>
                  <l>Outſtrip us in devotion, that each hour</l>
                  <l>Depend on thee, and ſeemingly profeſs</l>
                  <l>The true religion in truth and holineſs.</l>
                  <l>Oh! Let our holy carriage ſo adorn</l>
                  <l>Thy publick worſhip, and not be a ſcorn.</l>
                  <l>Let our bodies be Temples, not a cell,</l>
                  <l>That grace, and all the virtues there may dwell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So teach us, Lord, our living ſouls may be</l>
                  <l>Temples, where praiſes may be given to thee,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe our hearts ever to make addreſs</l>
                  <l>To thee alone, who art only goodneſs,</l>
                  <l>And let us not think building ſtructures will</l>
                  <l>Eternize names, unleſs we do fulfill</l>
                  <l>Thy holy precepts, and there fix our thought,</l>
                  <l>All other buildings are but vain and naught.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62740:53"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>John 20.11</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>But <hi>Mary</hi> ſtood without at the Sepulchre weeping, and as ſhe wept ſhe ſtooped down and looked into the Sepulchre.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId <hi>Mary</hi> weep? and can our Eyes be dry?</l>
                  <l>Will nought afflict our ſence? no miſery,</l>
                  <l>No loſs ſo great, make us ſhed tears? but ſtay!</l>
                  <l>Conſider it is the reſurrection day,</l>
                  <l>When her bleſt body bowed to look in there,</l>
                  <l>Where he was laid, the loathed Sepulchre,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhe beheld her Saviours tomb with grief,</l>
                  <l>Which was her ſweeteſt comfort, and relief,</l>
                  <l>See how religiouſly ſhe ſtoops to look</l>
                  <l>Into the grave, with care, leaſt ſhe miſtook!</l>
                  <l>When her younger ſiſters vainly did miſpend</l>
                  <l>Their precious time in dreſſing, which doth tend</l>
                  <l>To carnal pleaſures, ſome will ſcarce allow</l>
                  <l>A modeſt kneeling, or an humble bow</l>
                  <l>In their religious worſhip, they ſo ſlight</l>
                  <l>All reverence due to Majeſty and might.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See, ſee the power of love that is divine,</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Mary</hi> look into a loathed Shrine!</l>
                  <l>Which could ſtrike the world with paleneſs, and affright</l>
                  <l>The boldeſt Champion Saint, and put to flight</l>
                  <l>Our faith, had not the perfumes, which came thence,</l>
                  <l>Rarified the air with its ſweet influence,</l>
                  <l>And perfum'd thac naſty vault amongſt hardſtones</l>
                  <l>And crazy coffins, rotten dead mens bones,</l>
                  <l>Which were his pillow, till that joyful Morn,</l>
                  <l>When he aroſe in triumph to adorn</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:62740:53"/>
                  <l>The heavenly Throne, and there doth ever ſhine</l>
                  <l>In perfect glory, which is moſt divine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See, how the Martyrs Triumpht in their flame,</l>
                  <l>And gloried in their ſuffrings for his name,</l>
                  <l>And were carried in raptures through the fire</l>
                  <l>In holy love, and zeal! they did aſpire</l>
                  <l>Into true joy, that element did warm</l>
                  <l>Their earthy parts, and did their ſouls no harm;</l>
                  <l>They nobly met with death, their ſouls did ſing</l>
                  <l>Moſt divine Anthems unto Chriſt their King.</l>
                  <l>Their chains were Muſick, they did ſeem to be</l>
                  <l>Rather Prieſts than victims in that ſolemnity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How ſweetly did the bleſſed Martyr <hi>Stephen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expire, he having ſeen his Chriſt and Heaven!</l>
                  <l>That heap of Curſed ſtones, rais'd to torment</l>
                  <l>His earthy part, prov'd a bleſt monument,</l>
                  <l>Far richer than the chiefeſt Artiſts skill</l>
                  <l>In the proudeſt marble it could paralel.</l>
                  <l>He cimited it with his blood, and made it faſter,</l>
                  <l>By the undaunted ſpirit of the firſt Martyr.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus did the ſuffring ſaints their tortures turn</l>
                  <l>To pleaſures, and the terrors of the urn</l>
                  <l>To a ſtream of mirth, not all their rage</l>
                  <l>Of fierceſt Tyrants could once diſengage</l>
                  <l>Their ſouls from comfort, nay the neweſt pain</l>
                  <l>Of ſtudied torments could not hinder their gain,</l>
                  <l>Or force them from their pious Chriſtian love,</l>
                  <l>They ever bore to Chriſt who ſits above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that ſo loves his Saviour will ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoop with <hi>Mary</hi> to enrich his eyes</l>
                  <l>With the fruition of that deſired ſight,</l>
                  <l>That is ſo full of ſplendor, power, and might,</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:62740:54"/>
                  <l>And not only ſtoop, but ſtep into a tomb,</l>
                  <l>And embrace a coffin in that diſmal room,</l>
                  <l>And look on death, but as the door to bliſs,</l>
                  <l>The Meſſenger of glory, and happineſs.</l>
                  <l>And with St. <hi>Paul</hi> in raptures all in flame</l>
                  <l>Begging a diſſolution of this frame,</l>
                  <l>While his ſoul in extaſies tranſports its ſence</l>
                  <l>Into a holy zeal, to be mov'd hence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Lord, with what regret do we forſake</l>
                  <l>Earths vaniſhing pleaſures in which we do take</l>
                  <l>So great delight, the which ſhould make us ſorry,</l>
                  <l>That we do ſtrive ſo little for thy glory.</l>
                  <l>But are ever unwilling to let down</l>
                  <l>Our lives our pleaſures for an immortal Crown,</l>
                  <l>In obedience to the law of the bleſt Kingdom,</l>
                  <l>Which ſaith thy ſervice is a perfect freedom.</l>
                  <l>And yet we count the ſweeteſt ſanctuary</l>
                  <l>A Priſon, and trouble, if we find it vary</l>
                  <l>From our vile luſts, and think our ſelves to blame,</l>
                  <l>If that we pay due honor to thy name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pardon, O Lord, the corruptions of our frame,</l>
                  <l>And teach us how to love, and prize thy name;</l>
                  <l>But whether we live or die, we may delight,</l>
                  <l>In that which is moſt pleaſant in thy ſight.</l>
                  <l>That when this Tabernacle ſhall diſſolve,</l>
                  <l>Our earthy bodies may ſurely involve</l>
                  <l>Into everlaſting joyes, the ſeat of bliſs,</l>
                  <l>The only reſidence of happineſs,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoop withal due reference and fear,</l>
                  <l>And look into a loathed Sepulchre.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62740:54"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 12.1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Remember thy Creator in the days of thy youth.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw ſweet's the preachers voice that doth invite</l>
                  <l>Youth to a plous care, and doth excite</l>
                  <l>A holy life, it is the beſt expreſſion</l>
                  <l>In all his ſermon, checking youths tranſgreſſion.</l>
                  <l>Here younger Ones, are bid to have a care</l>
                  <l>Of ſpending time, leaſt that they do enſuare</l>
                  <l>Their ſouls in ſin, for none indeed can tell,</l>
                  <l>How ſoon young Men may hear their paſſing bell,</l>
                  <l>Toll the ſad ditty of their lateſt breath,</l>
                  <l>Surrendring up their ſences all to death.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The divine preachers chiefeſt aim is this,</l>
                  <l>To ſtir youth up to early holineſs.</l>
                  <l>And yet the worlds not pleaſed with the ſtrain,</l>
                  <l>It ſounds too harſh, though it deſign their gain.</l>
                  <l>Look on the creatures with a ſingle eye,</l>
                  <l>And you this doctrine quickly will eſpy;</l>
                  <l>They plainly preach it, yet we ſlug and ſlumber</l>
                  <l>With open eyes, our duller thoughts do cumber</l>
                  <l>Our purer meditations, which ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Of our backſlidings, and returns to thee.</l>
                  <l>Regardleſs youth delighteth not to hear,</l>
                  <l>This ſilver trumpet ſounding in his ear.</l>
                  <l>It ſpoils his mirth, and ſours his ſweeter Muſe,</l>
                  <l>Stirs thoughts of Heaven too ſoon, he'd rather chooſe</l>
                  <l>His Carnal ſports, than thus to dull his wit,</l>
                  <l>Make him look grave, before he attain to it.</l>
                  <l>His ſpritely blood thinks it too hard a task</l>
                  <l>To be religious, he prefers a mask</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:62740:55"/>
                  <l>And rather ravel out his time in pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vaineſt ſports, are held his chiefeſt treaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fond youth, call in theſe thoughts, lament thy way,</l>
                  <l>Remember the approaching judgment day,</l>
                  <l>When we to God, a ſure account muſt give</l>
                  <l>Of all our actions, whilſt we here do live.</l>
                  <l>Let not theſe fleſhly objects of thy pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Tranſport our ſences, beyond a due meaſure</l>
                  <l>From Heaven, and heavenly things, which ſhould rejoyce</l>
                  <l>Our very hearts to hear the Preachers voice.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſhall theſe luſts, which we purſue in pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Bewreave us of our joy, our only treaſure?</l>
                  <l>Shall we have greater zeal for to tranſgreſs,</l>
                  <l>Than for to magnifie thy holineſs?</l>
                  <l>And ſhall thoſe pleaſures that do quickly die,</l>
                  <l>Quite drown the thoughts of immortality?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My life, that's but a ſpan, let it decay,</l>
                  <l>And ſhorten rather, than miſpend my day.</l>
                  <l>Better this earthy tabernacle be</l>
                  <l>Diſſolved, than I by ſin ſhould fall from thee.</l>
                  <l>Much better 't is that I ſhould quickly pay</l>
                  <l>Nature her debt, and turn again to clay,</l>
                  <l>Than with thy juſtice run too far in ſcore,</l>
                  <l>That ſo thy goodneſs may again reſtore</l>
                  <l>Me to thy bleſſed ſelf, which cannot be,</l>
                  <l>But by thy mercies Lord alone to me.</l>
                  <l>'Twas thou didſt bring me from the loweſt duſt</l>
                  <l>To ſerve thy ſelf, not baſe, and filthy luſt.</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt implant in me a ſacred ray</l>
                  <l>Of thine own ſelf, to light the ready way</l>
                  <l>Of thy commands, which if we do purſue</l>
                  <l>With upright bearts, then ſurely will enſue</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:62740:55"/>
                  <l>Such joyes, as do accompany thy grace,</l>
                  <l>Then cauſe me, Lord, no longer to miſplace</l>
                  <l>My roving ſence, but henceforth fixt it faſt</l>
                  <l>In my deſires to follow Chriſt at laſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Make me, O God, ever to prize thy glory,</l>
                  <l>Declining pleaſures meerly tranſitory,</l>
                  <l>And teach me for to uſe this vain vain world,</l>
                  <l>As that which may again by thee be hurl'd</l>
                  <l>Into a Chaos, let me not loſe thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor the bleſt manſions of eternity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dear friends prize virtue though your blood gainſay,</l>
                  <l>Love and delight therein, 'tis the true way.</l>
                  <l>Other are by pathes, which do tend to ſin,</l>
                  <l>Much joy you'l find if that you walk therein.</l>
                  <l>Purſue it ſtrictly, 'tis a ſerious truth,</l>
                  <l>Remember your Creator in your youth.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:62740:56"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Luke 18.11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The Phariſee ſtood up and pray'd, God I thank thee I am not as other Men are.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>DId Chriſt reprove by parable theſe Men,</l>
                  <l>Which truſteth in themſelves, and rudely bin</l>
                  <l>Deſpiſers of others, in a haughty pride,</l>
                  <l>An humble ſanctity could not abide,</l>
                  <l>But overvalued in a fair pretence</l>
                  <l>Of ſelf conceit, not giving reverence,</l>
                  <l>And humility to thoſe parts they had receivid,</l>
                  <l>But boaſting of themſelves they had deceiv'd</l>
                  <l>The world, till Chriſt did ſharply them reprove,</l>
                  <l>In which he ſhew'd his mercy and his love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How proudly do the <hi>Phariſee</hi> give thanks,</l>
                  <l>He ſtands on tip-toe venting his vain pranks,</l>
                  <l>Ungrateful pride hath alter'd his diſpoſition,</l>
                  <l>Which uſed long prayers, and vain repetition.</l>
                  <l>The fits not now upon him for to pray,</l>
                  <l>He's out of tune, but opes his mouth to bray,</l>
                  <l>Not to adore his God, but commend himſelf</l>
                  <l>In ſuch proud boaſting: but alas poor elf,</l>
                  <l>That is ſo highly raviſht with his parts,</l>
                  <l>Not caring for to ſtudy divine arts.</l>
                  <l>But with ſo cold a zeal a poſture ill,</l>
                  <l>'Twere better he had bin unthankful ſtill.</l>
                  <l>He exceeded other Men in his own ſence,</l>
                  <l>In a ſuperlative kind of impudence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How largely doth he ſet forth his own worth,</l>
                  <l>Making no Apology for his filthy froth.</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:62740:56"/>
                  <l>He thanks God with a mind that's fully bent</l>
                  <l>To praiſe himſelf, 'tis rather complement,</l>
                  <l>Than prayer, he thinketh it Idolatry</l>
                  <l>To worſhip images, yet his vain folly</l>
                  <l>Makes him adore himſelf with his own praiſe,</l>
                  <l>As do the Catholick <hi>Phariſees</hi> of our days</l>
                  <l>In works of ſuperarrogation high,</l>
                  <l>And think by it ſtrait unto Heaven to fly,</l>
                  <l>Having numbred o're their beads their Ave-Mary's,</l>
                  <l>Their ſuperſtitions rights, that fouly varies</l>
                  <l>From the true Catholick Church, that bleſſed ſpouſe</l>
                  <l>Of Chriſt, whoſe ſplendid glory doth even rouſe</l>
                  <l>My ſoul, in contemplations of its love,</l>
                  <l>Which will ne're be perfected, till with Chriſt above.</l>
                  <l>Though that Rome's Juglers do pretend they can</l>
                  <l>Open, and ſhut the door to every Man,</l>
                  <l>And enjoyn ſuch pennance as Chriſt ne're require,</l>
                  <l>And teach by pilgramages, they aſpire</l>
                  <l>The heavenly Throne, by their exceſs of merit,</l>
                  <l>Thinking thereby ſalvation to inherit.</l>
                  <l>Let them forbear further to urge this ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Chriſt which ſaith, I am the dore, and life.</l>
                  <l>How nimbly our <hi>Enthuafiaſts</hi> follow their Leaders</l>
                  <l>Theſe trembling Saints, theſe ſanctimonious pleaders,</l>
                  <l>By imperious purity ſeem to reform</l>
                  <l>The world, and with an attack of words to ſtorm</l>
                  <l>The whole Creation, new model it again</l>
                  <l>And Saint themſelves new ſtile, with all their train,</l>
                  <l>And tell God plainly with their tongue and pen,</l>
                  <l>They are the elect, not like to other Men,</l>
                  <l>And railingly proclaim, that we are down hurl'd</l>
                  <l>And they the only true lights of the world.</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a pious lunacy and ſtrain</l>
                  <l>They rant, as come to Goſpel us again,</l>
                  <l>Extravagantly preſcribing religious rights</l>
                  <l>To the melancholly fancy of their ſights,</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:62740:57"/>
                  <l>And in a ſullen zeal, they think they ſhine</l>
                  <l>As Stars, counting themſelves purely divine,</l>
                  <l>Secluded from others in a peeviſh trance</l>
                  <l>Of ſuppoſed zeal, their ignorance to advance,</l>
                  <l>And proudly vent their follies with ſo much vanity,</l>
                  <l>To the loſs of all good order, and humanity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See how vain Man doth thus delude his ſence</l>
                  <l>In performance of religious reverence!</l>
                  <l>How is his heart taken Captive with ſuch wiles,</l>
                  <l>As Satan caſts before him with his ſmiles,</l>
                  <l>And make him think he's better than other Men,</l>
                  <l>When alas poor ſoul, he can but badly ken</l>
                  <l>His way aright, yet with all his might,</l>
                  <l>Urge his performance boldly in the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of his Creator, whoſe all ſeeing eye</l>
                  <l>Beholds his weakneſs, and his faults eſpy.</l>
                  <l>Humility Crowns all graces, and puts on</l>
                  <l>A comely beauty to religion;</l>
                  <l>When confidence in merit doth deform,</l>
                  <l>Moſt zealous actions done with ſo much ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>And ſecludes us from the enjoyment of that bliſs,</l>
                  <l>VVhich attends an humble zeal in happineſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Teach us, O Lord, an humble gratitude,</l>
                  <l>And ſelf donial of our ſelves, not rude</l>
                  <l>Prophaneſs to approach thy glorious Throne</l>
                  <l>Of mercy, which is our hope alone.</l>
                  <l>Oh lets not be forgetful of that power,</l>
                  <l>VVhich chaſtiſeth mortals every day and hour,</l>
                  <l>Nor pride our ſelves in works, though ne're ſo great</l>
                  <l>But humbly proſtitute before the ſeat</l>
                  <l>Of our offended God, and there confeſs</l>
                  <l>Our great preſumption 'gainſt his holineſs,</l>
                  <l>And bewail the imperfections of our ſpirit;</l>
                  <l>By ſuch an holy meekneſs we may inherit</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:62740:57"/>
                  <l>The heavenly manſions, where we may have acceſs</l>
                  <l>By faith in Chriſt and devout holineſs.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Matthew 16.26.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For what is a Man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEwitching world, how hath thy baits deceiv'd</l>
                  <l>Poor Man, by thy allurements, and bereav'd</l>
                  <l>Of pureſt comforts, for a moments pleaſure</l>
                  <l>To be ſhut out of the bleſt joyes for ever?</l>
                  <l>The enjoyment of our carnal pleaſures here</l>
                  <l>Are purchas'd, at a rate extreamly dear.</l>
                  <l>The Indian Mines are of too ſmall a price,</l>
                  <l>In value for that place where comfort lies.</l>
                  <l>All Crowns, and ſcepters, the earths higheſt bliſs</l>
                  <l>Are trifles to that infinite gloriouſneſs.</l>
                  <l>Then ceaſe thy proling humor, and controul</l>
                  <l>Thy pining cares, leaſt that thou loſe thy ſoul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet poor Man labors under miſtake,</l>
                  <l>Thinking the world his Heaven, and never take</l>
                  <l>Right aims, but with a covetous deſire</l>
                  <l>Of greatneſs, earneſtly ſtriving to aſpire</l>
                  <l>To ſome great title, or bubble here on Earth,</l>
                  <l>Which quite expireth with its lateſt breath,</l>
                  <l>And while he labors with unceſſant toil,</l>
                  <l>Is diappointed by ſome petty foil.</l>
                  <l>He frets, and fumes that he hath loſt his ſtation,</l>
                  <l>And ſo is turn'd to bruitiſh tranſmutation,</l>
                  <l>And buries his ſouls divinity in this Earth,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhould have greater happineſs after death.</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62740:58"/>
                  <l>Here this all ye that ſtudy complements,</l>
                  <l>And look no higher than the elements.</l>
                  <l>Ye gallants of the world, that are on fire</l>
                  <l>To pawn your ſouls to ſatisfie your deſire</l>
                  <l>For fading pleaſures, chief felicity</l>
                  <l>A ſeemingly delightful miſery,</l>
                  <l>Which gliſters for a time, you'l ſurely find,</l>
                  <l>They are but ſhadows, that delude the mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heark all you lofty aſpirers to ambition,</l>
                  <l>Check your proud fancies with a fair ſubmiſſion.</l>
                  <l>You that can worſhip Sathan with delight,</l>
                  <l>And do him homage with your ſtrength and might,</l>
                  <l>And glory in your luſt without controul,</l>
                  <l>And pay the immortal tribute of your ſoul.</l>
                  <l>Thy revellings will be horror in that day,</l>
                  <l>When ſad regrets will check thy ſoul, and ſay,</l>
                  <l>What profit is it for to gain the world,</l>
                  <l>And loſe my immortal ſoul, and ſo be hurl'd</l>
                  <l>Down from my lofty ſtate, to endleſs flame,</l>
                  <l>Where's dread, and horror, infamy, and ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heark you ſenſualiſts, that make diſputes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſouls are as unconcern'd as bruits,</l>
                  <l>And panteth after pleaſures ſeeming fair,</l>
                  <l>With more deſire than <hi>Camelion</hi> for air,</l>
                  <l>Thou, that wad'ſt in ſoaming floods of vice</l>
                  <l>O're whelm'd with wantonneſs at any price,</l>
                  <l>Sporting thy ſelf in the full bathes of pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Shunning that Chriſtal ſtream, divineſt treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Counting religion droſs, and do ſeem able</l>
                  <l>To correct divinity, as a very fable,</l>
                  <l>And in ſuch height of humor thy thoughts advance,</l>
                  <l>Thinking the lives of Saints a meer Romance,</l>
                  <l>Laughing at Heav'n, and that diviner light,</l>
                  <l>Keeping the worlds vain objects in thy ſight.</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:62740:58"/>
                  <l>It will bleer thy eyes unleſs thou doſt repent,</l>
                  <l>Thy looſer ways will ſuffer puniſhment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hearken thou miſer, that hath given thy eat</l>
                  <l>To the Rhetorick of a bag, thy ſoul doth chear</l>
                  <l>At the muſick of a purſe, where is thy aim</l>
                  <l>That gaze thy eyes to blindneſs at a Jem,</l>
                  <l>Wiſhing thy ſelf an Judian for ſuch pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>That thou mayſt ever dwell amongſt ſuch treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Inhabit mines, until thou art turn'd to oar</l>
                  <l>Thy hairs to ſilver, and thy heart, which poar</l>
                  <l>On the worlds filth, into a wedg of gold;</l>
                  <l>Then wilt thou be a perſon fit to hold,</l>
                  <l>Correſpondence with the Devil in the lower vaults,</l>
                  <l>Which will ſeverely ſtrip thee for thy faults;</l>
                  <l>Though thou art ſeemingly in a golden ſlumber</l>
                  <l>He'l find a time thy covetous thoughts to cumber,</l>
                  <l>With his ſevere corrections, thou wilt howl,</l>
                  <l>That thou ſo lov'ſt the world, to loſe thy ſoul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hearken ye gallants, which have loſt your ſence,</l>
                  <l>And are enamored on faſhions, with pretence</l>
                  <l>To beautifie your Limbs with better ſhapes,</l>
                  <l>Have loſt your true Ideas, are turn'd apes,</l>
                  <l>And meerly live to feed vain luxury,</l>
                  <l>With ſtudied diſhes for debauchery,</l>
                  <l>And martyr many creatures to fulfil</l>
                  <l>The unchaſt deſires of your wanton will;</l>
                  <l>Like Epicures on that abundance given</l>
                  <l>By the moſt good and bountiful hand of Heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Are your veins purer, have you nobler ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould your paſſions be full of great merits,</l>
                  <l>Abandoning a baſe, and covetous mind,</l>
                  <l>In getting wealth, which will ſcatter with the wind,</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62740:59"/>
                  <l>And breath of the diſpleaſure of the giver,</l>
                  <l>Which ſoon can blaſt our hopes and make them wither</l>
                  <l>Into a ſterile, dry, and pale complexion,</l>
                  <l>And make thee know, that thou art in ſubjection</l>
                  <l>To powers divine, that can ſtop thy career;</l>
                  <l>And make thy griping covetous purchaſe dear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could we live old, and ſtill recover ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>Not finding the miſeries of age at length;</l>
                  <l>Could we unwind time, and reverſe its wheel,</l>
                  <l>Stop the celeſtial poſts, and make them reel,</l>
                  <l>And ſet the worlds great clock far back again,</l>
                  <l>What ſhall we get by it, but trouble and pain,</l>
                  <l>Imaginary ſelicities here,</l>
                  <l>Sliding contentments, purchas'd very dear?</l>
                  <l>And when we're liſted in the diſmal book,</l>
                  <l>That accurſed catalogue of the damned, look</l>
                  <l>And ask <hi>Dives,</hi> without any controul,</l>
                  <l>What did it profit him to loſe his ſoul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh Lord, what is there in this world to prize,</l>
                  <l>And weary our ſelves with vain deſires to raiſe</l>
                  <l>A temporary felicity and name,</l>
                  <l>Which quickly vaniſheth, as a blaſt or flame.</l>
                  <l>'Tis hard to him, that's to thy law a ſtranger,</l>
                  <l>To apprehend the miſery, and danger</l>
                  <l>Of covetous deſires, the length of time</l>
                  <l>Hath made that vice a habit, and incline</l>
                  <l>Our natures to the breaches of thy law.</l>
                  <l>Oh Lord, teach me with care to ſtand in aw</l>
                  <l>Of loſing thee my God, my only pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Whom to enjoy is the divineſt treaſure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let the bleſſings thou haſt freely given</l>
                  <l>Quicken our duller ſouls, with thanks to Heav'n,</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62740:59"/>
                  <l>From whom we have receiv'd the chief promotion:</l>
                  <l>Let it not flack, but quicken our devotion,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe contemplations, not vainly rude</l>
                  <l>But with obedience, and humble gratitude,</l>
                  <l>That ſo the vanities that are here below</l>
                  <l>May be our ſcorn, but the graces with do flow</l>
                  <l>From thy abundant mercy may delight'us</l>
                  <l>To the boſom of thy Church, good Lord, unite us,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe our ſpirits, our vices to controul,</l>
                  <l>And think no profit for to loſe our ſoul.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Canticles 2.1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>I am the Roſe of <hi>Sharon</hi> and the Lilly of the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Solomons</hi> ſong, his moſt <hi>Seraphick</hi> ſtrein,</l>
                  <l>That in high, and tranſcendent raptures aim</l>
                  <l>To expreſs Chriſts love, to his Church the ſacred ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>Doth not his fervent divine fancy rouze</l>
                  <l>Theſe high paſſionate expreſſions divine,</l>
                  <l>The Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> love better than wine;</l>
                  <l>Lilly of the valleys, turtle undefil'd,</l>
                  <l>Love of delights, ſweeter than ſpices mild,</l>
                  <l>Spikenard and Mirrhe, Saphron and Frankincenſe,</l>
                  <l>All theſe alluſions, in an amorous ſence</l>
                  <l>Of divine love, as in a holy ſong,</l>
                  <l>VVith lofty ejaculations all along</l>
                  <l>In a devout harmony doth allude</l>
                  <l>In allegory, and ſimilitude.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Roſe is natures perfume, it diſplays</l>
                  <l>Its treaſures through the air unto its praiſe;</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:62740:60"/>
                  <l>It delighteth ſence both in color, and ſmell,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe odoriferous beauty none can paralel.</l>
                  <l>Other flowers (like <hi>Hypocrites</hi>) are fair of color,</l>
                  <l>And in a painted ſhew they do ſeem fuller</l>
                  <l>Of various ſhapes, but they have not the ſcent</l>
                  <l>Of that ſweet Roſe, that ſtill is fragrant,</l>
                  <l>And retains its ſweetneſs, ev'n in withered duſt,</l>
                  <l>When other flowers of Color pine, and burſt</l>
                  <l>Into a naſty ſhape, of the Roſe is made</l>
                  <l>A cordial, ſo, that it doth never fade;</l>
                  <l>It's virtues are ſtill uſeful of great price,</l>
                  <l>Of vegetables natures paradiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In this wonder of flowers, we may eſpy</l>
                  <l>Not only Phyſick but Divinity;</l>
                  <l>It wears Heaven's livery, in its beauteous color,</l>
                  <l>Natures maſter piece, nothing is fuller</l>
                  <l>Than the ſweet lovely bluſhes of the Roſe,</l>
                  <l>That Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> which all wiſedom knows</l>
                  <l>With many prickles, was his head ſurrounded,</l>
                  <l>VVith tanting ſcoffs, was his pure ſoul confoundad;</l>
                  <l>The perfumes of his prayers rais'd a richer ſmell,</l>
                  <l>Than all <hi>Arabia</hi>'s ſpices can paralel,</l>
                  <l>His divine miracles were higher ſcented,</l>
                  <l>Than all odoriferous gums, if ſublimated</l>
                  <l>Into one perfume, its a rifle to that ſweet,</l>
                  <l>That cordial poſie where the God-head meet</l>
                  <l>As join'd in one, and ſent ſuch perfume thence,</l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhould enamor our hearts with reverence,</l>
                  <l>To adore that Roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> which will never</l>
                  <l>Loſe its perfume, but will ſmell ſweet for ever.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh let us run with meekneſs, (not preſume)</l>
                  <l>After the odors of thy ſweet perfume;</l>
                  <l>And have fervent deſires for thee alone,</l>
                  <l>And for the ſtreams that do flow from thy Throne.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:62740:60"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Imprint in me ſuch rays of divine grace,</l>
                  <l>A purity capable to ſee thy face.</l>
                  <l>The greateſt perfections in creatures lie,</l>
                  <l>But a drop of tranſcendent excellency</l>
                  <l>That is in thee, let me have a longing ſtrife</l>
                  <l>To imitate the purity of thy life,</l>
                  <l>And in an humble meekneſs to ſubmit,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch indignities as thou think'ſt fit,</l>
                  <l>And when I ſhall lay down this earthy feature</l>
                  <l>I may be raiſed a renewed creature;</l>
                  <l>And be comforted with perfumes of thy love,</l>
                  <l>VVhich are prepared with the Saints above,</l>
                  <l>In the eternal paradiſe of reſt,</l>
                  <l>VVith the true Roſe of <hi>Sharon</hi> ever bleſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm <hi>119.92.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If my delight had not been in thy Law: I ſhould have periſhed in my trouble.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:61"/>
            <head>To the Honorable the Lord Chief juſtice Raynsford, upon his adding St. George's Church to the rules of the Kings Bench.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THanks noble Raynsford, for this bounteous favor</l>
               <l>To priſoners reſtrained, it doth ſweetly ſavor</l>
               <l>Of a pious clemency, thus to enlarge</l>
               <l>The footſteps of thoſe Men under thy charge,</l>
               <l>You've outdone loyal <hi>Keeling</hi> (that act we'le ſound)</l>
               <l>He'n larg'd the rules, thou giveſt us holy ground,</l>
               <l>St. George's Church, Englands Titular Saint,</l>
               <l>VVhere we may freely go, and make complaint</l>
               <l>Of our hard ereditors, and devoutly pray,</l>
               <l>That he'l enlarge his mercies in the day</l>
               <l>Of your account, we'l ſtudy to expreſs</l>
               <l>All ways of gratitude, for this happineſs,</l>
               <l>With thanks unto our Marſhal for his love,</l>
               <l>VVhich doth oblige us faſter, far above</l>
               <l>All other obligations, we'l expreſs</l>
               <l>All cordial love with humble thankfulneſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pardon Dear Sir, that I this ſilence break,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That am the meaneſt, how could others ſpeak?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:61"/>
            <head>An Elogie on the death of <hi>Edmund Lenthal</hi> Eſq: late Marſhal of the Kings Bench.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ARe priſons ſad? is't not a place of grief,</l>
               <l>To be reſtrain'd from liberty, the chief</l>
               <l>Deſire of Man, but here a comforts given,</l>
               <l>VVhen a mild keeper is decreed from Heaven.</l>
               <l>Such one we had, but ſuddenly ſnatcht hence</l>
               <l>By the impartial hand of providence.</l>
               <l>Death with his pale fac'd Envy hath bereav'd</l>
               <l>Of comfort, in which we were not deceiv'd.</l>
               <l>His carriage was obliging ſweet, and kind,</l>
               <l>Expreſſing ſtill a bounteous noble mind,</l>
               <l>And generous Courteſy, yet his care was juſt</l>
               <l>Preſerving them, that did oblige his truſt.</l>
               <l>In ſuch an harmony his acts did meet,</l>
               <l>Mixt mercy with juſtice in conſort ſweet.</l>
               <l>My meditations of Joy, and gladneſs</l>
               <l>Are turn'd to Elogies, and ſongs of ſadneſs.</l>
               <l>He's taken hence, which my ſad ſoul did chear.</l>
               <l>I ceaſe to write, ſurpriz'd with mournful tear.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:62"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:62"/>
            <head>THE TABLE Of the FIRST PART.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Philippians Chap. 4. v. 12.</label>
               <item>1. I <hi>Know how to abound, and how to ſuffer need,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <label>Job 2.10.</label>
               <item>2. <hi>In all this did not</hi> Job <hi>ſin with his Lips.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Romans 6.12. <hi>and part of</hi> 21.</label>
               <item>3. <hi>Let not ſin thereſore raign in your mortal bodies, that you ſhould obey it in the Luſts thereof: For the end of theſe things are death.</hi> 7</item>
               <label>Matthew 15.28.</label>
               <item>4. <hi>And he ſaid unto her, O Woman great is thy Faith.</hi> 11</item>
               <label>John 12.2.</label>
               <item>5. <hi>But</hi> Lazarus <hi>was one of thoſe that ſat at the Table with him.</hi> 14</item>
               <label>Geneſis 2.8.</label>
               <item>6. <hi>And the Lord God planted a Garden Eaſt-ward in</hi> Eden. 17</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:63"/>
               <label>Luke 10.25.</label>
               <item>7. <hi>And behold, a certain Lawyer flood up and tempted him, Maſter, what ſhall I do to inherit Eternal Life.</hi> 20</item>
               <label>John 11.36.</label>
               <item>8. Jeſus <hi>Wept.</hi> 23</item>
               <label>Matthew 6.33.</label>
               <item>9. <hi>But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God and his Righteouſneſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you,</hi> &amp;c. 25</item>
               <label>John 13.23.</label>
               <item>10. <hi>And there was leaning on</hi> Jeſus <hi>boſom, one of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples whom he loved,</hi> &amp;c. 29</item>
               <label>Luke 19.9.</label>
               <item>11. <hi>This day is Salvation come to thy Houſe.</hi> 32</item>
               <label>Luke 9.57.</label>
               <item>12. <hi>Lord, I will follow thee whereſoever thou goeſt.</hi> 36</item>
               <label> </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Copy of Verſe to Sir</hi> Anthony Bateman <hi>on the Death of his Daughter.</hi> 40</item>
               <label> </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Elogy on the Name and Death of the Virtuous Lady</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha Bateman, <hi>who departed this Life the Tenth of</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, 1674. 41</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:62740:63"/>
            <head>THE TABLE Of the SECOND PART.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Numbers 27.16, 17.</label>
               <item>1. <hi>Let the Lord, the God of the Spirits of all fleſh, ſet a man over the Congregation. Which may go out before them, and which may go in before them, and which may lead them out, and which may bring them in; that the Congregation of the Lord be not as Sheep which have no Shepherd.</hi> p. 1.</item>
               <label>Matthew 5.8.</label>
               <item>2. <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God,</hi> &amp;c. 6</item>
               <label>Daniel 12.3.</label>
               <item>3. <hi>And they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> 9</item>
               <label>Matthew 2.18.</label>
               <item>4. <hi>And when they ſaw the Star, they rejoyced with exceeding great Joy.</hi> 12</item>
               <label>Eccleſiaſtes 12.13.</label>
               <item>5. <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of Man.</hi> 16</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:64"/>
               <label>Matthew 8.2.</label>
               <item>6. <hi>And behold! there came a Leaper and worſhipped him, ſaying, Lord, if thou wilt, thou canſt make me clean.</hi> 20</item>
               <label>1 Kings 19.9.</label>
               <item>7. <hi>And he came unto a Cave and lodged there.</hi> 23</item>
               <label>Geneſis 28.12.</label>
               <item>8. <hi>And he dreamed a Dream, and behold a Ladder ſet upon the Earth, and the top of it reached unto Heaven, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Angels deſcending and aſcending on it.</hi> 27</item>
               <label>Proverbs 18.14.</label>
               <item>9. <hi>But a wounded Spirit who can bear!</hi> 33</item>
               <label>Matthew 24.38.</label>
               <item>10. <hi>And knew not until the Flood came and took them all away.</hi> 37</item>
               <label>Luke 7.5.</label>
               <item>11. <hi>For he loved our Nation and hath built us a Synagogue.</hi> 40</item>
               <label>John 20.11.</label>
               <item>12. <hi>But</hi> Mary <hi>ſtood without at the Sepulchre weeping, and as ſhe wept ſhe ſtooped down and looked into the Sepulchre.</hi> 44</item>
               <label>Eccleſiaſtes 12.1.</label>
               <item>13. <hi>Remember thy Creator in the days of thy youth.</hi> 47</item>
               <label>Luke 18.11.</label>
               <item>14. <hi>The Phariſee ſtood up and pray'd, God I thank thee I am not as other men are.</hi> 50</item>
               <label>Matthew 16.26.</label>
               <item>15. <hi>For what is a man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> 53</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:62740:64"/>
               <label>Canticles 2.1.</label>
               <item>16. <hi>I am the Roſe of</hi> Sharon, <hi>and the Lilly of the Vallies.</hi> 57</item>
               <label> </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Copy of Verſes to the Right Honorable the Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> Raynsford.</item>
               <label> </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Elogy on the Death of</hi> Edmund Lenthal <hi>Eſq;</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
